<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A discourse concerning supreme power and common right at first calculated for the year 1641, and now thought fit to be published / by a person of quality.</title>
            <author>Monson, John, Sir, 1600-1683.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1680</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 242 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 93 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A51170</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M2462</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R7043</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12801783</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12801783</idno>
            <idno type="VID">94067</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A51170)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 94067)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 362:8)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A discourse concerning supreme power and common right at first calculated for the year 1641, and now thought fit to be published / by a person of quality.</title>
                  <author>Monson, John, Sir, 1600-1683.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[9], 174 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for R. Chiswell ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1680.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to Sir John Monson. Cf. NUC pre-1956.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
                  <note>Marginal notes.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Monarchy.</term>
               <term>Divine right of kings.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:94067:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:94067:1"/>
            <p>A DISCOURSE CONCERNING SUPREME POWER AND COMMON RIGHT.</p>
            <p>At firſt Calculated for the Year 1641. and now thought fit to be publiſhed.</p>
            <p>By a Perſon of Quality.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>R. Chiſwell,</hi> at the Roſe and Crown in <hi>S. Paul</hi>'s Church-yard. 1680.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:94067:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:94067:2"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>THIS little following Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe, concerning the Origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of Paternal Power, and the Derivation of all others from it, with Reflections upon Regal Government, and the Relative Duties both of King and People to each other, is, for Subſtance, only a <hi>Summary Collection,</hi> from the beſt Authorities, of ſuch neceſſary and Practical Notions, as might have ſteer'd us in the moſt benight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and tempeſtuous times of the late unhappy (and almoſt unparallel'd) Rebellion, and keep us within the Bounds of Duty and Allegiance, both <pb facs="tcp:94067:3"/> to God and our King. But it loſt its uſefulneſs (being calculated for the high Diſtempers of that Age only) by miſcarrying in the <hi>Preſs,</hi> and for ſome years irrecoverably concealed, and kept from its deſigned end by one (ſince dead) who communicated to me the following Diſcourſe, which hath for ſome years layn in my hands as buried, unleſs ſomething of the like Contagion ſhould break out again, and give it a new Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, as an <hi>Antidote</hi> againſt the ſpreading of ſo popular an Infection. But now I am prevailed with, upon the ſad Proſpect of things that threaten a relapſing into the like Dangers, by <hi>Popiſh Plots,</hi> and thoſe many <hi>Sects, Diſtractions</hi> and <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions</hi> amongſt us, (ſome of whoſe Principles agree with the rigid <hi>Scotch Presbyters,</hi> and
<hi>Jeſuits,</hi> in their Tenents concerning the depoſing of Kings, and the forfeiture of their <pb facs="tcp:94067:3"/> 
               <hi>Regal Power</hi> into the People and their Repreſentatives,) to ſhew both from <hi>Scripture, Antiquity,</hi> the <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, Articles, Canons, Homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies,</hi> and <hi>Liturgy</hi> of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> which all agree with our ancient Laws and many late Acts of Parliament, That our Kings are on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſubmitted by God to the direction, not coaction of Humane Laws: (as Mr. <hi>Faulkner</hi> in his Treatiſe upon that Subject hath lately and moſt learnedly made appear:) Yet Kings are not unconfined by the Laws of God and our Kingdom, which ſet juſt bounds both to King and People, to regulate their Actions by (as a middle thing between Supreme Power and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Intereſt:) And our Municipal Laws may be ſtraiten'd or enlarg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in regard of the Soveraign's Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe of Power, but cannot influence or affect the Power it ſelf (which is of God) to alter or enervate the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture <pb facs="tcp:94067:4"/> of it: Nor can it oblige to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing,
<hi>foro divino,</hi> but what is juſt in the means, as well as good in the end, and ſafe in regard of Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Prudence: by which Rules we have much reaſon to believe our Superiours (as they yet have done) will take their meaſures, and neither countenance nor indulge the leaſt evil of ſin, to avoid the greateſt evil of puniſhment: Yet if God (for our almoſt unpardonable provocation and abuſe of thoſe many Miracles of Mercy he hath hitherto preſerved us by) ſhould ſubmit us to the impla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cable malice of our common Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies the <hi>Papiſts</hi> at home and abroad, or to Civil Commotions within our ſelves, to bring us again into Chaos and Diſorder, in which we may need ſome aſſiſtance for our Conſcientious Comportments, both with Prudence and Innocency; the enſuing Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe may be of great uſe, there being <pb facs="tcp:94067:4"/> things caſuiſtically propoſed and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved, (with modeſty and ſubmiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to others Judgments) in Relation to the late Rebellion, which may ſome way help us in other difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, if we fall under any; which that God in Mercy would avert, is the Prayer of,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your unknown Servant,</hi> &amp;c.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="discourse">
            <pb facs="tcp:94067:5"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:94067:5"/>
            <head>A DISCOURSE CONCERNING SUPREME POWER AND COMMON RIGHT.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. I.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S God is a Spiritual King, ſo Kings are Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Gods; his Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture drawn in Little, and the moſt expreſs Image of his Power, receiving (as the Wax from the Seal) all the parts and propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the Print, in the largeſt Chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cter, in which he ſhews himſelf in Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil Adminiſtrations: So as the endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of effacing any part of that juſt Power, where God hath Engraven it in <pb n="2" facs="tcp:94067:6"/> his Deputies, is a Spiritual Treaſon and Rebellion againſt God himſelf.<note n="a" place="margin">Rom. 13.</note> For not only <hi>by me,</hi> but <hi>for me, Kings Reign,</hi> ſaith God,<note n="b" place="margin">Prov. 8.15. Rom. 13.</note> in that he makes them his hand both to puniſh and protect by, and ſtiles them for that end, nurſing Fathers to the Church and State.</p>
               <p>Nor is the Stamp to be deſpiſed, though it be engraven but in Lead and Iron; the Power being the ſame in him (who by the undue exerciſe of a juſt Power, makes himſelf a Tyrant) as it is in a good King, and challenging the ſame Submiſſion and Obedience in lawful things from us: It being not the Wax, but the Impreſſion, that bears the value, as it is Gods. And therefore to wreſt the Sword out of our Soveraigns hands (the beſt of Princes) is as much as we can to diſ-enthrone God from his way of Rule amongſt us, as the <hi>Jews</hi> did in the perſon of
<hi>Samuel.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For which Reaſon our Laws give the King a kind of Immortality here, in ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing he cannot dye: becauſe his Power which is from above, paſſes, in the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendment of our Laws (by a kind of <hi>Py<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thagorean</hi> Tranſmigration) always into the next of his Line, and upon the fai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lure thereof only it Eſcheats into the People, as to the Election of another perſon to Reign, but never was, nor is <pb n="3" facs="tcp:94067:6"/> fundamentally in them, in regard of the Power by which they Govern. And the wiſeſt People do (but as a Pipe, not the Spring) derivatively paſs it into one man to actuate it, as the moſt abſolute and perfect Government, and that which God only owns. For when he ſaith, <hi>By me Kings Reign,</hi>
                  <note n="c" place="margin">Prov. 8.15.</note> he implies all other Forms of Government to derive their Pedigree only from men, not Divine In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution. They have his Permiſſion, but Kings only his Commiſſion; ſo as all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther leſſer Rivulets in the Adminiſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Juſtice in their Kingdoms, are in them, as their Spring, derivative from and ſubordinate to them: For the Supreme Power is ever annexed to the Perſons of Princes, in whom it is ſeated; the Infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour only to the Offices of ſubordinate Adminiſtrations, which are always re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſponſible to him that hath the Supreme Power. Elſe the God of Reaſon ſhould make a Body without Reaſon (a Head) to govern it.</p>
               <p>The contrary Opinion to which clear Truth, hath cauſed the ſad Tragedy of theſe benighted Times, and hath ever proved the Seminary of Anarchy and Confuſion in all States, where it hath taken root and prevailed; though it hath for the moſt part withered and periſhed <pb n="4" facs="tcp:94067:7"/> in the end, as having no true Principles of life and permanency, however for ſome time maintained by Tyranny and Oppreſſion; as may be inſtanced in moſt of thoſe Popular States that have been ſince the beginning of the World, which were but Weeds, no Plants of Gods ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting. For ſubordination of Perſons, which ariſeth by degrees, ſhould reſt when it comes to the Soveraign, or all things would wheel into a Confuſion.</p>
               <p>But God is a God of Order,<note n="d" place="margin">1 Cor.
14.32.40.</note> and as his Power made all in Number, Weight and Meaſure,<note n="e" place="margin">Wiſd. 11.20.</note> ſo his Providence up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holds all according to the ſame Model, by ſetting a kind of Hierarchy and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giment amongſt all the ſeveral Societies of the Creatures, even from the loweſt to the higheſt Story of created Beings, (ſo that levelling is contrary to his De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign) and by a ſweet ſubordination and ſymbolizing quality and affection, even amongſt Contraries, preſerves the whole.</p>
               <p>Firſt, In the Inanimate Creatures: For the Heavens have the Sun and Moon in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throned there to govern in their ſeveral Spheres, the one over the Day, and the other over the Night, which, with the Stars (though differing from one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in glory) make one uniform and glorious Structure;<note n="f" place="margin">Iſ. 60.13.</note> and though of
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:94067:7"/> ſeveral proportions, ſtates, and inequa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities, maintain a happy harmony a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt themſelves.</p>
               <p>Secondly, In the Unreaſonable Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures: As in Bees, which of all others maintain a moſt perfect Polity of Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchical Government amongſt them, and are the beſt Emblems of good Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, painful in their labour, dutiful in their life, all uniting in Obedience to the ſervice of their King, and ſupplying his weakneſs with their Wings, when he is unable to fly with his own (as ſome obſerve.) Nay all other Creatures from a Natural Principle mould themſelves into a ſociable ſubordination. Thus the Lyon is King of all the ſalvage Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the Foreſt: the Eagle of Birds. Nay even Sholes of Fiſhes, Heards of Beaſts, Flocks of Fowls, and the reſt, have their Heads and Leaders.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, In Man's Soul; by placing the Underſtanding in it as the Sun in its Orb, the Moon and leſſer Lights (as the Will and Affections) inferior to it in their Sphere and Station, to follow its Influences, and derive all their light and direction from it. Nor is it otherwiſe in the Body, which is compact of many Members, one more noble than ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, yet all united under one Head, as <pb n="6" facs="tcp:94067:8"/> ſupreme, from whence they receive Laws, and to which they pay Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence; there being not the leaſt Sinew, String, or Part unuſeful.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, In the Church, State, and all Societies; there being in all, by his Ordination, ſuperior and leſs Noble Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices; as in great Buildings, Rooms for State, others for more ordinary uſe and conveniency: In Clocks greater and leſſer Wheels, every one, like Stones in an Ark, being of equal neceſſity, though not beauty, with the reſt; yet all mak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing but one Uniform and Glorious Stru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture.<note n="g" place="margin">Iſa.
60.13.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Fifthly, In Heaven it ſelf: For there amongſt the Angels there is a <hi>Gabriel,</hi> and in other Orders Cherubim, Sera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phim, Thrones, Principalities, and Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers; teaching us that the more things draw to Unity, the nearer they are to Perfection, and Aſſimilation with God himſelf, who is not only a ſtrict Unity, but Oneneſs in himſelf.</p>
               <p>Now upon this fundamental Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and according to theſe Natural Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ductions God doth will, in his <hi>voluntas ſigni,</hi> or
<hi>beneplaciti,</hi> a Conformity to them in all things, but chiefly amongſt Men (rational Creatures, if not believ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Chriſtians) by centring all Power (of <pb n="7" facs="tcp:94067:8"/> Families, Societies, Kingdoms) in one Supreme and Paternal Head, both for perfection and permanence: So as all other Forms argue not only weakneſs in, but tend to the perverſion, nay ſubver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the Fabrick, (the ſeveral Poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies of Men would ſeem to raiſe) becauſe not agreeing to the Model, which God firſt erected in <hi>Adam.</hi> For even there he eſtabliſhed Regal and Paternal Power, that differ only in proportion, not ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militude; (it being the ſame, as a Child is a Man in little.) For all Government was virtually and ſeminally in him, though ſpreading and propagating with the growth and Generations of Men, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing firſt founded in Families, and with <hi>Ezekiel</hi>'s Waters, riſing by degrees from thence to the uniting of many, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corporating them into Societies under one Head; till at laſt many Heads did center in one Supreme, many natural Parents choſe one common Parent to them all, one <hi>Pater Patriae,</hi> to whom they ſubmitted the exerciſe of the Legi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlative Power; (which was before in eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Father of a Family, who, over his own Children and Servants, had a Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er even to Life and Death, and was their King) being guided to it both by di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctates of right Reaſon, God's over-ruling
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:94067:9"/> Providence, the guidance of his Spirit, and immediate deſignation of the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon from him (as in the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth) till he ſetled it in a lineal Succeſſion. That of Parents, Patriarchs, Kings, being but the ſame Power, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſeveral Dreſſes and Appellations, the ſame Beams of Majeſty, though reflecting ſeveral Luſters, and challenging a-like Obedience from all that are ſubjected to them, from one and the ſame Divine Right. So as the Duty of the fifth Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment had been as binding upon <hi>Adam</hi>'s poſterity in the State of Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency, had he ſtood, as upon us, though not promulgated till a thouſand years after; but there would have been none of that reluctancy and oppoſition in us, nor of that oppreſſion and irregu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larity in our Superiours, which we are now ſubjected to by our Sins, and his firſt diſobedience to God.</p>
               <p>So that I conceive it can neither be rationally, nor upon grounds of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion denyed, that all juſt Power, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially the Government by Kings, derives its pedigree from Paternal, and is an Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance of God, ſpringing out of a Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural and Eternal Principle, which hath ever been owned. Firſt, In the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emptive Precept of their perſons to be
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:94067:9"/> free from all other Power.<note n="h" place="margin">Prov.
21.3. Iſa. 10.5. Pro. 8.15. Eccleſ. 8. 1 Pet. 2. Rom. 3.</note> Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, In the deſignation of the perſon.<note n="i" place="margin">Deut. 17.15. Job.
36.7.34.30. Hoſ. 13.11. Wiſd. 6.3.</note> Thirdly, In the puniſhment of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion againſt his ſacred Ordinance.<note n="k" place="margin">Num. 16. 2 Sam. 1.4.14.15.</note> Fourthly, By the command of our Prayers for, and Obedience to them he hath ſet over us, though Wicked and Tyrants,<note n="l" place="margin">1 Tim. 2.2. 1 Chron. 12.1.
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. Jer. 29.7.25.9. Dan. 3.21. Gen. 20.27. Bar. 1.15. Mat. 22.21. 1 Sam. 24.4.6.8.9. 1 Pet. 2.27.</note> for ſince the loſs of our firſt Eſtate (wherein all ſhould have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued in a ſweet harmony and orderly ſubordination, and lived in an happy ſubjection, without any Schiſms, or mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinous irregularities) we muſt ſubmit to them, even in their <hi>Aegyptian</hi> Tasks, as the juſt puniſhment of our Rebellions a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt God, and not Rebel againſt his Ordinances.</p>
               <p>And upon theſe grounds, ſaith <hi>Opta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus, David,</hi> in fearing the Anointed, ſpared his Enemy King <hi>Saul,</hi> as he was God's breathing Image, the mortal pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture of the immortal God, a piece made for laſting, wrought in Oyl, at his Inau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guration, and not to be defaced by any hand. A preſident worthy the imitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of theſe apoſtate times, wherein mens ſpeculative Atheiſm hath made them ſuch Monſters in Wickedneſs as to attempt to depoſe the King, to root up the talleſt Cedars, to pull down and le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel all the high Mountains of greatneſs <pb n="10" facs="tcp:94067:10"/> God hath ſet up; that they might intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce and uſher in an Anarchy, or make the Bramble to Reign, bearing no Fruit but Thorns to tear and wound us; by it to efface all that is of God amongſt men, both outward Majeſty and Piety; when Regal Power (as it conveys it ſelf from the Father to the Son, to a kind of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortalizing it ſelf here) is the legiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate Iſſue of God himſelf, (deſcended from him for the good and preſervation of Men, in a ſafe and religious courſe of life) and ever bears his Stamp and Image, in regard of the Power, though the Perſons that bear it ſometimes (when they think not themſelves ſafe under the Guard of their own Vertues and Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples Affections) place their ſecurity in their ſtrength, and their happineſs ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in a Power to hurt, than in a juſt care to preſerve their Subjects, (whoſe hearts they ſhould account their beſt Treaſury and ſureſt Magazines) and ſo degenerate into Tyrants, and make that which is life to become death to us (as S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith in another caſe). Yet even then they are to be ſubmitted to upon rational grounds, and that Government is to be choſen before any other, though <hi>Caeſar</hi>'s Image and Superſcription were not ſtampt upon it by Divine Ordinance:
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:94067:10"/> All others being but Counterfeits of it, and of a more baſe allay, (little Money in great Medals,) when this, like the nobleſt Coins, contains much in little.</p>
               <p>But as there are many ſnares beſet the Throne of Majeſty, (though there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing on Earth ſo near the Deity, nor ſo commodious for the well-ordering of Humane <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ocieties:) the beſt Princes ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times fall into great perplexities and dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulties; becauſe perhaps wanting the
<hi>Meander</hi>'s Thread of free and honeſt Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monitions and Advice to extricate them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, or by having their Ears dull'd with Flattery (that Court-Earwig) or too tender to endure the too ſearching air of an ingenuous ſpirit, which ſpeaks his own Duty, not his Soveraigns Affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions.</p>
               <p>Man having loſt the felicity of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Law to himſelf, that ſhould keep him from tranſgreſſing the limits of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qual Juſtice to any other, hath cauſe to ſubmit himſelf to Monarchical Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as the moſt ſilken Rein and gentle Bit he can take on to reſtrain him in his deviations and ſtartings out of the right way of common Equity, though under an ill King, rather than a Popular State, or Elective Kingdom, which make a great ſhow, and glorious oſtentation <pb n="12" facs="tcp:94067:11"/> of Liberty, though it is but Paint artifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially laid on (like <hi>Abſalom</hi>'s<note n="m" place="margin">2 Sam. 15.</note>,) a Var<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh of Piety and publick Utility, only to hide a Thraldom: For they are the greateſt Servitudes imaginable, when ſubmitted to, and are accompanied with the greateſt Miſchiefs (like the back-doors in great Houſes) having many in-lets to Diſorder, more than the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and poſſeſs only<note n="n" place="margin">Hoſ. 8.4.</note> an Uſufructu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ary and Gubernative Power to Rule, without any juſt Propriety in the Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſlative, which none can pretend to, but ſuch as are Commiſſioned from God, according to his revealed Will, and poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſs their Crowns by a lawful Civil Right; as in this Kingdom ſince the Conqueſt.</p>
               <p>For, firſt, (as a good Author obſerves to me) Succeſſion in one Man (a King) diſarms the Ambition of all daring and aſpiring Spirits, who would be at the Stern (every one a Pilot) though they wrack the Ship through their Civil Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions. Nay it takes away that ground of Emulation, that might juſtly be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong men of one level (equals in Worth, Birth, and ennobled Vertues) to aſcend the Throne, and hinders the fomenting of Factions amongſt thoſe, that in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Governments have the Suffrages to
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:94067:11"/> Elect to the Supreme Power, or any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther eminent Place.</p>
               <p>Secondly, It prevents the exhauſting of the Publick Treaſure many times, which thoſe temporary Rulers are ever guilty of, holding it unnatural not to feather a Neſt for their own young ones, (though by the pluming all others) and a weakneſs to live like Gods, and dye like ordinary Men: And many Drains new-made, you know, will in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſibly take away more water than one Stream, where it is always full Sea.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, It cures the windy ſwelling Tympany of Pride in thoſe temporary Rulers, that are always in travel to bring forth a thing of their own ſhaping to ſucceed them in their Government, though againſt the Rules of it; (and who ſo fit a Pourtraict as ſome of their own Iſſue or Kindred?) as may appear in ſome of the <hi>Roman</hi> Emperours, and moſt Popular States, who (rather than fail in it) have nurſed and raiſed up their deſign, not only with the Milk of Flatte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and many vitious practices and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgences, (the making of Factions; by the toleration of all evils) but fed and brought it to perfection with the blood of Civil Wars, and exhauſting their Countries Treaſure in Bribes and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſeneſs, <pb n="14" facs="tcp:94067:12"/> ever legitimating all undue ways to keep what they have no Title to, but by their Crimes; even to the ſubverſion of Religion, with <hi>Jeroboam,</hi> not only in making Calves for (but of) the People, never wanting ſpecious preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces to prop and uphold their rotten Pile, though not truſting to them. For you ſhall always find ſuch Uſurping Tyrants maintain the Martial Sword, when once unſheathed, to Oppreſſion; that the Sword might maintain them, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tect them againſt the juſt revenge of an injured People.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, Elective and Popular States, as a breach in a Sea-bank, let in a deluge of confuſion, (the Effect of Arbitrary Power) which, in ſuch a tottering con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, is never maintained, but by grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter wickedneſs (as <hi>Cataline</hi> ſaid) than that which firſt formed it: And therefore read all Stories, and you ſhall find that few Common-wealths, and ſuch King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms, have ever been happy for preſent felicity or continuance, not having had the poor comfort of being ruined by their Gods, but Men, by their Servants, not Maſters; or elſe, <hi>Aetna</hi>-like, they have been always waſting themſelves by fire in their own Bowels; Pride, Envy, and Avarice ever blowing it up into the <pb n="15" facs="tcp:94067:12"/> flames of a Civil War, where there are many equal Competitors or Pretenders to Soveraignty: So as not the beſt and fitteſt (who will not aſcend by ſuch wind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſteps) but the moſt potent gain thoſe Dictatorſhips; all which are juſt Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments for endeavouring to form the Weapons of our ſtrength, draw the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>del and Materials of Government out of our ſelves; Our own Reaſons, when clouded with Paſſion, Intereſt, and Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice, not conſulting with Religion; nor ſuffering God, that made the Houſe, to order it.</p>
               <p>For when we ſo leave our Religion for our Reaſon, we loſe both Reaſon and Religion. Which would oblige us to think our ſelves ſafer under the prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of God's Ordinances, in whoſe hands are the hearts of Kings, (the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraints of Conſcience,) than by any out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Force or Humane Providence with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out them. For by God's appointment Gods they are, and (as the Head, from whence all Veins diſtribute their Spirits equally, with reſpect to the higher and inferiour Members) in a Body Politick maintain a happy Commerce and Traf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fick betwixt it and the moſt remote parts: Direction and Protection deſcending whilſt Love and Obedience aſcend.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:94067:13"/>But beſides this, have we not more Reaſon to expect happineſs from a lineal Succeſſion in Kings, than the Election of Men to that or any other Form? When, inſtead of a Muſhroom, the growth of one night, (that ſprings perhaps out of the baſeſt Excrements, and of ſuch a lazy deſpondency of Mind as ſinks him into the next degree to a Beaſt, making him to have no deſigns generous and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to carry him beyond his own felici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty) we ſhall have one whoſe blood is derived to him through the Veins of many Noble, Heroick, and Vertuous Progenitors, who becomes all Spirits, refined from thoſe mariſh and terrene parts, which weigh down, or raiſe Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pours to eclipſe others of a more baſe Extraction, when they aſpire to great and generous actions.</p>
               <p>Nay this makes Princes live in their Poſterities, when dead, and brings re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence to the very Swadling-Cloaths and Cradles of their Succeſſors, as if they might Command Obedience before they could ſpeak, (as <hi>Barclay</hi> obſerves.) Nor can it be imagined but that their high and vertuous Educations ſhould infuſe a Gallantry into them above Pride (ſaith the ſame Author) having been always uſed to the greateſt outward Obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vances, <pb n="17" facs="tcp:94067:13"/> and, by being ſo, placed above all Contempt; ſo as it cannot but nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh in them higher thoughts than ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Hatred, Emulation, or Avarice produces, and free them from thoſe ſelf-reflections private Families are ſubject to, (as I have touched before;) becauſe they are ſecured againſt the fears of Competi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors in rule, and have ſetled ſupplies for their wants, enjoying in the Stream what others have but in the Ciſtern, and conveying it to their poſterity, as their Patrimony and Inheritance; making them many times Heirs of the Goods of their minds, as well as Bodies, and to reap the Harveſt, and crop of all their noble and growing Deſigns; (which, as Seed ſown by them, will not perhaps ripen into Fruit in many years after.) For it is probable ſuch will manure and nurſe up with Induſtry and Care what their Predeceſſors planted.</p>
               <p>Nor can the Infancy and weakneſs of a Prince be of ſo bad a Conſequence as a Popular State; becauſe he is then in Guardian to the moſt able and faithful Great Ones, or the great Council of the Kingdom it ſelf, which the wiſeſt and beſt of Kings do always make uſe of to ſteer their Actions by. Nay, if that Government ſhould for a time degene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate, <pb n="18" facs="tcp:94067:14"/> it is more likely ſoon to recover, and unite again in one, when broken in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to many Intereſts, equally tainted with malignant Influences, and ſelf-ſeeking deſigns.</p>
               <p>But not, with the Mole, to loſe my ſelf upon the face and ſuperficies of things, when I may make my Habita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſafe by digging deeper, (the beſt Foundations being loweſt laid,) I ſhall return to my firſt deſign, and go to the Root of all, endeavouring to ſhow that Regal Power was a Plant of Paradiſe of God's own ſetting, and ſo of Divine Right; and that the Sword which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends with the Scepter, and raiſes it ſelf upon the ruines of juſt Power, cannot be free from all the fore-mentioned ſad Effects, which muſt eclipſe the Glory of every Nation, and leave it no Trophies but ſuch (as <hi>Pyrrhus</hi> once ſaid of his Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctories) as would undoe the Conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, and appear beſt when ſhrouded under the Vail of true Repentance, and offered up again by a holy Reſtitution to the Altar, from which they were ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crilegiouſly taken: Such ſucceſſes being our greateſt vanquiſhments, and leaving us no juſt Title to make other uſe of our unjuſt acquiſitions. Though
<hi>Abiſhai</hi> would have preached <hi>David</hi> into a Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:94067:14"/> and Rebellion at once, upon no bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter grounds than Gods delivering <hi>Saul</hi> into his power,<note n="o" place="margin">1 Sam.
26.9.10.24.12.</note> had he not learnt a better Divinity, meaſuring his Actions by Gods revealed Will, not outward Events; knowing he there writes in Characters, ſhewing us his hand only, but not letting us at all read his meaning in them.<note n="p" place="margin">Deut. 9. 2 Chron. 13.8.</note>
               </p>
               <p>But to be a little more plain and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpicuous in ſo neceſſary a Truth, I ſhall endeavour, as in an Epitome or Index to thoſe many large and learned Diſcourſes that have been written upon this ſubject, to ſum up the beſt Collections I can, and to digeſt them into this Method.</p>
               <p>Firſt, To ſhew that Kings are the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance of, and hold their Supreme Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er from God, not Man; and that they are only accountable to him for the uſe of it. Secondly, What that Power is, and how limited. Thirdly, That re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance in the Subject againſt that Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er is in no Caſe warrantable. Fourthly, What Duties Kings owe to their Subjects. Fifthly, What the Subject's Allegiance conſiſts in to them.</p>
               <p>Firſt, That Kings are the Ordinance of God; contrary to that of the <hi>Roma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſts</hi> and our new <hi>Statiſts. Reges coro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nas &amp; ſceptra ab hominibus recipiunt, &amp; <pb n="20" facs="tcp:94067:15"/> ad eorum placita tenent.</hi>
                  <note n="q" place="margin">Bellarm. lib. 5. de Rom. Pon. cap.
7.</note> So <hi>Bucha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nan</hi>
                  <note n="r" place="margin">De Jure Reg. apud Scotos.</note> 
                  <hi>Populus Rege praeſtantior etiam &amp; major: Rex igitur cum ad Populi Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicium vocatur, minor ad majorem in jus vocatur.</hi>) For they are called God's by In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution and Appropriation from God: For, <hi>By me Kings reign,</hi> ſaith he,<note n="s" place="margin">Prov. 8.15. Rom. 13. 1 Pet. 2. Jo. 14.30. Hoſ. 13.11. Wiſ. 6.13.</note> and <hi>with my holy Oyl have I anointed him;</hi>
                  <note n="t" place="margin">Pſ. 89.20.</note> not only to rule by, but for God too, as the moſt expreſs Character of him up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Earth: Which made him lead his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple by the hand of <hi>Moſes</hi> and
<hi>Aaron;</hi> (one Chief in Civil matters, the other in things concerning the Prieſt's Office, though with ſubordination.) Not one People by many Rulers, (much leſs the Ruler by the People) but by one in Chief under the conduct of God himſelf, and by his Authority; as may appear in that, and all other Inſtances of Regal Power. So as Kings are to be reveren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced and diſtinguiſhed from others, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of that Natural and Paternal Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er God planted in <hi>Adam,</hi> and cauſed im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately after to derive from many Heads into one Chief, in one place; a cauſe of the diviſion of the Nations amongſt the Sons of <hi>Noah,</hi> as Monarch of the whole Earth after the Flood.<note n="u" place="margin">Gen. 10.32.</note> So as Kings are Gods, and to be o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beyed.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:94067:15"/>Firſt, In regard of their Attribute of Power: <hi>For where the word of a King is, there is Power;</hi>
                  <note n="w" place="margin">Eccleſ. 8.4.</note> 
                  <hi>that he might be fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed;</hi>
                  <note n="x" place="margin">Pro. 24.21.</note> 
                  <hi>and who may ſay unto him, what doſt thou?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, In that of Mercy: <hi>For there is Mercy with him that he may be feared; in that he beareth not the Sword in vain,</hi>
                  <note n="y" place="margin">Rom. 13. 1 Pet. 2.</note> 
                  <hi>but doth whatſoever pleaſeth him,</hi>
                  <note n="z" place="margin">Eccle. 8.3. 1 Sam. 8.</note> in giving gracious Indulgen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, In regard of Majeſty and Soveraignty: <hi>For God expreſſeth them by thoſe higheſt Titles,</hi> (ſaith
<hi>Calvin</hi>)<note n="a" place="margin">Inſt. 4. l. cap. 20.</note> 
                  <hi>to affect us with the awful ſence of the Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity it ſelf, and our Duty to them, in put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the Glory of his own name upon them.</hi> For<note n="b" place="margin">Pſ. 82.6.</note> 
                  <hi>I have ſaid ye are Gods;</hi> and not only ſo, but decreed and ordained it, it ſhall be ſo, even Gods before Men (though Men before God.) 1ſt, By Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logy. 2dly, Deputation. 3dly, By Participation. Thus <hi>Tertullian.</hi>
                  <note n="c" place="margin">Lib. ad Scapalum</note> 
                  <hi>Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rillus,</hi>
                  <note n="d" place="margin">Ep. ad Thro. pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fix. lib. ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſ. Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian.</note> 
                  <hi>Chryſoſtom,</hi>
                  <note n="e" place="margin">Hom. ad Pop. An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioch.</note> 
                  <hi>Gregory,</hi>
                  <note n="f" place="margin">L 9. De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret. 1 Tit. 3.3.</note> which is the reaſon of thoſe high Titles of Prerogative the ſacred Word ſtyles them with, after the
<hi>Iſraelites</hi> rejection of <hi>Samuel,</hi> (as that of God, in regard of the immediate rule they were to exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe over them) after their deſire of a King; for before the Power was not veſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <pb n="22" facs="tcp:94067:16"/> in the Perſon of any, but miniſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rially only in regard of Exerciſe, which ſtill proceeded from immediate and Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Directions: But after he placed the Power in the perſon of the King<note n="g" place="margin">1 Sam. 8.</note> to be accounted for only to God<note n="h" place="margin">Pſal. 51.</note> as a puniſhment of the Peoples Rebellion a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him, and deſire of innovating their Form of Government. Nay, he then dignified the perſon of the King with all the Attributes of Majeſty, to ſhow that he left the power of ordering all things to the conduct of Man (though with an over-ruling Providence) which before derived immediately from him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf; ſo eſtabliſhing Monarchy, but no other Form of Government by any Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Commiſſion. And then he ſtyles them,</p>
               <p>Firſt, <hi>Children of the moſt high,</hi>
                  <note n="i" place="margin">Pſal. 82.</note> to ſhow from whom the Inheritance of their Crowns deſcends, and that they are a middle thing, as it were, between Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and Earth, like a Cloud in the Air, above Man, and below God.</p>
               <p>Secondly, <hi>The Lords Anointed,</hi>
                  <note n="k" place="margin">1 Chr. 4.18. 1 Sam. 24.16.</note> and ſo Sacred by Conſecration.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, <hi>The Angels of God,</hi>
                  <note n="l" place="margin">2 Sam. 14.20.</note> in regard of Wiſdom.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, <hi>The Light of</hi> Iſrael,<note n="m" place="margin">2 Sam. 21.17.</note> in regard of comfort and influence.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:94067:16"/>Fifthly, <hi>The Kings of Nations,</hi>
                  <note n="n" place="margin">Luk. 12.25.</note> in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of their vaſt Empire.</p>
               <p>Sixthly, <hi>Nurſing Fathers, and Nurſing Mothers,</hi>
                  <note n="o" place="margin">Iſa. 49.23.</note> in regard of their tender Care and Affections to their People, and to ſit in the Throne of God,<note n="p" place="margin">2 Sam: 3.1. 1 Chron. 29.23. 2 Sam. 12.7. Iſa. 62.3.</note> in regard of protection, as the Spring and Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain from whence all Juſtice doth flow. And therefore the Queen of <hi>Sheba</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged of
<hi>Solomon,</hi> That he was King, (as hath been ſaid) not only from, but for God, to do Juſtice and Judgment<note n="q" place="margin">2 Chron.
9.8.</note> for ever;<note n="r" place="margin">Job. 36.7.</note> 
                  <hi>Cuſtos &amp; moderator utriuſque Tabulae.</hi> And not only ſo nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther (though theſe are great Preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives) but even as God, (two Conſtella<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions in one Hemiſphere, God and Man, neither eclipſing the light of the other) For ſo ſaid <hi>Jacob</hi> to his Lord <hi>Eſau,</hi>
                  <note n="s" place="margin">Gen.
33.10.</note> 
                  <hi>vidi faciem ut faciem Dei,</hi> that is, ſaith the
<hi>Chaldee,</hi> (as a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verend Divine obſerves) God in him, as he was the Prince. For, <hi>Rex eſt ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mata Imago Dei,</hi> ſaith St.
<hi>Auguſtine.</hi> And for this Cauſe it was ſaid of <hi>Moſes,</hi> (who, with the Patriarchs and Judges, had the exerciſe of Regal Power ſucceſſively be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Saul</hi>'s Inauguration) the Scepter he held was God's, not his own, <hi>virga Dei in manu;</hi>
                  <note n="t" place="margin">Exod. 17.9.</note> God and <hi>Caeſar</hi>
                  <note n="u" place="margin">Mat. 22.21. Prov. 24.21.</note> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to be obeyed <hi>tanquam conjunctae Perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nae.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:94067:17"/>Nor is it St. <hi>Peter</hi>'s calling all Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracy an Humane Creature, and St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s ſtyling it God's Ordinance, contradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory one to the other. For one ſpeaks of the Authority,<note n="w" place="margin">Rom. 13.</note> the other of the Laws or Ordinances made by ſuch as he hath impowered to it, whether it be the King or thoſe Commiſſioned by him, which St. <hi>Peter</hi> calls Humane Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces moſt properly, becauſe made by Men, but intends not the King himſelf, as if he were made by the People,<note n="x" place="margin">1 Pet.
2.</note> nor his Power, but the exerciſe of it; which, in regard of Circumſtance, as Time, Place, Actings, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> is by Cuſtome or Municipal Laws become Humane.</p>
               <p>And now, after ſo great Light hath ſhined into the World, is it not ſtrange that Men ſhould ſeal up their Eyes, and chooſe to walk in darkneſs of Errour? ſhould trace the Paths of Diſobedience and Rebellion, and by a daring Impiety heaping of one ſin upon another (as the Gyants of old did <hi>Pelion</hi> upon <hi>Oſſa</hi>) ſhould mount this Throne of God by force and violence<note n="y" place="margin">1 Chron.
29.23.</note> to overthrow and diveſt him of all his Regalia and So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraign Power on Earth, pulling the Crown from his Head, the Scepter and Sword from his Hand, in the Perſon of our Sacred King, who as the ſum and
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:94067:17"/> recapitulation of the Virtues of all his Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deceſſors, or as ſo many Lights in one Conſtellation, ſhows the Glory and Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtre of all; when a Heathen by the Light of Nature, even
<hi>Ariſtotle</hi>
                  <note n="z" place="margin">1 <hi>Eth. c.</hi> 2.</note> as well as <hi>Calvin</hi>
                  <note n="a" place="margin">4 <hi>Inſt.</hi> 20.
<hi>Sect.</hi> 33.</note> did ſee ſomething Divine in the Officers of Governours, who are called<note n="b" place="margin">Sap. 6 4.</note> 
                  <hi>The Officers of God's King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>From whence the Schools conclude, That any the leaſt Irreverence to a King, as to queſtion our Obedience to him, may juſtly be called Sacriledge. And ſince Sacriledge is a violation or taking away of ſomething that is Holy, it is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vident that the Office and Perſon of a King is Sacred; ſo as one obſerves, Thoſe Men that are moſt Sacrilegious againſt God and his Church, are moſt likely al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways to offer Violence to the Honour and Perſons of their Princes, as too late experience hath taught us; and to deny themſelves the greateſt Bleſſing<note n="c" place="margin">Jer. 22.34. Num. 23.21. Iſa. 49 22, 23.</note> to introduce the greateſt Curſe, Licentiouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Confuſion.<note n="d" place="margin">Prov. 28.2. Iſa. 3.5.</note>
               </p>
               <p>All which ſad Effects are but the airy Off-ſpring of a Platonick Speculation, a wild and untaimed ſeemingly wiſe Folly, in affirming that the People are in their Repreſentative above the King; contra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry to St. <hi>Peter</hi>'s Doctrine,<note n="e" place="margin">1 Pet.
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 13.</note> our known
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:94067:18"/> Laws (as may be ſeen in <hi>Bracton,</hi> and all our ancient Sages) the Oaths of Supre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macy and Allegiance, which they have ſworn; and his juſt Title, being ever acknowledged by all, <hi>Carolus</hi> (but)
<hi>Dei Gratia,</hi> Charles, <hi>by the Grace of God,</hi> not Election nor Suffrages of the People. Though were it admitted that (in ſome places, as in Elective Kingdoms) or here in caſe of Eſcheat, (if there were none living that by lawful deſcent were right Heir of the Crown) the choice of their King were in the People, they can only hold forth the Perſon to the Power, if God have ſo in his Providence ordained it,<note n="f" place="margin">Deut.
17.15.</note> not give the Power to the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon; which is not habitually in them, (though by them mediately not imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately) conveyed, but in God's Uncti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Approbation of the perſon. For Power (like the Soul in the Body, when reduced to its firſt Element) returns to God that gave it. And as in the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of Biſhops, though the choice ſometimes was perhaps in the People, God was the Author, and other Biſhops, by laying on of hands and Prayer, the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediate Inſtruments only of conveying the Power of their Miniſterial Function to them, as an indelible Character, which their firſt Electors could not efface; nor <pb n="27" facs="tcp:94067:18"/> any (unleſs it derived from the Supreme Civil Magiſtrate, under whom they liv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed) juſtly ſuſpend in the Exerciſe; in that the Power doth ever derive from God, and by them.</p>
               <p>But for further illuſtration we will conſider it in the more familiar Inſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of free Elections. And firſt in Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porations, as in a Model, or hand con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted (which is but expanded, and the more ſtretched out in the higheſt Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernments) where the Commons pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound the Perſon for the ſucceeding Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour, the Repreſentatives chooſe, and the Kings Power inveſts, without which Act the reſt are but Cyphers without a Figure; but having once <hi>Caeſar</hi>'s ſtamp and Image upon it, it becomes legiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate, current, and of value; ſo as none can clip or efface it to leſſen his Authority (much leſs diſplace the Magiſtrate) but orderly, by the Power that ſet him up without much Crime, Rebellion, and hazard of damnation.<note n="g" place="margin">Rom. 3. 1 Pet. 2.</note>
               </p>
               <p>A ſecond illuſtration is, That the People by free Votes chooſe their Repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentatives in our Parliaments; yet the Power, by which they Elect, and that of the Elected, is derived from the Kings Writ; ſo as they cannot for any miſcarriage, or breach of truſt in the
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:94067:19"/> Perſon recal their choice, or make a new Election in any caſe, without a new Warrant from the Crown, but do be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come inſtrumental in conferring that which is not at all inherent in them, as may more fully appear in the applicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of thoſe ſimilitudes to Kings where they are Elected; in that Almighty God, how tyrannous ſoever they prove, uſes them but as he did <hi>Aſhur,</hi> for the Rod of his Anger,<note n="h" place="margin">Iſa.
10.5.</note> when he gives a King in his Wrath,<note n="i" place="margin">Hoſ.
3.</note> like <hi>Saul,</hi> to ſcourge the Rebellions of a people, not leaving them any juſt Power to depoſe him, or any remedy, or other appeal, than to him in Prayer:<note n="k" place="margin">1 Sam. 8.18.</note> In that his Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence orders all Actions and Events, and ſuffers no evil of puniſhment, without intitling himſelf to it; <hi>For there is no E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil in the Land, but I have done it,</hi> ſaith he: And therefore he accounts repining as impatience, reſiſtance by force Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion againſt himſelf. For, as the Apoſtles were Chriſts, Kings are Gods Miniſters upon Earth, in as near a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation. Nay himſelf, as it were, ſhowes that all ſuch Arrows are ſhot at them, wound him, when Chriſt ſays, Saul, Saul, <hi>why perſecuteſt thou me,</hi>
                  <note n="l" place="margin">Act. 9.4.</note>
               </p>
               <p>And thus God expreſſes it both in <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> his caſe,<note n="m" place="margin">Num. 16.</note> where he made the dull
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:94067:19"/> and patient Earth (the common Hack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney to all injurious trampling) the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere Avenger of his diſhonour; and ſo in
<hi>Samuel</hi>'s,<note n="n" place="margin">1 Sam. 8.</note> though even then by the fore-deſignation of God,<note n="o" place="margin">Deut. 7.15.</note> the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples free Election was confined to <hi>Saul,</hi> the man that he did chooſe<note n="p" place="margin">1 Sam 9.15, 16, 17.</note>: For till then God did rule by immediate direction and revelation, thoſe he appointed to be their Governours, and would not total<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly caſt them off for their revolt, but ſtill continued his goodneſs to them, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven in his Indulgence of Anger; not leaving them to a factious and tumultu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Election, but ordered it by imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate command to the perſon he had fore-appointed, till he had ſettled the ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion in <hi>David</hi> and his Seed:<note n="q" place="margin">1 Sam. 16.</note> By it ſhewing his diſ-allowance of all popular and diſorderly Elections; for even there where he permitted their concurrence in chooſing the perſon, in whom all Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er ſhould habitually reſide, and from whom its Actual Adminiſtrations ſhould derive; he ſuffered them only to aſſiſt <hi>Samuel,</hi> in holding forth the Wax which he had appointed to ſet his Seal and I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage upon, but not to give any Impreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</p>
               <p>Nor can it rationally be imagined by any man, that is a Chriſtian, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgeth <pb n="30" facs="tcp:94067:20"/> the Sword to be Gods, and that he that ſheds Man's Blood, without his Commiſſion, is guilty of Murder, how a power of Life and Death ſhould be collated by any Community of Men, to one or more, when neither <hi>diviſim</hi> nor <hi>conjunctim,</hi> they have power over their own, or one anothers lives: Nor could ever any pretend to it, (unleſs Parents and Heads of Families, by Divine, Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural and Paternal Right) but when de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rived from God the other way, and by his Commiſſion exerciſed. Yet the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple may in ſome ſence be ſaid to be the Pipe by which (not at all the Spring from which) the Power is derived; the Hand that holds the Burning-Glaſs to the Sun, no cauſe of thoſe Rayes of Power that ſhine upon it, and are contracted in it; or as the Men that lay out the dry Bones (as the Prophet did) whileſt God breaths the Spirit of Government, and animates them for Action: In which we muſt next conſider,</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:94067:20"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. II.</hi> What Power Kings have, and how limited.</head>
               <p>AS I have endeavoured to make it appear, by what hath been ſaid, that all Power is Originally, Fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damentally and Vertually flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from God, and abiding in the King only as its Ciſtern and Receptacle, from whence it is conveyed to us by many Pipes of ſeveral ſizes. Our inquiry muſt be how it is limited in it Self or Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: For reſolution wherein we muſt go to the Standard of the Sanctuary, the Holy Scriptures; and there we ſhall ſee, That when God firſt gave a King in his Wrath,<note n="r" place="margin">1 Sam. 8.</note> the cauſe of it was the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples being not ſatisfied with the Regal Power God did exerciſe over them in his Vice-Royes and Deputies before; but diſtruſting God Almighty, when they ſaw
<hi>Nahaſh,</hi> King of the Children of <hi>Ammon,</hi> come againſt them, that he would not ſuddenly provide for their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverance, they would have one in readi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs always to go up and fight for them. Which diſtruſt or deſpair of theirs, who <pb n="32" facs="tcp:94067:21"/> had found ſo many miraculous Delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rances under God's Government, was that which ſo highly diſpleaſed God; and not ſimply the deſire of a King) yet they neither deſired to caſt off God's Laws, nor his chooſing the Perſon, as in <hi>Saul:</hi> nor is it ſaid that the Kingdom of God is caſt off at the Election of
<hi>Saul;</hi> but they deſired more ſenſible Evidences of Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty and Glory, becauſe <hi>Samuel</hi> held not forth the outward Pomp, Splendour, and Majeſty of Heathen Kings, but (as a Type of Chriſt, whoſe Kingdom was not of this World) with Humility as well as Power. Upon which God gave them a King, after the manner of other Nations,<note n="r" place="margin">1 Sam. 8. Dan.
5.18.19.</note> but withal commanded <hi>Samuel</hi> to let them know what kind of King they deſired, even <hi>[Jus Regis]</hi> and that he ſhould rule by abſolute and unli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mited Power, in regard of Man, (how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever he may want the immediate dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction and over-ruling Grace of God) though not for want of a Rule for dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction,<note n="s" place="margin">Deut 17.2. 2 Sam. 23.3.</note> in that<note n="t" place="margin">2 Sam. 22.3.</note> he that ruleth over men muſt rule as in the fear of God,<note n="u" place="margin">Ezek. 46.16, 17, 18.</note> and not oppreſs the People. For no King can do that <hi>[de jure]</hi> juſtly in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of his Office and Commiſſion; yet from thence implying a Tyrant ſhould be exempt from all account to Man, and <pb n="33" facs="tcp:94067:21"/> free from any force or reſiſtance, though he be exorbitant, and that Subjects are in ſuch caſes denyed all Appeals but to God; as may be proved out of <hi>Samuel.</hi>
                  <note n="w" place="margin">1 Sam. 8.18.</note> 
                  <hi>Nay, againſt ſuch a King there is no riſing up,</hi> ſaith
<hi>Solomon.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note n="x" place="margin">Prov. 30.31. Eccleſ. 8.</note> To which <hi>Calvin</hi> agrees in his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment upon that place; for againſt Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rannical Acts in a lawful King he allows no reſiſtance in theſe words,
<hi>Nec quic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam adverſus Reges movere, licet Tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nidem exerceant, &amp; rapinis ſint graves ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditis, nullam<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> nec Dei, nec aequi recti<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionem habeant:</hi> For, <hi>Non veſtrum eſt his malis mederi; hoc tantum eſt reliquum Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mini opem implorare.</hi>
                  <note n="y" place="margin">Inſtit. l. 4. c. 20.</note>
               </p>
               <p>But though we find <hi>[Jus]</hi> a Right of ſecurity for Kings againſt all violence (as I have obſerved) we find no <hi>[Jus]</hi> right for Tyranny and Arbitrary Power, which is to be eſteemed a ſin, for which Kings are to account to God; and the rather becauſe they are above all Humane Judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cature, and only under him, as the People are under them: For which God ſtyles him, <hi>Lord of Lords,</hi> and <hi>King of Kings.</hi> And upon this ground, though <hi>David</hi> had ſinned againſt <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>riah,</hi> firſt in defiling his Bed, then in murdering his Perſon, (both to be puniſhed with Death by the Law of God, in any com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon <pb n="34" facs="tcp:94067:22"/> man) but moſt in making him ſin againſt his God, in Drunkenneſs, (by one ſin to conceal another) he yet was never queſtioned for thoſe black Deeds, but in his Confeſſions to God cryes out,<note n="z" place="margin">Pſal. 51.</note> 
                  <hi>Againſt Thee, Thee only, have I ſinned, and done this evil in thy ſight: Quia cum Rex ſim</hi> (ſaith the Gloſs) <hi>quamvis contra <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riam deliquerim, non habeo tamen in ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra qui me judicet, ſed te in Caelo agnoſco Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicem meum.</hi> (So alſo in Pſalm, <hi>Miſerere mei Deus,</hi> written by <hi>R. P.</hi> and dedica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to <hi>Thom. de Trugillo.</hi>) And <hi>Joannes Lorinus</hi>
                  <note n="a" place="margin">C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>mm. in Pſal.
50.</note> ſaith to the ſame ſence upon thoſe words, <hi>[Tibi ſoli peccavi] quia ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus poteſt cognoſcere aut punire peccatum ip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſius, qui Rex eſſet nec ſuperiorem haberet.</hi> Thus St. <hi>Hierom</hi>
                  <note n="b" place="margin">Ep. 22. &amp; 4. Caſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſia Col. 20.</note> 
                  <hi>Quia non fuit qui arguere auderet Regem, qui poſſet accuſare &amp; punire: <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>tpote cum quo nullus poteſtate par, nedum major eſſet, non eſt qui audeat dicere Regi Apoſtata, vocare<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> Judices im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pios,</hi>
                  <note n="c" place="margin">Job 34.18.</note> 
                  <hi>niſi velit ipſe impius haberi (ut Chryſoſtomus, ac Nicetas, &amp; hoc loco Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rillus notant.)</hi> In which accord <hi>Cyprian</hi>
                  <note n="d" place="margin">Ad No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vatian.</note>
                  <hi>Ambroſe,</hi>
                  <note n="e" place="margin">Serm. 16. iu Pſ. 118.</note>
                  <hi>Clemens Alexandri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi>
                  <note n="f" place="margin">4 Storm. c. 6. Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racramata 1 Summae de Eccl. 1. Q. 92. ad 6.</note> Though <hi>Baronius</hi> in his An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nals, ſpeaking of the <hi>Sanhedrim (Anno Chriſti</hi> 31.
<hi>Num.</hi> 10.) ſaith, That <hi>Herod,</hi> though a King, was cited thither for his Cruelty: But it was falſe by the Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:94067:22"/> he quotes,<note n="g" place="margin">Joſeph. Antiq l. 14. c. 17.</note> in that <hi>Joſephus</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies him to be a King then, but ſaith, That he was a Subject to <hi>Hyrcanus:</hi> For when <hi>Herod</hi> was cited by the <hi>Sanhedrim,</hi> his Father <hi>Antipater</hi> was living, (and <hi>Hyrcanus,</hi> then High-Prieſt and Prince in State and Right) who gave him notice of the Confederacy againſt him in the Synagogue; ſo as
<hi>Baronius</hi> in that In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance (as Biſhop <hi>Mountague</hi> infers) on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſhewed his good meaning to extend Papal Authority over Kings. Yet
<hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rod,</hi> in revenge of it, took away their lives that convented him when he came to the Crown.</p>
               <p>And it is a Tradition among the <hi>Rab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bins,</hi> That when King <hi>Jannaeus</hi> was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded by the <hi>Sanhedrim</hi> to appear and anſwer before them, thoſe who pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed to ſummon him, were ſhrewdly puniſhed by the Angel <hi>Gabriel;</hi> which although it were perhaps fabulous, yet it is certain that the <hi>Jews</hi> in their
<hi>Talmud</hi>
                  <note n="h" place="margin">In Cod. Sanedrim c. 11.</note> have it as a confirmed Maxime; <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gem ſuum non judicari, nec cuiquam licere in eum teſtimonium dicere.</hi> The King was not to be judged or accuſed by any, (according to that of <hi>Solomon,</hi>)<note n="i" place="margin">Prov.
17.26.</note> in that they are not Children of the moſt Voi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, but of the moſt Higheſt; the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples approbation ſerving only <hi>ad pompam,</hi>
                  <pb n="36" facs="tcp:94067:23"/> but not <hi>ad neceſſitatem,</hi> in a King's Coro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation. A Reaſon why <hi>Melchiſedech</hi> was ſaid to have no Father in regard of his Kingly Office; becauſe Regal Power is an emanation from the Deity it ſelf.</p>
               <p>Yet this exemption from all Humane Powers here, doth not exempt them from the higheſt Power; for then moſt properly, <hi>Judgment is mine, and I will repay,</hi> ſaith the Lord. <hi>Be wiſe now there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore o ye Kings, be learned ye that are Judges of the Earth; ſerve the Lord with fear, and rejoyce before him with reverence,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>leſt ye periſh from the right way, if his Wrath be kindled, yea but a little.</hi>
                  <note n="k" place="margin">Pſal. 2.10.11.12.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Nay it is ſometimes his greateſt ſeveri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty not to let them be puniſhed here,<note n="l" place="margin">Hoſ. 4.14.</note> that they might bear the weight of his Wrath hereafter.<note n="m" place="margin">Heb.
1.12.</note> In that every ones account muſt be according to the Talents they receive, and Great Ones you know are hardly cleared. Nay Experience tells us, That he who falls from a high Scaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold or Pinacle, is in more danger of ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recoverable hurts, than he that ſlips upon a level ground: So as this Opinion is no ground for Licentious Exorbitances in Kings, but a juſt ſtating of the queſtion concerning Regal Power, which Origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally is one and the ſame in it ſelf, in all States where it is, though in many pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:94067:23"/> and according to ſeveral Forms li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mited and regulated in regard of Exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe and Execution only; which I ſhall endeavour to make yet more clear, though <hi>veritas in profundo</hi> (as one ſaith) Truth lyeth not in the ſurface and ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficies of things, but is almoſt buryed un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Rubbiſh of falſe Opinions, or corrupted in the ſteam, before we come to the Fountain it ſelf; and being much obſcured by Clouds of Errour, hath ſome <hi>(veriſimilia)</hi> plauſible mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtakes received and digeſted by wanton Stomachs, which do <hi>morbum alere, non hominem.</hi> But it proves a Monſter when pertinaciouſly held; For then the truth of God is detained in Unrighteouſneſs:<note n="n" place="margin">Rom. 1 18.</note> And therefore I will go with St. <hi>Baſil</hi> to the Mine (which was the Prophet's and our Saviour's advice) to ſearch the Scriptures,<note n="o" place="margin">Joh. 5.29. Iſa. 8.20.</note> and endeavour to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the Vein of Truth, as it lyes there, where we ſhall find that all things (even Hell it ſelf) ſtand by a ſubordination; and that God did firſt ſettle it here in <hi>Adam,</hi> then <hi>Moſes,</hi> from them to be derived to all poſterities; wherein we will farther conſider the Power, and then the Regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of it.</p>
               <p>And firſt for the Power. As, <hi>Sapiens ſemper incipit a fine,</hi> ſaith the Philoſopher, <pb n="38" facs="tcp:94067:24"/> in that the end ſets all a-working; let us conſider how God in the conveying it out of himſelf, for Adminiſtrations in the Political and Civil World, did pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marily intend the due ordering of things by it, according to the rules of Juſtice, Piety and Religion, that all might concen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in Gods Glory and Mans Good; Order, Truth, and Juſtice being the only Founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and Pillars of Government. For as in the leſſer World of mixed Bodies, due tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per and moderation of parts, and in the rational World Tranquillity of Soul by the ſubordination of inferiour Faculties and Paſſions to the Soveraignty of Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, preſerves them; ſo in the great World propriety and enjoyment of our juſt and native Rights, with puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Offences, (which the mind of the Law, rule of Juſtice and Right, the meaſure of all things according to Equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and Reaſon under the Supreme Head) is that which preſerves a happy Harmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny and ſweet Society amongſt men.</p>
               <p>And for this end God gave his firſt Commiſſion to
<hi>Moſes</hi> only, even Regal Power (which before was Natural and Paternal in <hi>Adam</hi>) both for expedition in Affairs of State, which could not be acted by many, and the prevention of Factions and Schiſms, that Popular
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:94067:24"/> States are always ſubject unto; but this under certain Fundamental Rules (though he had immediate Revelation) to ſhape himſelf by, yet with an abſolute Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, where Gods Law did not reſtrain him, to be derived to all Kings for ever; who ſtill are, or ought to be, the Depoſitories of that Supreme Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority; as to make War and Peace, to call and diſſolve Aſſemblies both in State and Church Affairs; which (as the greateſt Eſſentials of Regality<note n="p" place="margin">Num. 10.1, 2, 8. and 29.1.</note>) were only Originally in God himſelf, but ſince exerciſed and practiſed by all ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding Kings, as may appear by multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes of Scriptures<note n="q" place="margin">Joſ. 1.17. and 34.18. 1 Chro. 15. &amp; 23.3.6. 2 Chro. 15.14. &amp; 20.21. &amp; 25.5. &amp;
34.31.32.33.</note> and the Stories of all Ages; ſo as none durſt in former times have refuſed to come when called by them,<note n="r" place="margin">Num.
20.13.</note> though for matters of Conſcience, (or a <hi>Diana</hi>) unleſs ſome <hi>Demetrius,</hi> or Crafts-man led on the Rout, as one obſerves upon the Text.<note n="s" place="margin">Acts 19.4, 23, 36.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Nor is this only of Divine Inſtitution, but founded in Nature, as hath been ſhewed, (in that all the Conjugations of Sinews and Strength meet in the Head, the Fountain of Motion, from whence all the Members derive their Operati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons) and practiſed among the Heathen, by the Light of that Law only, as in <hi>Pharaoh,</hi>
                  <note n="t" place="margin">Gen. 41.44.</note> and the Character God <pb n="40" facs="tcp:94067:25"/> gave the <hi>Jews</hi> of their Kings when they asked one after the manner of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.<note n="u" place="margin">1 Sam. 8.</note> From whence we may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, That <hi>Moſes</hi> had all Monarchical and Abſolute Power, (in reſpect of the <hi>Jews</hi> radically in him, even <hi>Jus Regale</hi>)<note n="w" place="margin">Deut. 33.3.</note> and was in <hi>Rectitudine Rex,</hi> as well in Name as Power;<note n="x" place="margin">verſ. 4.5.</note> which after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards was transferred upon
<hi>Saul,</hi> as a Puniſhment to the People for rejecting it in thoſe God had appointed to conduct them by the immediate aſſiſtance of his Holy Spirit; But that he ever left (or gave) Commiſſion for the exerciſe of this Power to a Community, can never be ſhewed.</p>
               <p>Yet here God leaves not Tyrants to their own unbridled range and rapine (as the Wild Beaſts of the Foreſts) without a rule both of Direction and Obligation, (as hath been ſhewed) which ought to be the meaſure of all juſt Power,<note n="y" place="margin">Deut. 17. Gen. 17.6.49.10.</note> (though he did foretel what did or ſhould follow;) for he no ſooner eſtabliſhes the Throne upon <hi>David</hi> and his Seed, but does it under a Covenant of Obedience,<note n="z" place="margin">2 Chro. 6.16.7.17. 2 Kin. 11.6. Ezech.
37.12,</note> by the fail of which his Crown was forfeited to God only, not Men, upon any Compact or Condition betwixt him and the People.<note n="a" place="margin">2 Sam. 5.</note> Yet had there been a ſtipulation between them, the viola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion <pb n="41" facs="tcp:94067:25"/> thereof could not have evacuated his Power, no more than a Fathers ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity<note n="b" place="margin">1 Tim. 6. 1 Pet. 2.18.</note> can cancel a Child's Obedience, it being only a peculiar of God's, <hi>by whom Kings reign</hi>
                  <note n="c" place="margin">Prov. 8.15,
16.</note> to remove and ſet them up;<note n="d" place="margin">Dan.
2.21.</note> which made <hi>Nazianzen</hi> (in his firſt Oration againſt
<hi>Julian</hi>) condemn thoſe that would not depend upon God's Providence, and expect the execution of his Counſels upon Wicked Princes, whoſe hearts are in his hands, and <hi>He turneth them whitherſoever he liſteth;</hi>
                  <note n="e" place="margin">Prov. 21.1.</note> but would be their own Gods and Deliverers; when Tyrants are God's hand upon us for our Sins: (So
<hi>Peter Martyr,</hi> upon <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. out of <hi>Dan.</hi> 4.) Nay,
<hi>Calvin</hi> ſaith, It is our fault if ſo great a Bleſſing be turned into our Puniſhment; it being but a juſt retaliation for our diſobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to God: For, <hi>[Secundum merita po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puli diſponuntur corda Rectorum]</hi> accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Deſerts of a people the hearts of Governours are diſpoſed, and the juſt Judge puniſheth the faults of the Prince many times upon them that had cauſed him to offend, ſaith St.
<hi>Grego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry.</hi>
                  <note n="f" place="margin">Ep. l. 2. Ep. 6.</note>
               </p>
               <p>So as we may juſtly invert that of <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid,</hi> a King, to his People, and ſay, as Wicked Subjects of a pious Prince; <hi>Let thy Judgments, O Lord, fall upon us;</hi> but <pb n="42" facs="tcp:94067:26"/> that innocent Lamb, what hath he done! that he ſhould become a Sacrifice for us, who ought to ſacrifice our ſelves for him? ſince it is our Rebellions againſt Thee that have occaſioned in us this Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion againſt ſo good a Prince,<note n="g" place="margin">2 Sam. 21.1.</note> that by them thou mighteſt take occaſion to be the more ſevere in thy Judgments up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on our Nation.</p>
               <p>However, let us conſider, there is ſomething good in the higheſt Tyranny and ever to be preferred to <hi>Anarchy:</hi> For when there was no King in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> every one did oppreſs his brother, and act after the Luſt of his own heart, not only rejecting their Civil but Spiritual Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to God;<note n="h" place="margin">Jud. 17.2.17.6.18.</note> whereas the Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion of a Tyrant moſt commonly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends but to ſome; ſo as the good or evil Eſtate of <hi>Iſrael</hi> ſeemed to depend upon the having, or not having a King. And having thus ſhewed how the Power of Kings is abſolute, without dependency upon their Subjects, though limited in regard of their Soveraign God, I ſhall proceed to the exerciſe of it, and ſhew how that may be bounded and moderated by Compact, the Indulgence of good Princes and municipal Laws.</p>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="43" facs="tcp:94067:26"/>
                  <head>What that Power is, and how limited.</head>
                  <p n="2">2. I ſay as God is Goodneſs and Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and every perfection in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, ſo he communicates of them in ſome degree to all, though moſt to Kings, (his moving Statues upon Earth) eſpecially of thoſe Attributes which moſt concerns the diſpenſation of Mercy, Juſtice and Judgment to the World. For Kings are <hi>maxime &amp; proxime,</hi> ſeconds to God (as <hi>Tertullian</hi> ſaith) above all others, and as it were, his immediate Deputies upon Earth, to Govern us according to Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of Common Equity, and his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed Will, and ſuch other Rules as the Indulgence of good Princes (from whom all other ſubordinate Powers derive,<note n="i" place="margin">Exod. 18. 1 Pet. 12.</note> as the Moon borrows her Light from the Sun) many times ſubmit themſelves to: For thus, though Monarchical Power be the ſame in root in all Kings, it doth not ſpread nor grow to one and the ſame height in regard of Exerciſe, but is with the free determination of their own Wills limited, <hi>ab externo,</hi> by ſome poſitive Law or Cuſtome, which only obliges ſo far as the Law extends, and to that always, except it be in Caſes of extremi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and viſible neceſſity; ſo as this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraint <pb n="44" facs="tcp:94067:27"/> is Moral and Legal in it ſelf, and in regard of mixture of perſons with the King many times in the Exerciſe (not Supremacy) of his Power.</p>
                  <p>From whence proceed the Voluntary Suffrages of all thoſe he hath joyned with himſelf in the fabrication of this Government, as in the making of Laws in our Parliaments. But this Indulgence of Kings ought to be always free, never forced; Kings having ſometimes the Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligation of an Oath they ſubmit to, to bind their Conſciences, but never of a Militia to bind their Hands, if <hi>Caeſar</hi> have his due. For though in Democra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical and Ariſtocratical Common-weales the practice be contrary, we muſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider them only as Governments of Gods Permiſſion, as a puniſhment upon a Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; (for, <hi>For the Tranſgreſſion of a Land many are the Princes thereof,</hi>
                     <note n="k" place="margin">Prov. 28.2.</note>) and not of his Ordination, but differing as much in Conſtitution, as a ſick and a ſound man, weakneſs and perfection, and are as a Dwarf in nature, if not a perverſion of it.</p>
                  <p>For the Power of Arms, with other things for protection, (which none elſe ought to aſſume) are ſo eſſential to the being of a King by Divine Inſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on (who owes protection to his people
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:94067:27"/> from all violence Foraign and Domeſtick, as well as they him Obedience) as he cannot diveſt himſelf of them; becauſe they are Fundamental and Inherent in his Office, and one of thoſe Principles out of which it is elemented:<note n="l" place="margin">Num. 10. Deut. 33.3.4. 1 Sam. 8.
1 Pet. 2.</note> Other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe he bears the Sword in vain, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther but the Scabbard, when others have the Weapon, with Endeavours to ſheath it in his Bowels.</p>
                  <p>Nor is it more impious than unreaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable for to affirm men can convey more than they are inveſted with, or that any ſhould delegate a Power over others lives, that hath not an immediate Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion for it from God, ſince no man hath Power over his own, nor can ſhed Blood (though under the outward For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>malities of Juſtice) without being Guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Murder, having no juſt Calling to it; the uſurpation of an unjuſt Power being much worſe than the moſt Tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nical uſe of the Sword can be in the hands where God hath placed it, even in Kings, and ſuch as act by Commiſſion from them.<note n="m" place="margin">1 Pet. 2.13, 14. Ge. 9.5, 6.</note> So that, as our Saviour ſaid to <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, All they that take the Sword ſhall pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh by the Sword,</hi>
                     <note n="n" place="margin">Mat. 26.</note> becauſe drawn with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the conſent of the lawful Magiſtrate;<note n="o" place="margin">Mat. 22.20. Job 19.11.</note> and if we once come but to ſay, with the Sons of <hi>Belial,</hi> Who is <hi>Saul</hi> or <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid,</hi>
                     <pb n="46" facs="tcp:94067:28"/> that we ſhould ſerve them, that of the
<hi>Atheiſt</hi> will ſoon follow<note n="p" place="margin">Job. 26.</note> Who is the Lord that we ſhould ſerve him; in that thoſe that reject his Ordinances, or act not according to them, renounce God; and then no Superiour will be owned, but their own Luſts, which al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways poſſeſſed the Throne, when <hi>Iſrael</hi> had no acknowledged King,<note n="q" place="margin">Judg. 17.</note> and produced the Effects of Beaſts, not Men.</p>
                  <p>For as in all Popular States there are many Eyes to diſcern what is beſt, ſo there are many Heads to contrive their private Deſigns, many Ambitions to ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie, many Luſts to obey, many In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juries to revenge, many Mouths to fill, (and many Hands to fight for Sin's Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire but Man's Slavery:) Whereas a good King will reſtrain thoſe miſchiefs, and in all juſt things make <hi>Salutem Populi ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>premam Legem;</hi> believing he cannot con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſcend too much to the correſponding Affections of the People: In that the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of the King ſhould be like the Dew upon the Graſs,<note n="r" place="margin">Prov. 19.12.</note> to nouriſh and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſh them, and make them produce Fruits of Obedience to him; it being in the Body Politique, as in the Natural, an equal mixture of thoſe Principles, out of which they are elemented, an even <pb n="47" facs="tcp:94067:28"/> poyſe of humours, a due regulation of all the Powers, (in regard of exerciſe) with ſymbolizing qualities in each to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards one another, that preſerves a State. Upon which grounds the happy conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution of our Kingdom, according to the Rules of Equity, is founded in three Eſtates, each having a Negative Voice, that none might be obliged to any Law, but by their own Suffrage; for in our Laws (as in ſounds) the Harmony of all makes the Muſick.</p>
                  <p>So as a middle temper, between Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme Power and Common Intereſt, is that of which our Parliaments are funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentally compoſed, which have the Legiſlative and Supreme Power (conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering the King as a part of them) for the making of Statutes, as a meaſure be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween both, (as Nerves of a Body Poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tique) and to be as Bonds of a Civil Life; in that (like the Center in the Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference) they do, or ought to ſtand e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qual to all parts, and (with the Pin in the Balance) upright, to weigh unto every one their due according to Juſtice and Equity; That for the King's weighty Care and Protection of us, we might pay him an ingenuous Subjection, not Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitude but Obedience.</p>
                  <p>Now though a Derivative Power can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not <pb n="48" facs="tcp:94067:29"/> ſet new bounds to Soveraign Power, it may and ought to ſtand to keep thoſe (the Soveraign Power hath aſſented to by a Law) in all ways, but force: Prayers and Tears, in Extremities, being, as St. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> ſaith, the only Weapons we have Commiſſion from God to uſe. For in ſuch Caſes, (if they prevail not)<note n="s" place="margin">1 King. 8. 1 Sam.
8.18.</note> we muſt bear the Indignation of the Lord whatever it be, becauſe we have ſinned againſt him; the ſubmiſſion of his Will being the only way to compaſs our own,<note n="t" place="margin">Pſal.
37.</note> and to be protected by him in the greateſt miſeries that can fall upon a State,<note n="u" place="margin">Iſa. 43.2.</note> in that he is the Lord, and beſides him there is no Saviour<note n="w" place="margin">verſ.
11.</note> who makes the Army and the Power to lie down together, and to riſe up no more.<note n="x" place="margin">verſ. 17.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>Thus all Magiſtrates, as in the <hi>Septem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viri</hi> of the
<hi>Medes</hi> and <hi>Perſians,</hi>
                     <note n="y" place="margin">Dan. 6.14. Eſdr. 1.19.</note> are Bounders in the Exerciſe of (but are no Sharers Originally in) the Supreme Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, which is ever to be ſubmitted to, though not obeyed in contrary to Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine,<note n="z" place="margin">Act. 5.29.</note> and ſometimes Humane Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onal Laws:<note n="a" place="margin">Phil. 4.</note> For the juſt execution of which, Magiſtrates <hi>diſtributive</hi> are to take care, as the two houſes <hi>congregative &amp; conjunctive</hi> are in the making or repeal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of them. And thus, and no other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe is Supreme Power to be regulated; <pb n="49" facs="tcp:94067:29"/> though there are a Rebellious People, <hi>Which ſay to the</hi> Seers, <hi>ſee not, and to the Prophets, propheſie not unto us right things, ſpeak ſmooth things, and Propheſie Deceits,</hi> &amp;c. and, <hi>Cauſe the Holy One of</hi> Iſrael <hi>to be forgotten before us.</hi>
                     <note n="b" place="margin">Iſa. 30.9, 10, 11.</note> And therefore I ſhall proceed to the third part, and ſpeak a word of reſiſtance in the Subject againſt the Soveraign Power.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. III.</hi> That Reſiſtance in the Subject, by force, againſt his Lawful Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate, is in no Caſe Lawful.</head>
               <p>AS the great World (even the whole frame of Nature) ſtands by a wiſe and apt combination of ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Beings ſo contempered by Divine Providence, as all agree in a ſubor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinate Obedience to make up one entire Body without any Reluctancy, Strife, or Rebellion againſt the ſuperiour and firſt Mover, though they are ſometimes ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed even to the Interruption of the whole courſe of things, and unhinging of many goodly pieces of it, as it were involuntarily, (as at the time of Our
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:94067:30"/> Saviour's Sufferings, when all the whole Creation ſeemed to have Compaſſion of him, except Man, for whom only he ſuffered; the glorious Sun withdrawing its light to put on blacks, and the dull Earth trembling under the weight of our Sins.)</p>
               <p>So likewiſe Man, as a Rational and the nobleſt of all God's Creatures, ſhould much more obſerve the Law of his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker, even the whole Oeconomy or Model of Government ſo deeply imprint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in his Soul, where Reaſon is enthron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for Soveraign, as a Beam or Linea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of God himſelf, (who is the only King of Kings upon Earth) to ſuppreſs and not ſuffer any exorbitant and tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>multuous riſing of the lower Paſſions and Affections to carry it to any exorbitancy, nor to indulge it to them, which ſtill ought to obſerve a regular motion in their own Sphere, and leave the ſupe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rior one to God's ordering in all their Irregularities. In that it is he alone that is the firſt Mover in, and ſole Orderer of all Humane Affairs upon Earth, (for though the Obliquity of all ill Actions be from us, the Natural Power of doing any thing is from him) by it to ſhew us, as by a clear light, the abſolute ſubmiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on (which is our Paſſive Obedience) we <pb n="51" facs="tcp:94067:30"/> owe our Lawful Soveraign, though Wicked, with the active in lawful Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands; yet not for themſelves, but the Lord's ſake, and as his Ordinance;<note n="c" place="margin">Rom. 13.2 1 Pet. 2.13.14 15.</note> for we are not to revile them, no not in upbraiding words.<note n="d" place="margin">Ecc. 8.4. Ex. 22 28. Act. 23.5. 2 Pet. 2. 2 Tim. 3. Jud. Epiſt.</note> And if we muſt not ſpeak evil of the Rulers of the people, <hi>a majore,</hi> we may much leſs bind our Kings with Chains, and our Nobles with Links of Iron, (which only is God's Prerogative) though they be Heatheniſh and Tyrannous; which made
<hi>David</hi> always Loyal to <hi>Saul,</hi> in all his Perſecutions. (though<note n="e" place="margin">1 Sam. 24.</note> a Tyrant by the abuſe of Power, not Uſurpation,) even when he himſelf was anointed of God, and choſen to ſucceed the other:<note n="f" place="margin">1 Sam 16.</note> And this he performed as an Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to God: (for, <hi>The Lord forbid that I ſhould do this thing,</hi> ſaith he,<note n="g" place="margin">1 Sam.
24.6.</note>) to whom only his appeal lay againſt <hi>Saul;</hi> though he was guilty of Murder, Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, Oppreſſion, Witchcraft, and the greateſt Crimes; becauſe that by his Holy Oyl (which is ever uppermoſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt all Liquors) God did deſign his Soveraignty and Superiority above all others, and made him capable of reſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving a charge only at the Divine Tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal.<note n="h" place="margin">1 Sam. 24.12.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="52" facs="tcp:94067:31"/>And St. <hi>Paul</hi> in his time commanded no leſs Obedience to <hi>Claudius,</hi> in whoſe Reign he lived, (as
<hi>Baronius</hi> conjectures)<note n="i" place="margin">1 Tom. 11. An.
45.</note> knowing that a <hi>Claudius,</hi> a <hi>Nero,</hi> or a
<hi>Cyrus,</hi>
                  <note n="k" place="margin">Iſa. 45.1.</note> becauſe of the odour of that Oyntment of Inauguration, are to be loved, never to be rejected by their Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects: For God's Commiſſions to Kings are <hi>[durante beneplacito]</hi> during his plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, (who can by millions of ways take away their Aiery Beings (the only dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference between Sleep and Death) with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out an unnatural Parricide, or the riſing of their People, if he think fit to eaſe them of ſuch a ſervile condition as cruel Tyrants bring upon them) and not <hi>quam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diu ſe bene geſſerint,</hi> by it to make their Subjects Judges of their Actions, who are only lyable to the Directive (not Coactive and Coercive) Power of Laws. For as the Moral Law to the lively and true Members of Chriſt, they are only a Rule to order and guide (not to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn) Kings, though, as an <hi>Aſhur,</hi> the Rod of God's Wrath, the King ſhould ly heavy upon his People in himſelf, or by inferiour Powers.</p>
               <p>Much more therefore ought we to bear the Yoak of Chriſtian Princes, (eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially in ſuch a mixed Government as ours, wherein the King <hi>de facto</hi> may <pb n="53" facs="tcp:94067:31"/> invade our Liberties, but cannot with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out conſent of both his Houſes, <hi>de jure,</hi> change the Laws,) and much better in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure Tranſient Acts, than a Model of Man's framing, which will be always ſubject to Arbitrary Changes. And thus <hi>Calvin</hi> underſtands<note n="m" place="margin">Inſt. 4.20. Nu. 27.</note> what was im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed upon the <hi>Jews</hi>
                  <note n="n" place="margin">1 Sam. 8. Jer.
27.</note> not to be <hi>pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiare mandatum</hi> to them, but general,
<hi>cuicun<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> delatum eſt Regnum ei ſerviendum,</hi> when he ſays,
<hi>Ex quibus apparet ſubditos Regibus nec poſſe nec debere adverſus ipſos quicquam movere, licet tyrannidem exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceant.</hi> So as by his ſence the higher Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er<note n="o" place="margin">Rom. 13.</note> is the Power above Subjects, and only below the higheſt Power of all, (even God) which St.
<hi>Paul</hi> there expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes in the ſingular number often, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare this Regal and Supreme Power to be in the King, and all others derivative from him, if St. <hi>Peter</hi>'s be a good Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment upon it,<note n="p" place="margin">1 Pet. 2.13.15.</note> where he ſtyles the King as Supreme. For,
<hi>Rex non debet eſſe ſub homine ſed ſub Deo &amp; Lege,</hi> the one for direction, the other for puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: Under the Law, as a Rule; under God, as Judge of his Actions:<note n="q" place="margin">Eccle. 8.</note> which made <hi>David</hi> be put in Ballance with all the People;<note n="r" place="margin">2 Sam. 18.3.</note> for their telling him he was worth ten thouſand was to be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood of all: As in <hi>Jude,</hi>
                  <note n="s" place="margin">verſ. 14.</note> where <pb n="54" facs="tcp:94067:32"/> God's coming at the laſt Judgment is ſaid to be with ten thouſand of his Saints, inſtead of all, as is expreſſed by the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Zachary.</hi>
                  <note n="t" place="margin">c. 14. v. 5</note>
               </p>
               <p>And therefore that now received (but much abuſed) Maxime, That the King is <hi>major ſingulis, univerſis minor,</hi> can in its juſt latitude be meant only of the Origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal and Fundamental Right the People had in the firſt Election of the Perſon to the Power (where God did not immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately appoint him) not of giving the Power to the Perſon; for that is only from God, who claims the Sword as his own Right, and will not have it uſed by any hand, to which he conveyes it not by Humane (which is always accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panied with Divine) Right. And ſo it is to be eſteemed of according to God's revealed Will, who never inſtituted o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Government for Civil Regiment, but commands it (as other Spiritual Fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions in the Church) for Divine Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtration; there being no happy State in the perfection of Government with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a Lawful King; nor Glorious Church without Epiſcopacy. (Nor can any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther juſtly intitle themſelves to the hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Divine Precept or Inſtitution for their Practiſe.) So as if others have the
<hi>eſſe,</hi> they want the <hi>bene eſſe</hi> of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:94067:32"/> though men have found out many other inventions for both.</p>
               <p>And therefore whoſoever reſiſt their Lawful Rulers by force, purchaſe to themſelves Damnation, as they op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe the Ordinance of God, though in wicked ones, (yet Rulers if wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, are to expect the ſame Reward.) <hi>For,</hi> ſaith <hi>Bucer, the word Subject ſignifies a fall and abſolute Subjection to Rulers, and forbids all force;</hi> becauſe, as another ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves,<note n="u" place="margin">upon Tit. 3.</note> to be ſubject is to obey; and the rather becauſe in the worſt Government of any King, the protection we receive from it doth more than ballance the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils we perhaps might ſuffer under ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Form.<note n="w" place="margin">Jud.
17.</note> 
                  <hi>And therefore,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>let every Soul</hi> (as well Spiritual as Temporal) <hi>be ſubject to Kings,</hi> (as the beſt Form of Ruling) in whom by Gods Ordination the Habit of all Power re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides (though the Act be in his Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters) in all Cauſes (though not over them, but their Perſons) as Supreme; (and <hi>qui tentat accipere, tentat decipere,</hi> ſaith <hi>Bernard.</hi>) So as none, but thoſe that ſwear falſly in making a Covenant, and fear not the Lord, will ſay what ſhould a King do to us?<note n="x" place="margin">Hoſ. 10.3, 4.</note> When, as it is in the Fable of Beaſts, all ſhould agree to chooſe the Lion for their King, rather <pb n="56" facs="tcp:94067:33"/> than have none: For, <hi>praeſtat unum ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mere quam multos.</hi> And therefore it is probable God in his Providence (to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent <hi>Inter-regnums,</hi> the miſchiefs that did follow upon having no King<note n="y" place="margin">Judg. 17.</note> and the tumultuouſneſs of Popular Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions) did ſettle Regal Powers in a ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion of Blood firſt in <hi>David,</hi> though promiſed to
<hi>Abraham,</hi> and propheſied of to <hi>Judah.</hi>
                  <note n="z" place="margin">Gen. 17.6.49.10. 1 King. 11.14. Jer. 41.1. 2 Chro.
22.10.</note>
               </p>
               <p>So as that Poſition of the <hi>Romaniſts,</hi> and our new
<hi>Statiſts, (Simeon</hi> and <hi>Levi,</hi> Brethren in Iniquity) that Princes are made by the People, becauſe made by the conſent of the People; and that People Originally make the Magiſtrate, not the Magiſtrate the People, is moſt falſe; yet thus <hi>Parſons</hi> (in his <hi>Dolman</hi>) and many others, broached that ſediti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Poſition, with divers of the ſame nature, to ſtir up the People againſt Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> perſwading them they had power to diſpoſe of the Crown, and might depoſe her, and transfer the Kingdom to the Infanta of <hi>Spain;</hi> and ſince that time both <hi>Junius Brutus, Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chanan,</hi> and others, like
<hi>Sampſon</hi>'s Foxes, have joyned with the <hi>Jeſuits</hi> in this, though ſtanding as Extreams in other things.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="57" facs="tcp:94067:33"/>But this Opinion (as a moſt Reverend Divine of our Church hath ſhewed) hath no Foundation in Reaſon nor Scripture. <hi>For,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>from the Canon, the Powers that be are ordained of God.</hi> And how can man give the Sword (the power of Life and Death over others) that hath not power to take away his own life by any Natural or Divine Right? (For as hath been ſaid, no man can convey to another what he hath not himſelf:) So that Power, whereſoever placed, is an Emanation from God immediately, and ſo to be obeyed only where orderly ſetled and conſtituted; <hi>For the Powers that be,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle,<note n="a" place="margin">Rom. 13.</note> (whether by Election or Inheritance, Compact or juſt Conqueſt being once legally eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed) <hi>are of God,</hi> and may not be diſturb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by their Subjects, in a way of Arms, or Force, for any Impiety, Tyranny or Oppreſſion whatſoever; they having no Power over the perſon once inveſted in, and diſcriminated by the Power all Kings have by God's Ordination; for in all changes men can only chooſe the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, but never give the Power. As Sil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver that is mere Plate, if it be tendered for exchange, may be taken or left at the liberty of him, to whom it is offered; but when once ſtampt by the King, and <pb n="58" facs="tcp:94067:34"/> Coyned becomes currant and not to be refuſed. Or as Acts of Parliament, whileſt Voted by the two Houſes, have to this time been only Conſents, but after the King's concurrence Statutes that bind the perſons that Voted them, and all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers; and not to be altered by them without his aſſent: So in Governments, or Governours, as ſoon as any are creat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by man, whether Kings Elective or by Succeſſion, even St. <hi>Peter</hi>'s Humane Creatures are by St. <hi>Paul</hi> called God's Ordinance,<note n="b" place="margin">Rom.
13.</note> and not to be reſiſted nor altered at the Will of the Electors, who irrevocably part with their own Right, as the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Servant (by boring) made himſelf a Slave.</p>
               <p>For if there remained in them a Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er dormant, to over-rule and unmake them, whom they have once ſubmitted to, then where were decency and order?<note n="c" place="margin">1 Cor. 14.</note> Nay what Tumults, Diſorders, and Maſſacres would ariſe from it, when Revenge would remove the one, or Ambition, Faction, and the like, ſet up another, to compaſs their own ends? (like <hi>Herodet</hi> a <hi>Perſian</hi> King, who being a cruel Tyrant, when he could not find out a Law to warrant his unlawful Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, found out another that he might do what he liſt.) And thoſe that fear not
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:94067:34"/> God and the King (<hi>conjunctim,</hi> as one in regard of Divine Relation and Inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution) are given to ſuch changes,<note n="d" place="margin">Prov. 24.21.</note> though Chriſt himſelf, as man, gave the example of ſubmiſſion and acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Divine Right of
<hi>Caeſar</hi>'s (and his Deputy <hi>Pilate</hi>'s) Power,<note n="e" place="margin">Mat. 17.27. Joh. 9.11.</note> the convi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of which Truth fetcht the Confeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of it from a <hi>Popiſh</hi> Divine,<note n="f" place="margin">Royard. in Dom in 1. Advent.</note> 
                  <hi>Rege conſtituto, non poteſt Populus jugum ſubje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctionis repellere.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And though <hi>Bellarmine</hi> lays it as a Poſition, (as cited by <hi>Suarez</hi>
                  <note n="g" place="margin">Li. 3. c. 3. p. 224.</note>) That the People never ſo give up the Act of Power unto the King, but that they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain the Habit ſtill in themſelves, it is contradicted by
<hi>Suarez</hi>
                  <note n="h" place="margin">Defend. Fid. Cath. l. 3. c. 3. p.
225.</note> in theſe words. <hi>Non eſt ſimpliciter verum Regem pendere in ſua poteſtate a Populo, etiamſi ab ipſo eam acceperit:</hi> for he adds, <hi>Poſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam Rex legitime conſtitutus eſt, ſupre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mam habet poteſtatem in his omnibus, ad quae accipit, etiamſi a Populo illam accepe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit.</hi> So <hi>Cuneris</hi>
                  <note n="i" place="margin">L. de Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fic. Princi.</note> 
                  <hi>Principis (ſive Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctione, ſive Poſtulatione, vel Succeſſione, vel belli jure Princeps fiat) Principi tamen fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cto divinitus poteſtas adeſt.</hi> Otherways there would be Sword againſt Sword, whereas God hath made but one, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe for one hand, and will ſtill be a Repreſſor of the Tumults of the People, <pb n="60" facs="tcp:94067:35"/> which are more raging than the Waves of the Sea.<note n="k" place="margin">Pſ. 65.7.</note> For that keeps its bounds, when the other will know none.<note n="l" place="margin">Hoſ. 5.10, 11.</note>
               </p>
               <p>But here it is but he that reſiſteth, not he that obeyeth not, that purchaſes Damnation. For there may be not only a lawful but a neceſſary Diſobedience, when the Commands of our Superiours run counter to God's revealed Will,<note n="m" place="margin">Acts 4.18, 19.5.29.</note> as in <hi>Daniel</hi> and the three Children.<note n="n" place="margin">Dan. 3.4.5. chap.</note> But even then reſiſt not though a <hi>Nero,</hi> under whom ſome think St. <hi>Paul</hi> writ his Epiſtle to the <hi>Romans,</hi> and a little after felt ſome ſparks of his Perſecution,<note n="o" place="margin">Ep. 3.</note> as he was <hi>flagellum Domini,</hi>
                  <note n="p" place="margin">Hoſ. 13.11.</note> by an Ordinative Permiſſion.</p>
               <p>Nay further, our ſubmiſſion to ſuch ſhould be <hi>ex animo,</hi> (as <hi>Aquinas</hi> gloſſes) becauſe the command is
<hi>omnis anima.</hi> For it is not an Eye, but a Heart-ſervice that God requires, even to our froward and perverſe Maſters;<note n="q" place="margin">1 Pet. 2.18. Ep. 6.6.</note> knowing that God will both recompence and protect thoſe that ſuffer according to his Will, and commit their Souls to him in well-doing;<note n="r" place="margin">1 Pet. 4.19.</note> which made
<hi>David</hi> conclude, <hi>They that know thy name will put their truſt in thee, for thou Lord haſt not failed them that ſeek thee, but wilt be their refuge in ſuch times of trouble.</hi>
                  <note n="s" place="margin">Pſ. 9.9,
10.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="61" facs="tcp:94067:35"/>Nay the duty of not reſiſting may alſo be enforced from the contrary; when Chriſt in ſaying that, If his Kingdom were of this World, then would his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants fight,<note n="t" place="margin">Joh. 18.36.</note> intimates, that we owe our lives for the protection of our King's juſt Rights, but ought not to do any thing againſt them or theirs, whether concerning the Perſon or Poſterity.</p>
               <p>For after the free Suffrage or Submiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of a People to a Succeſſive Monarchy, the Son and next in Blood have always a juſt right to the Crown (as in our Kingdom) upon the death of his Father, though wanting the Ceremony of Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronation, which doth but declare not convey the Right. Nor is it in the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples Power to revoke their former Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſions, no more than a Wife when ſhe hath taken a Husband can divorce her ſelf, or juſtly refuſe him other duties, though he grow froward and unjuſt. And if it were otherwiſe how ſhould we imitate Chriſt our General in his Paſſive Obedience, (as is commanded,<note n="u" place="margin">1 Pet. 2.21.</note>) keep our Covenant in Baptiſm, (the Epitome of Chriſtian Religion,) and make many living Chriſtians by one dying Saint, (in that <hi>Sanguis Martyrum eſt ſemen Eccleſiae</hi>) or be Partakers of that Spiritual Good that comes by ſuffering, even the Tryal <pb n="62" facs="tcp:94067:36"/> of our Faith<note n="w" place="margin">1 Pet. 1.7.</note> and Improvement of our Glory.</p>
               <p>So as the contrary Opinion muſt needs proceed from Infidelity or diſtruſt, when we will be our own (God's) Deliverers, and not rely upon Providence for the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent in all Diſtreſſes, in only uſing ſuch means as by his word are warrantable. And the Weapons of our Warfare, we know, are not Carnal, but Spiritual;<note n="x" place="margin">1 Cor. 10.4. 2 Tim.
4.7.</note> even our whole <hi>Panoplie</hi> being but the Girdle of Verity, the Breaſt-plate of Righteouſneſs, the Sword of the Spirit, the Helmet of Salvation, and Shield of Faith,<note n="y" place="margin">Eph. 6.</note> by which we overcome the World.<note n="z" place="margin">1 Joh. 5.4</note> And therefore
<hi>Tertullian</hi> in his Apology againſt forcible entrance,<note n="a" place="margin">Text. 37.</note> begins with an <hi>Abſit,</hi> and concludes,
<hi>We muſt rather be ſlain than ſlay our Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periours.</hi> So
<hi>Ambroſe,</hi>
                  <note n="b" place="margin">L. 5. Ep. ad Aurent.</note>
                  <hi>Prayers and Tears are our only Weapons.</hi> And to that purpoſe ſpeaks St. <hi>Cyprian,</hi>
                  <note n="c" place="margin">Ad De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metriad.</note> 
                  <hi>Gregory Nazianzen,</hi>
                  <note n="d" place="margin">Orat. 2. in Julian.</note> with all the concurrence of the Primitive times.</p>
               <p>Nor are we to ſubmit for fear, (unleſs filial) or want of force, but Conſcience ſake: Nor can the New-minted <hi>Jeſuiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal</hi> Diſtinctions (of differing between the Perſon and the Power in their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellions, by placing it in the People, and the Adminiſtration of it only in the <pb n="63" facs="tcp:94067:36"/> King) abſolve their Conſciences from the Guilt, who <hi>de facto</hi> have reſiſted in our times; it being but a
<hi>Popiſh</hi> Riddle (ſuch as their Tranſubſtantiation) in which they turn the ſubſtance of the Regality of Kings into a mere Chymera, a fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyed nothing, and make Accidents to ſubſiſt without a Subject, the Supreme Power without his Perſon; a Paradox that neither the Goſpel nor the Law can unriddle.</p>
               <p>For they ſpeak the contrary, in making the Supreme Power inſeparable from the Perſon of a King,<note n="e" place="margin">1 Pet
2.</note> eſpecially ours, which is ſetled as well by Municipal, as Divine Law; as may appear by all the Laws of this Kingdom, both Cuſtoms and Acts, as well as by the Oaths of Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>premacy and Allegiance,<note n="f" place="margin">Cook. fol. 36. 37.</note> which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn ſuch Monſters of Opinion to be illegitimate:<note n="g" place="margin">See Cook fol. 8. 35. So Pref. 4. part fol. 1. Bract. l. 1. c. 8. fol. 5. 6. 16. Ri. 2. cap. 5.24. Hen.
8. C. 12. D. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Stu. f. 43. Dier 29. Co. 11.90.93. 1 Eliz. c. 1.
5. Eliz. 1. Cook Calvin's Caſe f. 11. Exilium. Henricide Spencer. 1 Edw. 3. 3 Edw. 25. Calv. B. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>0. Cook 4. Parl. Inſt. fol. 46. 7 fol. 30. 2 fol. 15. 1 Jacob. c. 1.10.33. Hen.
8.21.</note> And if the unhap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs of evil times and men have <hi>de facto</hi> done otherwiſe, and depoſed, or deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, or rejected their Princes, they are to expect no Lawrels nor Trophies for it; the memory and monuments of them being beſt buryed in Oblivion: In that ſuch Victories ought to be aſhamed of themſelves; for though ſuch ways may ſeem right to a man, the end thereof are the ways of death.<note n="h" place="margin">Prov.
14.2.16.25.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="64" facs="tcp:94067:37"/>And thus having taken the Timber that grows upon other Mens Soyles, and ſquared it into a leſs Model for uſe, gathered the choiceſt Flowers out of other mens Gardens, and made them into a Noſe-gay, fit for every hand, to refreſh the Spirits of ſuch as are fainting under the perſecution of theſe times for their Loyalties, (there be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing little of mine but the Thread that binds them) drawn my Oar out of others Mines to melt it into a ſmall Wedg or Ingot, that every one might carry a ſtock of Knowledg about him, as a Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter-Charm to thoſe ſeducing Spirits now raiſed among us, to withdraw men from their due Obedience, I deſire every one to treaſure up ſomething for their uſe: and having proved all Power to be of Divine Right, and only ſubject to limi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation in regard of Exerciſe, with a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity againſt Force, though a <hi>Nebucha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>donozor,</hi> or a <hi>Jeroboam</hi>
                  <note n="i" place="margin">Jer.
29 7. Hoſ. 13.11.</note> be over us, I ſhall proceed to ſpeak of the Duty of Kings; in which I ſhall not ſay much, ſince all are Doctors and read Lectures upon that ſubject, being all Eye for without (none for within) to take no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of the ſlips and failings of their Prince, which they always behold in a Multiplying-Glaſs, though by making <pb n="65" facs="tcp:94067:37"/> too much Window they weaken the Walls, and cauſe Factions and Diviſions that the Roof might fall, and then I am ſure the Frame will not ſtand long, let them ſeem to underprop it with never ſo many ſpecious pretences; (painted, but rotten Poſts:) For as the firmneſs and uniting of the Walls ſupport the Roof, ſo the Roof covers and preſerves them from many an ill Blaſt that would otherwiſe weaken and overthrow them. But I ſpin this Thread too long on this Subject, and therefore I here wind it up, and proceed to conſider,</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. IV.</hi> What Duties Kings owe to their Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, with the Excellency of that Government.</head>
               <p>HAving endeavoured to ſhew, as it were in Landskip and dark ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow only, the Great and High Prerogatives of Kings, not being able perfectly to deſcribe them as they are in themſelves without a ſeeming Court-flattery, (which yet might be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>given <pb n="66" facs="tcp:94067:38"/> given in theſe times, and in a Garriſon, where Peace of Conſcience is the only reward of Loyalty) I ſhall further ſhow you the Excellency of Regal Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment by its Effects. For ſo (as the Sun in Water) it is beſt ſeen in its Reflections, and the juſt Actions of Pious Kings, who are the Fountains of Honour, Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, Power, and all other regular ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinate motions in the lower Spheres, (as the Vital Spirits in the Head are of all Natural Operations of the Body) are always beſt ſeen in their Piety and Moralities; the induſtrious endeavour of which makes their Mitres rather pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derous than glorious, as the Emblems of Chriſtian Kings do ſhow; in that the Croſs is always fixt (but ſuperiour) to their Crown, to the imitation of their Maſter, who was Crowned indeed, but with Thorns; to teach them how full of vexing Cares and Troubles that Head ſhould be ſubject to, that (as the Stern to the Ship) is to guide the great Barque of the State, not only in Calms but Storms, which beſt prove the Pilot. So as we may conſider the Infelicities of Good Kings (with reſpect to this World) to be more in the Scale than their happineſs; when they are not Lords but Stewards; not Owners but Diſpenſers of all their <pb n="67" facs="tcp:94067:38"/> glorious Attributes and Endowments. For Regal, is that Paternal Power in the fifth Commandment, which
<hi>Philo Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daeus</hi> obſerves confines upon both Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, that their Arms of Protection might extend to the keeping of both; and the greater the Truſt the more ſevere the Account. In which there ſtands,</p>
               <p>Firſt, a Charge of Power upon each King's Score (it being one of God's communicable Attributes) how he hath uſed the Sword God hath put into his hand, which St. <hi>Peter</hi> ſaith ought to be a terrour to the Evil, not to the Good, (though a Protection to all againſt pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate wrongs) with the Militia and Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of making War or Peace: which is ſeated in them, and inherent, by Divine Right;<note n="k" place="margin">Num. 10. Deut.
17.</note> (as well as in our King by the known and eſtabliſhed Laws, and
<hi>magna charta</hi>
                  <note n="l" place="margin">C. 2.6. &amp; 7. &amp; Ed. 7. C.
1.</note> and to the Son,<note n="m" place="margin">H. 3.</note> ſucceeding him;) and though it be regulated in the Exerciſe,<note n="n" place="margin">By
13. El. 1. &amp;c. 6 1 E. 3. c. 5. 4 H. 4. c. 13 5 H. 4. 11 H. 7. c. 1. 2 E.
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 4. 5 of P. M.
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 3. 4 Jac. c. 1. 22 E.
4.</note> the Parliament never did pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to give the Power but to declare it.</p>
               <p>And thus <hi>Reynolds</hi> in his Comment on the 110 Pſalm,<note n="o" place="margin">Upon Pſ. 110.2.</note> amongſt the
<hi>[Jura Regalia]</hi> proper honours belonging to the Perſon of the King (which none can uſe but in a ſubordination to him) doth reckon
<hi>[Armamentaria Publica]</hi> the Magazines of all Military Proviſions,
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:94067:39"/> (citing <hi>Greg. Tholoſ.;</hi>)<note n="p" place="margin">De Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pub. l. 9. c. 1. Rom. 13. 1 Sam.
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>0.16.</note> by them to fence and impail God's Church and Vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard both from the wild Boar and little Foxes; and the perſons of men from In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juries and Violence; which are the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Priviledges we can enjoy in this World, as may more clearly appear by the contrary Effects; (For things are ſeen <hi>carendo magis quam fruendo.</hi>) As in <hi>Judges,</hi>
                  <note n="q" place="margin">Cap. 17.</note> where the decay of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, advancing of Idolatry, making Prieſts of the loweſt of the People, and all other Civil (uncivil) Diſorders pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded from the want of this Power in one man, and are imputed to it, as to the efficient cauſe, though properly <hi>ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum non habet efficientem, ſed deficientem cauſam.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And therefore we may expect great good from them, when ſo many Evils are occaſioned by their want. For when there was no King in
<hi>Iſrael,</hi> every man did what ſeemed good in his own Eyes, (ſaith the Spirit of God) diſenthroning Reaſon, and making Luſt their Law, and Rapes their boaſt.<note n="r" place="margin">Judg. 19.</note> So that by juſt conſequence the having of a good King is the proper Remedy of thoſe Evils, who makes his juſt Power the meaſure of his Will, not his Will the meaſure of his Power. And therefore it is Enacted, <pb n="69" facs="tcp:94067:39"/> ſaith St. <hi>Peter,</hi> in the ſtyle of a Law-giver (as ſome obſerve) that all ſhould be ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to him (at leaſt in not doing his Lawful Commands, be puniſhed by him.)<note n="s" place="margin">Rom. 3 4. Eccl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſ.
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. Eſdr. 7 25, 26, 27. Rev.
2.20.</note> And ſo we find it in all the Reigns of the good Kings of
<hi>Iſrael;</hi> for there were no <hi>Micha</hi>'s Idols nor High-places left; no Rapines nor Violences ſuffered; no acting of Wickedneſs un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Countenance of Laws and Acts; but, as Gods,<note n="t" place="margin">Pſ.
82.6.</note> they medled with the Affairs of God; as Nurſing-Fathers they nouriſhed the Church with the two Breaſts of God's Word and Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, through the Miniſterial Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtrations of Prieſts, and as publick Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters for good,<note n="u" place="margin">Rom. 13.</note> they reſtrained all other Uncivil Inſolencies, not ſuffering every man to be a King; nay more than a King, in doing what he liſt: for a King ought not to be a <hi>Jeroboam,</hi> favouring idolatry, or any falſe Worſhip;<note n="w" place="margin">2 Chro. 10.14.</note> but a <hi>David,</hi> Learned, Pious and Wiſe, as an Angel of God,<note n="x" place="margin">2 Sam. 19.27.</note> that Fraud, Inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, and violence might be detected and reſtrained, Innocency relieved, Indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry encouraged, Vertue rewarded, and Vice puniſhed.</p>
               <p>Secondly, Juſtice Diſtributive is ow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from a King to all his Subjects, as that which eſtabliſhes his own Throne, <pb n="70" facs="tcp:94067:40"/> (ſaith <hi>Solomon</hi>) and keeps the juſt Boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daries of
<hi>[meum &amp; tuum]</hi> Common Right amongſt men (out of which, as Seeds, the large Harveſt of Contentions growes:) For, <hi>Judicium</hi> or
<hi>Poteſtas ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diciaria</hi> is a peculiar of Royalty, in that the Adminiſtration is from the Prince as the Fountain of all Humane Equity (under God) depoſited in the hands of inferiour Officers:<note n="y" place="margin">Pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>v.
20.8.</note> For ſo he is <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretative</hi> in them, who, as his mouth, are to publiſh the Laws, and to execute thoſe Acts of Juſtice and Peace which principally belong to his own ſacred Breaſt. So
<hi>Reynolds</hi> ſtill in that place, alluding there to that of
<hi>Joh.</hi> 5.22, 27. and drawing his Parallel from Chriſt, where he ſaith, <hi>The Father hath commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted all Judgment to the Son,</hi> &amp;c. And therefore herein a good King ought e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver to make God's revealed Will, and the known Laws, (of which his ſworn Judges are to be the Interpreters) the meaſure and rule of his proceedings; and that under pain of Damnation, a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verity from God, infinitely above the coercion of men: nor ſhall their puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment be leſs, who uſurp the Exerciſe of this Juſtice without his Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="71" facs="tcp:94067:40"/>Thirdly, Mercy muſt all derive from the King (as a Flower that groweth on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in his Garland) a Gem which can ſhine only from the Diadem of Princes, For <hi>Jus vitae &amp; necis,</hi> a Power of pardon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Condemned Perſons, and delivering from the Terrour of the Law, (though in ſome caſes limited, as in wilful Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, and the like) belongs only to him; being there depoſited by God himſelf, and in no other Repreſentative whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever; ſo that where Regal Government is ſetled, the Execution of any man (though wicked and deſerving to dye by the Law) is wicked, if not having the King's Commiſſion for it.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, Honour (the ennobling of the Blood) is to derive from him, when Vertue or ſome Heroick Acts dignifie the Perſon; for without that he that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceives it is but a Label which bears the Wax, without any impreſſion of the Seal, or as a rotten Poſt that bears a glorious Eſcutcheon. But for the more clear manifeſtations of this, his
<hi>[Orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menta Regia]</hi> Regal Ornaments, as a Crown, a Throne, a Scepter, and the like, with the univerſally acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Rights to them, ſpeak him to be the only Spring, from whence it can flow,<note n="z" place="margin">2 King.
12.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>2. 1 Kings 10.8.</note> and ought ſtill to iſſue in leſſer and <pb n="72" facs="tcp:94067:41"/> greater Streams, by it to enrich the hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Valleys, and make them ſhew gay, when adorned with thoſe Flowers of the Crown for the encouragement of Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue; (as he beareth the Sword to cut down Offenders and prevent their growth:) And as a Teſtimony hereof the <hi>Romans</hi> had wont to ſend to Foreign Kings in League with them, an Ivory-Sceptre, a Royal Robe, and Chair of State,<note n="a" place="margin">Tacit. Annal. l. 4.</note> to ſhow in Hieroglyphick what they were.</p>
               <p>Fifthly, Kings owe an Example of Vertue and Piety to their Subjects in that (<hi>inſtruimur praeceptis ſed dirigimur exemplis,</hi> ſaith <hi>Seneca,</hi>) the Actions of great men have a Compulſory Power in them, <hi>[Regis ad exemplum]</hi> are an Eye-Catechiſm, and (as the
<hi>Baſilisk</hi>) by ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing they many times kill our Vices, or by being ſeen invite us to Vertue; Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples being the ſhorteſt way of teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: For from that Milk we uſually, as from our Mothers Breaſts, ſuck our good or bad Inclinations.<note n="b" place="margin">Gal. 2.14.</note> Nay like the firſt Mover they carry all the Infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour Orbs with them, as the firſt Deer the Herd: When bad Kings, with the ill Influence of the Planets, kill more deadly than Poyſon in Plants, becauſe coming from a more glorious Body,
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:94067:41"/> though the other be more Infecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous.</p>
               <p>But herein we in this Nation have the advantage of all others: For if ever the Rayes of Vertue had a Power of affimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lating others into their own Divine Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, the Beams of Goodneſs that ſhine upon us from the Example of our dear Soveraign (who, as a Combination or Conjunction of Graces, both Divine and Moral, hath all in himſelf that a fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite and limited Being is capable of) muſt needs have a prevalency over us. Or if they make us not better, they will make us much worſe, as they will riſe up in Judgment againſt us to our greater Condemnation. And I am confident as he is an Active Example of Vertue, ſo he would be Paſſive to teach us how to ſuffer in a good Cauſe, though it were to paſs through a Red Sea of his own Blood for the good of his People; <hi>Peli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>can</hi>-like to nouriſh us with the Spirits that flow out of his own Breaſt; and, by thoſe Beams, to reflect a more glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Luſtre than in his Meridian and height of Greatneſs.</p>
               <p>But, not to ſuffer my Zeal to carry me beſides my purpoſe, there is, amongſt many others, one part of Duty moſt eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially incumbent upon Kings. For,</p>
               <p n="6">
                  <pb n="75" facs="tcp:94067:42"/>6. Laſtly, as Kings reign by God, ſo they ſhould rule for him and the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt good of their People in matters of Religion, both in maintaining the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance and Eſſential Parts of it, in their Vigour and Power, by Active Compul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions and Humane Reſtraints, to force the outward man to Obedience in things good in themſelves, and to preſcribe ſuch Rules, Methods, and Boundaries in things indifferent, as may bring all to Uniformity in Worſhip, and may ſtand as a Wall or Fence to God's Vineyard, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Invaſions of the little Foxes of Schiſms and Factions. And this not only for Decency, Order, and Signifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cancy, but as that without which Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion it ſelf cannot ſubſiſt: For though they are no parts of it, but Circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tials, Eſſentials in a Well-formed Church cannot be maintained without them, no more than a Tree can be preſerved to live without its Bark, or Majeſty in a King without Reverence: For that, like the Skin to the Body, preſerves it both in Being and Beauty; which occaſioned St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Precept of having all things <hi>be done decently and in order,</hi> that is, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to appointment, as the Original<note n="c" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> will bear it; ſo Dr. <hi>Hammond</hi> renders the Words.<note n="d" place="margin">1 Cor. 14.40.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="74" facs="tcp:94067:42"/>For take away thoſe Regulations of our Publick Devotions, (which are as the Hemme, that ſtrengthens the Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and keeps it Uniform,) all would reſolve into Rents and Schiſms, Chaos and Confuſion. So as if the Church of God (his encloſed Garden) be not fenced by good Laws for Conformity, all Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thods of Devotion are loſt, and the Bores of the Forreſt (unruly men of Facti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Spirits) will ſoon break in to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy and root it up; and offer nothing but the blind and lame to God, in looſe and untruſs'd poſtures, unbecoming the Greatneſs of an Earthly Prince in our Addreſſes to them, much more to our God,<note n="e" place="margin">Mal. 1.</note> by it to make their Superiours bend to them, if pertinacious obſtinacy could do it, when they ſhould bow to their Superiours,<note n="f" place="margin">Rom. 13. 1 Pet. 2. Eph. 4. and 6.</note> according to the Oeconomy of Nature it ſelf, where the inferiour Orbs are to be guided and move by the higheſt Spheres: Other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe the whole Fabrick would be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hinged and fall in pieces, or at leaſt grow weak by ſeparation. For a Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſation to ſeveral Forms of Worſhip in one Church would prove an Act ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of Diviſion than Comprehenſion, encreaſe Emulation and Factions, and plant a Seminary for a continued Schiſm:
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:94067:43"/> In that there could be no ſuch Encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement but there would be ſcandal and a way of ſeduction in it, to all Ortho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dox Proteſtants, and a Tranſmigration of Souls amongſt themſelves from the Father to the Son, with Encouragements and Supports from their pro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uſe Zeal of the
<hi>Proſelites</hi> to their Opinions. So as they would ſtrengthen with time (in that Novelties never want Courtſhip and Adorers,) though the old way is <hi>(Regia via]</hi> God's way, and only to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended for<note n="g" place="margin">St. Jude Ep.</note> and preſerved by our Act of Uniformity.</p>
               <p>And in this reſpect Kings and Queens are chiefly ſtyled Nurſing Fathers and Nurſing Mothers to the Church; Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers for Proviſion and Protection; Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers for their tenderneſs and care; when as by little Stratagems and Circumven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions they bring their Children to an ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bituated Obedience, and keep Dangers from them by ſome outward and extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary Confinements, both for Hone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty and Order.<note n="h" place="margin">1 Cor.
14.40.</note>
               </p>
               <p>So as Kings have no meaner a depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitum committed to them, than the Crown and Throne of God and Chriſt in the Church: For they are as the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons about the Throne, to ſecure and guard it; and as Law-givers in indifferent <pb n="77" facs="tcp:94067:43"/> things,<note n="i" place="margin">Deut. 33.4,
5.</note> (though ſubject to the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection of their Laws) and are with
<hi>David</hi> to preſcribe Rules for fixed Servi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and Devotions,<note n="k" place="margin">1 Chro. 23.</note> and with <hi>Joſiah</hi> to compel to Religious Duties and Laws of his commanding, (as is before expreſt,)<note n="l" place="margin">2 Chro. 34.33.</note> as <hi>Hezekiah</hi> did;<note n="m" place="margin">2 Chro. 29. &amp; 30. &amp; 31.</note> which
<hi>Conſtantine</hi> the firſt Chriſtian Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour imitated:<note n="n" place="margin">Euſeb. de vita Conſtant. l. 2. c. 37, 38, 39.</note> But they never (as <hi>Praxiteles</hi> the Painter made the ſilly People worſhip the Image of his Strumpet, under the Title of <hi>Venus</hi>) impoſed the Viſions of their own Fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies, nor licenſed the crude and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouriſhing Vapours of others empty Wits upon the credulous People, it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing below the Majeſty of Truth and Religion; but according to the ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerity of God's Law: not ſuffering their Luſts to guide them, which ever bring unconſtancy with them, and make the Soul, like a diſtempered Body, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver well in any poſition or condition. For then men (like Bees from one Flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to another) will be ever flying from one Change and Vanity to another, and not find enough to ſatiate the intempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate deſire of change.</p>
               <p>So as it can be neither agreeable to Religion nor Prudence for a King to ſuffer variety of Poſtures and Forms in <pb n="78" facs="tcp:94067:44"/> the outward Exerciſe of Religion; (for what is good is to be obeyed for it ſelf; what, indifferent in Obedience to his Command, when in middle things Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme Power chiefly conſiſts.) And,</p>
               <p n="1">1. For Religion, Kings ought to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain it in its Eſſentials and Purity (without any Indulgence or Diſpenſations to any) as that only which can maintain them.<note n="o" place="margin">Prov. 16.12, 20,
28.</note> And ſuch <hi>Joſephs</hi> will be Store-hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes in their Kingdoms, and as <hi>Elijah,</hi> Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riots and Horſe-men for their ſecurity; there being no guard to that of Piety and Zeal for God's Glory, which they are entruſted to preſerve, (even both Tables of the Law;) and are not to bear the Sword in vain, which is put into their hands for that uſe; Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulſion being neceſſary where Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands are contemned.<note n="q" place="margin">Luk. 14.23. Rev. 2.2, 6, 14, 15, 20. Ch. 3.15,
16.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Nor doth Chriſt's Permiſſion of the Tares to grow give any juſt Power of Toleration to Princes by God's Law in known Evils, or pertinacious contuma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy to lawful Commands, but only per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits mixed Aſſemblies, where, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of outward Conformity, none can diſcriminate the truly pious from the Hypocrite; by which he yet doth not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid their Eradication abſolutely, but for fear the good Seed alſo ſhould be deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; <pb n="79" facs="tcp:94067:44"/> when a Connivance to known Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours in Doctrine, (or to pertinacious <hi>Non-conformiſts</hi> in indifferent things) would make the Magiſtrate contract the guilt of their Crimes, (<hi>Judg.</hi> 5.23.) by confirming the one in their miſtaken Doctrines, and the other in their ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitious believing indifferent things un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawful; even to an adoring the Idol of their own Fancy, uncharitably cenſuring of all others, (even the Church and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment it ſelf;) though it bring Hell out of Heaven, (in a pretence of Devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion) and the Devil upon God's Shoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders to rule amongſt us in <hi>Samuel</hi>'s Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, by the ſilly Charms of a ſeducing Spirit, through the warmth of Zeal, when it wants the light of Knowledge to guide it; though like the Volatil Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits of Poyſons, when unconfined, (by not being luted up in ſome Viol or Veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel) it evaporates into an Airy being, of uſe only to infect others that ſuck it in by a nearneſs of Converſation. So as ſome Ingredients of a ſeeming Cruelty in our Laws will prove the moſt Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign Mercy to reduce and recover them, and preſerve the ſound from their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagion, if tempered in a proportion to their Crimes by pecuniary Mulcts or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Confinements; ſaving ſome by <pb n="80" facs="tcp:94067:45"/> Compaſſion, others by Fears;<note n="r" place="margin">Jude ver. 22.23.</note> when the violation of any juſt Law, if wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully done, is unlawful. Nay the leaſt minute Atome or Airy Omiſſion, if ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitual, may become the greateſt Crime, if done with Scandal and Contempt to Authority; in that the Tranſgreſſion is againſt Gods Ordinance, that requires Obedience to the Commander, not in the value of the thing commanded by him, it being no leſs Treaſon to coyne a Farthing, that has the King's ſtamp upon it, than a piece of Gold, according to our Saviours Rule; in that, He that offends in one wilfully, is guilty of the breach of all the Commandments, when upon equal Temptations he would break the reſt; for one little wilful Sin, like the firſt drop in an Orifice, will uſher in more, and diſpoſe the whole Body to ſuch Evacuations and Eruptions.</p>
               <p n="2">2. In Prudence there ought to be no Indulgence, as to the Publick Exerciſe of any falſe Religion or variety of Forms in outward Worſhip: For, what Unity, Decency, or Order can there be in ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting up one Congregation againſt ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther? when Order is the Bond of Peace that keeps us in Unity: For once break that, or tye but with a ſlip-knot, and all will be diſſolved and come to Confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, <pb n="81" facs="tcp:94067:45"/> which is the Womb of all Rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Schiſms.</p>
               <p>Nay, it were to depoſe Reaſon (the Supreme Monarch) and Enthrone the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriour Members, which ſhould ſubmit, and not impoſe. And certainly the giv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Ground in ſuch a Duel would give Courage and Inſolency in the Enemy to preſs for more; and the Pale of Law, that has a breach once made in it, will let out all the Beaſts of the Forreſt to Rapine and Prey, to the loſs of good Subjects, but not to the making any better. So as however wiſe Princes may inlarge any thing that is too ſtrait in matters of Diſcipline, they will never let Clamour, or the Unjuſt Diſcontents of any Midwife in what they call Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation; and much leſs a Toleration of all Sects and Errours.</p>
               <p>Nor can the King expect a Harmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny amongſt Antipathies by permitting ſeveral Forms in one ſettled Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, though the want of Power to maintain his own Laws may force him to unreaſonable Condeſcenſions; (for then a Dam againſt that Current would but enrage it to greater Violences) yet in ſuch a Caſe I conceive he ought rather to make a General Rule of Conformity for all, if poſſible, than Differing-ones to
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:94067:46"/> Parties;) by it to lay aſleep and bury all Animoſities the other would maintain; and, like Oyl upon Paper, would ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther harden than ſoften ſuch Rebellious Spirits, and render them rather Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>querours than Supplicants: But I hope God will not ſubmit his own Glory and our King to ſuch an Eclipſe, when no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but neceſſity can make it lawful: Though probably ſuch a Scheme by ſome may be ſet and calculated for our Horizon, when his Majeſty's Comply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance to ſome things has made them ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther impoſe more than acquieſce in what they deſired; for he that once gives Ground ever loſes more in his Retreat; (unleſs it be to rally again with ſome Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves to maintain his own Right more vigorouſly;) ſo as we ought ſtill to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to Blood for our King's Freedom in his Actings againſt ſuch. Eſpecially thoſe whoſe Principles are for Reſiſtance and Rebellion (not Submiſſion) in things that are contrary to their ſeditious Principles; that hold it lawful to murder the King, (if not the man in whom the Regal Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er is veſted,) by diſpoiling him of all his <hi>Regalia,</hi> and Eſſentials of Royalty; which were to un ſhakel mad-men, and ſet them free to Fury and Rage, perhaps for the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of thoſe that endeavoured their <pb n="83" facs="tcp:94067:46"/> recovery and preſervation, and not to ſtrike Sparks into thoſe Brands that need be quenched: but they heighten all into a Flame.</p>
               <p>Beſides, it were unſafe to the Publick Peace to permit the Factious <hi>Separatiſts</hi> (who are yet as Sand without Morter, weak, diſperſed and looſe) to gather in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Combinations and Confederacies, by which they'll know their own ſtrength, and take advantage of others weakneſs to compaſs their own end, whoſe end is only (like Oyl among other Liquors) to be uppermoſt, and bring all into a ſubje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to them, and to be able perhaps to give, not ask Diſpenſations.</p>
               <p>Nay it would reflect diſhonour and diſgrace upon our Government and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours, and Diſcouragement to all Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodox Profeſſors, not to maintain what hath been proſperouſly practiſed among us ſince the Reformation, and hath had the Influences of Heaven to give it a Prolifick Vertue, in producing a Loyal, Zealous and Pious People to beautifie their Profeſſions. And therefore Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Kings ſhould not be out-done by a Heathen inſpired by God to it, but ſend out a Decree that whoſoever will not do th Law of God, and the King's Law, let him have Judgment without delay, <pb n="84" facs="tcp:94067:47"/> whether it be to Death, or to Baniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or to Confiſcation of Goods, or to Impriſonment,<note n="s" place="margin">Ezr. 7.25, 26, 27.</note> which was in part practiſed by the Kings of <hi>Iſrael,</hi>
                  <note n="t" place="margin">2 Chro. 15.12, 13, 14, 15. &amp; 29. &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>0. &amp; 31. &amp; 34.31, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>2,
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>3. 1 Chron. 23.</note> and ought much more to be done under the Goſpel, that hath more of light and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection in it to walk by; leſt Liberty ſhould turn into Licentiouſneſs, in hold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing things contrary to the Analogy of Faith, and againſt the Rules of Charity, Purity, Loyalty, Sobriety and Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, to the diſturbance of the Peace and Unity of the Church, which Good and Pious Kings ought always to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent or reſtrain by wholeſom and Penal Laws of Regulation, to encourage or fright their People the more to their Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and Obedience; which I ſhall in the next place touch upon with a light and unskilful Pencil.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <pb n="85" facs="tcp:94067:47"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. V.</hi> Of the Debt and Allegiance Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects owe to their Princes.</head>
               <p>NOW, that we may pay and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute the Native Rights (right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly) which we owe to the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon upon whom God hath fixt the Sacred Character of Supremacy, let us endeavour to ſet a true value and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimate upon the great benefits we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive by him, when we either find in the foot of the Account all the Glory of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and happineſs of a free People (if he Governs well) ſummed up in him, or when ill, not only the Exerciſe of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Chriſtian Graces in us (God com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding our Submiſſion to him) but ſometimes the higheſt Crown of Martyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, when we ſuffer for Chriſt and a Good Cauſe, and are not only ready (with St. <hi>Paul</hi>) to do, but dye for his Name:<note n="u" place="margin">Acts 21.</note> For by it we may make Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants and our greateſt Enemies to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come our beſt Friends, if we can but im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove thoſe holy advantages for our Spiritual Good, and make our Spirits, when extracted from the more earthly <pb n="86" facs="tcp:94067:48"/> parts in all outward enjoyments, to mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiply our Joyes: ſo that were there not a higher Principle to move us, our own Intereſt and ſelf-advantage (the delight and complaiſance of a quiet Conſcience) ſhould naturally incline us to an holy gratitude to God for them, and oblige us to all proportionable returns; unleſs we will have the inanimate and irratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Creatures to riſe up againſt us in Judgment. For thus the Rivers run back into the Lap of their Natural Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and offer up their ſtreams there, as a juſt Tribute for having ſucked and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rived their nouriſhment from her Breaſts. Thus the dull and heavy Earth doth put forth her ſelf in an early Spring to make an Offering of her Fruits to man, for his labour and coſt beſtowed on her, and ſends up an Incenſe to Heaven (con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt of the Spirits of her richeſt Flowers) in thanks for her fruitful Showers and ſweet Influences by which they grow and flouriſh. Nay the moſt unnatural of all Birds, the Raven, became <hi>Elias</hi> his Caterer out of a natural gratitude to God (as ſome have obſerved) for feeding her young ones when ſhe left them.</p>
               <p>And therefore let not theſe become, in this, reaſonable Creatures, and we Men become Beaſts, nay worſe by our <pb n="87" facs="tcp:94067:48"/> unthankfulneſs for Bleſſings by Afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; but moſt when we fail in our Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties to our Superiours for their benefits to us; the contrary being enjoined by God; who, becauſe Princes are to rule for him, takes care for them; and no ſooner provides for his own Worſhip, but for their Honour,<note n="w" place="margin">Ex. 20.2, 3, 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> ſtill coupling them with himſelf through all the Scripture: as<note n="x" place="margin">Prov. 24.21. Mat. 22.21.
1 Pet. 2.17.</note> 
                  <hi>Fear God, honour the King,</hi> that ſo both Law, Prophets, Apoſtles, nay the Son of God himſelf, might enforce it as a Duty upon us, as a learned Father of our Church obſerves. But not to looſe my ſelf in this Sea, we will follow the ſeveral ſtreams that run into it, and ſhew how they all meet there. And,</p>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Firſt, of Obedience.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. The firſt great Out-rent and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage we are to acknowledge our ſubje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction in is Obedience (in lawful Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands.) For ſo St. <hi>Paul</hi> to <hi>Titus,</hi>
                     <note n="y" place="margin">Tit. 3.1.</note> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menting as it were upon the 13th Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to the <hi>Romans,</hi> expounds it. And, as the Learned obſerve, the very word [Subjects] ſignifies Obeyers in the Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal, as an Eſſential Ingredient into an happy Government; which, with <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon,</hi> is ever moſt glorious, <hi>Si Populus
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:94067:49"/> Magiſtratui obediat, Magiſtratus autem legibus.</hi> But then this duty muſt be root<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in Conſcience and ſpring from thence, in that we muſt obey for the Lord's ſake, terminating it in him, becauſe the bond to Civil Obedience is from Divine Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance, and that not only to the good, but froward Maſters:<note n="z" place="margin">1 Pet. 2.18. Eph.
6.</note> And then let it ſpread into every duty (even in all things<note n="a" place="margin">Col. 3.20.</note> Actively or Paſſively, obeying the Lawful, ſubmitting our Perſons, though not our Actions to the reſt)<note n="b" place="margin">Act. 5.29.</note> to our King as he is <hi>Pater Patriae,</hi>
                     <note n="c" place="margin">1 Pet. 2.17.</note> of all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers the Supreme Head; for only <hi>in rebus mediis L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>x poſita eſt Obedientiae;</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe, as I noted before, in things ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary by any Divine Law we ought to obey though no Humane Authority com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand them; in things unlawful we ought not to obey though commanded; and are only to obey for the Commands ſake (not the things commanded) in things indifferent, which only become unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful becauſe forbidden, and are not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden becauſe unlawful. For ſuch O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience is not only accepted with (but rewarded of) God; as in the <hi>Recabites, Jer.</hi> 35. and can only keep us in a ſerene and calm temper in the Body politick; ſo as a frown will not appear in the face of that great Ocean by the raging of <pb n="89" facs="tcp:94067:49"/> Waves and madneſs of the People; nor will a wrinckle ſhow it ſelf to abate its beauty.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. We owe Honour to him, and that as juſtly as Fear to God himſelf, being commanded to pay it to God in the Man, not to the Man, but as he repreſents God. And this (as the Flags and main Sails of a Ship) doth not only deck and adorn the Throne, but makes it bear up in all Weathers; nay, (as the Bark the Tree) doth preſerve it in all its other Rights. For, let us but once ſlight or contemn the Perſon, (in ſaying, what is this
<hi>Moſes</hi> that takes ſo much upon him?)<note n="d" place="margin">Num.
9.</note> and we ſhall ſoon deſpiſe his Power; nay God himſelf as repreſented in the King or Supreme.<note n="e" place="margin">1 Sam.
1.8</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>Upon which ground it is probable that God and the King are linked together: <hi>Fear God, Honour the King,</hi>
                     <note n="f" place="margin">1 Pet. 2.17.</note> to teach us that their Precepts are not two, but one and the ſame in Root, though the Fruit we muſt pay them is different. And therefore St. <hi>Paul</hi> in commanding all to ſubmit to the higher Powers, concludes, to whom you owe Honour,<note n="g" place="margin">Rom. 13.7.</note> (as to a Father, or to God, for Gods command)<note n="h" place="margin">Iſa.
49.23.</note> and this in our thoughts not to blaſpheme them,<note n="i" place="margin">Eccl. 10.20.</note> in our words not to deprave them,<note n="k" place="margin">Ex. 22.28. Acts 22.5. Jude 8.</note> nor ſpeak evil of them; in all our Actions to reverence <pb n="90" facs="tcp:94067:50"/> them, as Gods upon Earth, his Chair of State, wherein Divinity it ſelf is En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throned,<note n="l" place="margin">Pſ. 8<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.6. 2 Sam. 14.10 Num. 12.10. &amp; 16.32.</note> though in the Perſon of a Wicked man: For though he forfeit his claim to double Honour, due to them that rule well,<note n="m" place="margin">1 Tim. 5.</note> one to his Place, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother to his Vertues,) he cannot deveſt himſelf of, nor juſtly be denyed that Honour, Fear, Subjection, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which Subjects, as a debt and duty, muſt everpay to his Office and Supremacy, as a moſt learned Divine hath obſerved.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. We owe Tribute both of our Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons and Purſes. Firſt of our Perſons, for the juſt defence of our King and his juſt Rights. This is implyed in thoſe words of our Saviour, <hi>My Kingdom is not of this World, elſe would my Servants fight.</hi>
                     <note n="n" place="margin">Joh. 18.36. 1 Tim. 22.</note> As alſo in reſpect of the Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of Life a King has over his Rebellious Subjects, that would not ſubmit to his Government;<note n="o" place="margin">Luke 19.27.</note> which though a Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable may from the Application inforce it. And it may be further proved from his juſt Power of making War and Peace;<note n="p" place="margin">Num. 10.</note> as hath been ſhewed fully from Scripture and our Law-books.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Secondly,</hi> To this we muſt add the Tribute of our Purſes; in that Money is one of the Pillars of Power, and the Nerves of War; Majeſty without it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <pb n="91" facs="tcp:94067:50"/> but the ſhadow of Regality, and without Power but a Speculative Great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs that hath the Viſion of gallant things, but no means to detain them; becauſe wanting of that Soul which ſhould animate that (otherwiſe dead and uſeleſs) thing to Action. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God hath provided againſt the <hi>Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lilites</hi> and
<hi>Herodians</hi>
                     <note n="q" place="margin">Act. 5.37 Mark 12.17. Mat.
22.16.21.</note> in one and the ſame Command, reſolving upon that Common Rule of Juſtice <hi>[ſuum cui<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan>]</hi> for neither but againſt both; thoſe that would give all to God and no Tribute to <hi>Caeſar,</hi> or all to <hi>Caeſar</hi> and nothing to God (divorcing thoſe he hath joined together) by ſaying, <hi>Give therefore to</hi> Caeſar <hi>the things that are</hi> Caeſar's, <hi>and to God the things that are God's.</hi>
                     <note n="r" place="margin">Mat. 22.21.</note> Upon which ground (as I conceive) Dr.
<hi>Rey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nolds</hi> ſtill obſerves,<note n="s" place="margin">Pſ. 110. pag.
128.</note> [<hi>Bona adeſpota in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certi Domini vectigalia cenſus,</hi> &amp;c.] Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cealments, Tributes, Cuſtoms, and the like, are Teſtifications of Homage and Fidelity belonging to the Perſonal Prero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gative of Princes, and are (as the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle ſaith) due unto them.<note n="t" place="margin">Rom.
13.6, 7.</note> Thus <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon</hi> levyed, and the Princes with whom he held Correſpondence, payed Tribute.<note n="u" place="margin">1 Kings 4.21. &amp; 9.21. &amp; 10.10. Deut. 20.16.</note> Nay Chriſt himſelf paid it, (by his Command to <hi>Peter</hi>) though he was at the coſt of a Miracle for it,<note n="w" place="margin">Mat. 17.27.</note> even <pb n="92" facs="tcp:94067:51"/> to a
<hi>Tiberius,</hi> a Wicked Prince, though it was the only Miracle he ever wrought in money matters, (as peculiar to Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces) whereas all his others concerned the general neceſſities of mankind.</p>
                  <p>And we may further obſerve the juſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of it from the Latine word <hi>Reddite,</hi> not <hi>Date,</hi> importing that it is not only lawful to pay, but unlawful to with-hold it as a due; nay it ſhould be willingly (the Offering of a free-heart.)<note n="x" place="margin">2 Cor.
9.71.</note> So as Legal Cuſtoms,<note n="y" place="margin">Luke 3.3.</note> Taxes or Homage,<note n="z" place="margin">1 Sam. 17.25. 2 Kings 15.19,
20.</note> Fines,<note n="a" place="margin">Eſt. 7.26.</note> Confiſcations,<note n="b" place="margin">Ezr. 10.8.</note> are the juſt Rights of our Superiours. But ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary Impoſitions cannot legally be now laid upon us, (in any caſe but vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible and immergent neceſſity) without the conſent of both Houſes of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; it having been the Wiſdom of our Predeceſſors (by the Indulgence of good Kings) to keep the Purſe and the Power (by Municipal Law) divided, to prevent all Tyranny and Exorbitancy in the uſe of either.</p>
                  <p>And if we owe theſe Aſſiſtances to our lawful Soveraign, how are they guilty againſt God of a High Rebellion that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject and oppoſe him in their Superiour, and do not endeavour by juſt duty to prop, but undermine his Throne? For if a Negative Obligation, not to aid him,
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:94067:51"/> be unlawful where God commands aſſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance; what is their Crime, but as the Sin of Witch-craft, that enter into an Engagement againſt him, who is to them God amongſt men in the viſible Chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cter of his Power? (when all others are only Men before God:) So as he never countenanced any other Government than what was Monarchical, depoſited and ſummed up in one Perſon, exerciſing the Power, though not always poſſeſſing the name of King. As appears by that of <hi>Judges,</hi> where it is ſaid, every one did what they liſt when there was no King (that is, no ſupreme Judge, or law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Magiſtrate) in <hi>Iſrael.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Nay, even in Popular States (ſo na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural a thing is Monarchy) in what hands ſoever the Power is, one Finger will ſtill (as in natural Bodies) be found longer than the reſt, and become a King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Tyrant by his over-ſwaying Intereſt. And therefore let us not caſt <hi>Pelion</hi> upon <hi>Oſſa,</hi> heap Sin upon Sin, by countenan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing ſuch muſhroom Alterations. Nay, he that is not againſt them is with them in this caſe, and ſo becomes guilty of their unfruitful deeds of Darkneſs, if not diſcountenancing and preventing them by all lawful wayes; according to that of the Apoſtle,<note n="t" place="margin">1 Theſ. 5.</note> avoid all ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance <pb n="94" facs="tcp:94067:52"/> of evil by appearing to diſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low of it, never concurring actively with it, though we ſuffer to Bonds and death: For that will in the end prove our Crown of rejoycing, though the
<hi>Abſoloms</hi> of theſe times would with fair and ſpecious pretences ſeduce us from our Allegiance. For it is better in this Caſe (contrary to
<hi>David</hi>'s choice) to fall into the hands of Men, (embalmed with Innocence to preſerve our names from Infamy, and our Souls from Damnation) than into the hands of God, beſmeared with the Leproſie of Sin, that muſt needs cauſe his rejection of us.</p>
                  <p>But if the Deſpiſers of God and their King will ſtill pertinaciouſly maintain the black and horrid Sins of Oppreſſion, Sacriledge, Murder, and the like; not only depoſing, but deſpoyling them (as the greateſt Delinquents) of all their juſt Patrimonies and Rights, by plun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering the one, and vilifying the other, (in all things ſacred, whether Places, Perſons or Revenues, ſanctified and diſcriminated by Gods own Inſtitution) by prophaning his Sanctuaries, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſing his Prieſts and Ordinances,<note n="d" place="margin">Lam. 31. Pſ. 74.</note> they may be aſſured of a certain (if not ſwift) deſtruction to overtake them from the Authority of the like Precedents in <pb n="95" facs="tcp:94067:52"/> all Ages, and the Word of God it ſelf. For their Poſterity here (like a Plague-ſore in the Body growing out of their own putrefaction (their ſoul and ulcerous Sins) as the meritorious cauſe of Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments will haſten them.</p>
                  <p>Nor can they account themſelves free from the other's guilt, who have not acted in their Crimes, if they have not ſome way oppoſed them<note n="e" place="margin">Judg. 5.23.</note> according to their ſeveral Callings and Capacities, being bound to it by the Laws of God, the Kingdom, and that of Natural Obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation to their Civil Parents, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Charity to their engaged Brethren; in that Damnation will be chiefly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced againſt Sins of Omiſſion, at the laſt day; which I expreſs not to upbraid any, but to convince them; by it to make them ſteer a more ſafe courſe in Emergencies of the like nature, (if any ſhall hereafter happen) making God's Law the Compaſs by which they ſail (e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven Heavenly Influences, not ſublunary Agitations.)</p>
                  <p>However, I hope they will keep them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves from a countenancing of, or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyance with the Perſons and Actings of thoſe that uſurp the Supreme Power, (both in regard of Scandal to others, and contracting Crime upon themſelves) <pb n="96" facs="tcp:94067:53"/> by avoiding all Appearances of Evil,<note n="f" place="margin">1 Theſ. 5.</note> when Vertue and Vice border ſo upon one another, are ſo near in their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fines and ſo contiguous, as the leaſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs or defect makes a Natural Action many times an unnatural diſorder, and a thing indifferent in it ſelf become the parent of a great Sin.</p>
                  <p>Therefore he cannot be innocent that holds Communion with thoſe that are guilty of ſuch high Crimes, in any thing that ſeems to countenance them; though God's Service be a thing pretended, as in their Thankſgivings and Humiliati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; ſo St. <hi>Auguſtine.</hi>
                     <note n="g" place="margin">Serm. 6. de verb. Dom.</note> For two will not walk together unleſs they agree, ſaith the Prophet.<note n="h" place="margin">Amos
3.3.</note> So as it is the duty of every Chriſtian not to betray the truth by his Silence or Countenance, but to contend for it againſt all Actions that ſeem to favour the ſucceſſes of an unjuſt Cauſe, grounded in Rebellion, or tend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the maintaining an Uſurped Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er.<note n="i" place="margin">Judg. 3.11.</note> And therefore we ought by ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rating from them<note n="k" place="margin">2 Cor. 4.17.</note> to reprove their Errours;<note n="l" place="margin">Eph. 5.7, 11, 15.</note> in that our Actions have a Tongue in them, as well as the Corn, Earth, and other inanimate Creatures.<note n="m" place="margin">Pſal. 19.</note> So that though Humiliations and Thankſgivings are Pious and Religious Duties in themſelves, yet when called <pb n="97" facs="tcp:94067:53"/> to advance any unjuſt Intereſt, or to coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance it, our preſence there intitles us to their Sin; (though we abhor it, and the Miniſter at that time preach againſt it) in that the end for which it was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded terminates and ſpecificates the Duty in all ordinary and publick Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation; and makes us give, by our preſence, Offence to the Innocent, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm the Wicked, and partake of their Crimes; ſo as Diſobedience in that caſe is better than Sacrifice.<note n="n" place="margin">1 Sam. 15.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>Nay, I may not only appropriate others Sins<note n="o" place="margin">Pſal. 50.28.</note> by Countenance, Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation, or Imitation, (while liv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,) but may be guilty of Sin in others many thouſand years after I am dead, (as well as I did Sin before I was born) when they ſin by Example or Infuſion derived from me. For as the long precogitation upon any ſin with delight makes it an old and inveterate one before it be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced into Act, ſo another's repetition of any ſin by my Example or Authority (though committed many Ages hence) makes it a new ſin to me, and to increaſe my Damnation; as is deduced moſt juſtly by Divines from the Parable of
<hi>Dives,</hi>
                     <note n="p" place="margin">Luke 16.</note> who reflected upon himſelf (not his Brethren) in his charity.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="98" facs="tcp:94067:54"/>And therefore let us walk with all pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſeneſs,<note n="q" place="margin">Pſal. 119.53.63.</note> hating Evil with a perfect hatred, and doing nothing that either may be made an Argument to confirm others in any evil way or action by our complyance; or be matter of juſt ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dal to the Innocent and ſuffering Party; eſpecially if our Judgments approve it not. For if I ought not to do a good Action, nor favour a good Cauſe, if not of Faith,<note n="r" place="margin">Rom 14.</note> I am much leſs excuſable in countenancing an ill one, my Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in any thing diſſenting. So that none can conſcientiouſly and voluntari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly act with thoſe that uſurp the exerciſe of Supreme Power in any Kingdom, in any thing that gives countenance to ſuch an Authority, or is conducing to the eſtabliſhing or maintaining of it, without contracting the guilt of all thoſe ſins and irregularities the others ſmoothed their way by to that aſſumed Greatneſs. For there are ſo many ways to contract others Crimes, as <hi>Junius</hi> and <hi>Piſcator</hi> obſerves,<note n="s" place="margin">On Iſa. 10.1.</note> that the very Scribe or Notary of an unjuſt decree, though but inſtrumental in it, is threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with a Curſe; a woe being pronoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced both againſt them that decree un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteous decrees, and that write griev<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous things, which the other preſcribed;
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:94067:54"/> as the Prophet expreſſes it. For we are commanded to walk honeſtly toward them that are without,<note n="t" place="margin">1 Pet.
2.12.</note> not giving the leaſt ſcandal in any thing: (What then is their guilt, who make or put on their own Shackles, and twiſt the Hal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter for the ſtrangling of themſelves, by departing from that Rule?) Though we may, in lawful Actions, ſubmit to the Power of Uſurpers, (eſpecially when ſeconded with ſome Coercive Penalty) as in paying of Taxes, compounding for ones own Eſtate in caſe of ſequeſtration, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> where the leaſt evil of Puniſhment only falls under Election; yet we ought not o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe to countenance ſuch a Party, for theſe enſuing Reaſons, which may contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute ſome directions for men to walk by, in the ſad and Labyrinthian turns of theſe times, by ſhewing the unreaſonableneſs of any ſuch Complyance or Diſſimulati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on by our Actings. And,</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Firſt, All compliance in an unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful thing, or that which I believe ſo, and every Act of Diſſimulation, ought to be avoided, as it is oppoſite to ſince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity and truth, which God commands in every Word and Act, there being nothing ſo contrary unto him as a Lye, nor ſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructive of Humane Society; in that our Words are our common Coin, and <pb n="100" facs="tcp:94067:55"/> ought to bear the ſtamp of the heart, both in regard of our Commerce with men, and Tribute we pay in them to God,<note n="u" place="margin">Pſal. 5. Rev. 21.27.</note> nay to our own happineſs;<note n="w" place="margin">Aug. c. 3. Tom. 3. Tho. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quinas 2. 2 qu. 10. Art. 1.</note> yet when Words and Actions are of a double ſignification, and that no other is defrauded, miſ-led, or juſtly ſcanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lized by them, a man may uſe them by way of deſign, though <hi>Opus exterius naturaliter ſignificat intentionem,</hi>
                     <note n="x" place="margin">Aquin. 2. 2. qu 111. Art. 1. 2. Aug in Pſ. 25.</note> as the Woman's of <hi>Tekoah</hi> to <hi>David,</hi>
                     <note n="y" place="margin">2 Sam. 14.</note> and <hi>Nathan,</hi>
                     <note n="z" place="margin">2 Sam. 12.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. Secondly, as it takes away the Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and Crown of Martyrdom and Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering for God and a Good Cauſe, and prevents the exerciſe and manifeſtation of Faith, Patience, Perſeverance, and many other ſaving Graces (contrary to St. <hi>Peter</hi> and St. <hi>Paul</hi> in their whole E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtle.) Yet where there is a lawful means to preſerve my ſelf, I am bound to uſe it, (but not to tempt God by a temptation) in making diſſimulation or outward complyance a way to preſerve my ſelf or Eſtate by; for that were to allow to every man a retreat in all Try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>als, and hold it forth as the Horns of the Altar by which he may be ſaved, and place truth in unrighteouſneſs; though neither Law nor Goſpel ever allowed of ſuch a Diſpenſation, (as to deny a truth, or <pb n="101" facs="tcp:94067:55"/> ſpeak, or act a Lye for ſelf-preſervation;) but <hi>Eliſha</hi> denyed it to <hi>Naaman</hi> the <hi>Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian:</hi>
                     <note n="a" place="margin">2 King.
5.</note> The Prophet's <hi>[Go in Peace]</hi> being nothing but a Civil Farewel to him, no toleration for his bowing in the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of <hi>Rimmon,</hi> though he profeſſed an uprightneſs of heart to the true God. Nay, St.
<hi>Paul</hi> reproved it in St. <hi>Peter,</hi>
                     <note n="b" place="margin">Gal.
2.</note> though but in an Act of Omiſſion, a not doing what he might at ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther times lawfully have forborn, even a not converſing with the
<hi>Gentiles;</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe then proceeding from a ſervile fear it proved ſcandalous, and of ill Example: And if Chriſt, the Morning-Star,
<hi>[vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centi dabitur]</hi> be only given to them that overcome, what hope can they have that yield before the fight?</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Thirdly, All ſeeming outward Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation of, or conſent to any thing that is evil, makes us guilty of all the whole Chain of Sins the firſt Link draws a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long with it. For, if a Robbery in one occaſion a Rape in his Companion, and that a Murther in a third, the firſt Approbation and Complyance in an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawful King, and Confederacy in one e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil makes all three guilty of all thoſe ſins. So if I but once give up my perſon to a free and voluntary Obedience to any unlawful Power, uſurping the Crown
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:94067:56"/> in any thing that conduces to the ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port of it, (though not my heart) I do with <hi>Peter</hi> deny my own Maſter, <hi>(ore, ſi non corde)</hi> and not only forſake <hi>David</hi> for
<hi>Abſolom,</hi> but become guilty of our unnatural Rebellion, and the Innocent Blood it occaſioned the expence of, with all its train of Vices. As
<hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> by countenancing the Perſecution of the Prophets in her time, became guilty of the Blood of all the Righteous that had been ſlain in that Cauſe, from the firſt Martyr <hi>Abel</hi> to the Death of
<hi>Zachari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as.</hi>
                     <note n="c" place="margin">Mat. 23.34, 35.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>For as I may be guilty of murthering one that overlives me, if I comply with the Wicked in deſigning of it, (though it fail in the Event) or but countenance it in the Attempt; ſo may I by an after- Approbation be guilty of a Murther committed a thouſand years before. And therefore we are commanded to ſeparate from <hi>Babylon</hi> in Practice and Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, if we will not partake of her ſins and puniſhments;<note n="d" place="margin">Rev.
18.</note> (as <hi>Daniel</hi> did from the Nation he lived in, though but in a Negative Precept:<note n="e" place="margin">Dan. 3.</note> For, what Communion can light have with dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in what is ill, Chriſt with <hi>Belial,</hi> if we will keep our ſelves void of offence towards God and towards Man?<note n="f" place="margin">Acts 24.</note> 
                     <pb n="103" facs="tcp:94067:56"/> 
                     <hi>Thyatira</hi>'s countenancing of <hi>Jezabel,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing as hateful as <hi>Laodicea</hi>'s lukewarm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.<note n="g" place="margin">Rev. 2. &amp; 3.20.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>So that we ought to reprove and not become guilty of others Crimes by a <hi>ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cite</hi> complyance; but (fearing God and the King, as
<hi>Solomon</hi> commands)<note n="h" place="margin">Prov. 20.19.</note> avoid them that are given to change Loyalty into Licentiouſneſs; Religion into Prophaneneſs; Piety into Policy, Oblations into Ablations;<note n="i" place="margin">Prov. 20.25. Mic. 3.8. Acts 5.3, 5. Rom. 2 22</note> known Laws into Arbitrary Orders; Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy into Anarchical Tyranny; a Virgin into an Harlot, whoſe houſe is the way of Hell, going to the Chambers of Death,<note n="k" place="margin">Prov. 7.27.</note> by the proſtitution of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, Law and Right. For know (ſaith <hi>Solomon</hi>) man's iniquity ſhall take and hold him in the Cords of Death,<note n="l" place="margin">Prov.
5.</note> that wilfully doth what is evil in it ſelf, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil in his Opinion, or generally eſteem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſo of the beſt men,<note n="m" place="margin">Phil.
4.8</note> whether in thought or act.<note n="n" place="margin">Jer. 17. Jam.
1.15.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="4">4. Fourthly, We are the rather to avoid all ſuch Compliance and Diſſimulation, and to walk with all circumſpection, in regard of Man's proneneſs to follow a Multitude to do evil, and to run upon the Byaſs of Popularity or ſelf-intereſt: Eſpecially ſince the Example of great men hath not only a perſwaſive but <pb n="104" facs="tcp:94067:57"/> compulſory Power in it.<note n="o" place="margin">Gal. 2.</note> For he that in Authority countenances one Thief makes many. Nay, he will ſoon do what he ſhould not, that doth all he may law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, not conſidering Expedience. So as rather than for to prejudice or ſcanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lize others, we ought to ſuffer all things,<note n="p" place="margin">2 Tim. 2.10.</note> and rather expoſe our ſelves to all perſonal hazards in a ſtrict walking and ſelf-denyal than comply willingly with the Apoſtatizing Practice of theſe times, charactered by St. <hi>Paul</hi>
                     <note n="q" place="margin">1 Tim 3.</note> and St.
<hi>Jude;</hi> and not only avoid every appearance of evil, but every lawful Action, that may be an inlet to a Temptation to our ſelves or others; when difficulty is the Teſt of true Chriſtianity, which ever makes men (with the Cypreſs-trees) keep their viridity and freſhneſs (their Innocency) in the ſharpeſt Winter, (the greateſt dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers) and (with the Roſe) ſmell beſt in the Still, when on the Fire.</p>
                  <p>So as (with St. <hi>Bernard</hi> to <hi>Eugenius,</hi>
                     <note n="r" place="margin">Baron. de conſid. l. 3.</note>) all our Actions require
<hi>[trinam con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderationem]</hi> a three-fold conſideration, as a moſt learned Divine obſerves to me; an <hi>liceat,</hi> an <hi>deceat,</hi> an
<hi>expediat;</hi> ſo as Diſcretion, Charity, and Edification, muſt be Inrgedients into all our Actions. For, <hi>[Quorum uſus coercetur certis Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiis, ea dicuntur non expedire, non di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuntur <pb n="105" facs="tcp:94067:57"/> non licere.]</hi>
                     <note n="s" place="margin">Cham. 3. Panſtrat.
21.27.</note> All Circumſtances are to be conſidered in lawful things, as Times, Places, Perſons, Meaſures, Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, to the making up of a lawful Action, otherwiſe a right end, without theſe, frees not the Action from being ſinful in the Doer;<note n="t" place="margin">Aug. 4. contra Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian.
3.</note> though lawfulneſs in a ſtrict ſenſe looks but at the nature and quality of the thing it ſelf, expedience at all Circumſtances that conduce to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny end.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. Fifthly, We are to avoid all ſuch Complyance and Diſſimulation, and to be jealous of our ſelves in the leaſt ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow of Evil, leſt by an habitual counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nancing of any evil act, we become worſe than the firſt Authors of it, (who perhaps by their hearty Repentance have endeavoured their reparation) when by my countenancing, owning or main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining any paſt Injuſtice or Oppreſſion, I do not only contract the guilt of the firſt Contrivers of it, (for the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures attribute to one what he approves of in another: So St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi>)<note n="u" place="margin">Serm. 6. de verbo Domini.</note> but entail a Curſe upon my own poſterity by it;<note n="w" place="margin">Exod. 20.5.</note> though the thing was done at firſt without my conſent; nay, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps againſt my will. And thus <hi>Ahab</hi> was the reputed Murderer of <hi>Naboth</hi> by poſſeſſing the Vineyard,<note n="x" place="margin">3 King 20.</note> and not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proving, <pb n="106" facs="tcp:94067:58"/> but actually countenancing his Wifes action.</p>
                  <p>A Preſident for thoſe that now enjoy or purchaſe the Churches or King's Lands and Revenues, and had no other ways to make the Inheritance theirs,<note n="y" place="margin">Mar. 12.</note> but by killing the Heirs, (thoſe Chriſt ſent to poſſeſs them by lawful Title.) Nay the Owner of the ſpoyles is (in my Judgment) in a more dangerous condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, than the firſt Deſigner of the ſin; In that the one cannot conſiſt with Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, (of which Reſtitution is a part) when the other, as a tranſient Act, may be ſorrowed for, though effected in the moſt horrid way of diſſembled holineſs (which makes vertue it ſelf ill-ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of) when Faſting and Prayers are made preparatory to the worſt deſign, putting on moſt of God, when they acted for the Devil.<note n="z" place="margin">Iſ. 29.13. &amp; 19. Jer. 13.13. Ezech. 33.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>1, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="6">6. Sixthly, Diſſimulation or Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyance in evil is to be avoided in regard of that Rectitude we are to maintain in all our Actions: (For what Communion hath Light with Darkneſs?) Therefore, ſaith the Apoſtle, have no fellowſhip with its unfruitful deeds, but reprove them; doing nothing that may bear the appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of evil.<note n="a" place="margin">1 Theſ. 5.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>2.</note> By which all State-Hypocrites and Hermophrodites, that
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:94067:58"/> can ſerve all Sexes and Turns, and (<hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meleon</hi>-like) aſſume all ſhapes, are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned.</p>
                  <p>Wherefore let us walk honeſtly, as in the day, free from all Artificial Um<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brages and Diſguiſes, (unleſs to conceal a truth only which we are not obliged to diſcover) maintaining a Conſcience void of offence towards God and all Men.</p>
                  <p n="7">7. Seventhly, We are to avoid all ſuch Complyance and Diſſimulation, ſince all Aberrations from the Truth and our Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties (whether <hi>Dictum, Factum,</hi> or <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupitum</hi>) are in their own nature Damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble (ſaith St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi>) in that they all ought to be as intenſively pure as our Prayers; eſpecially our Actions, which are to others the Images and Counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parts of our Souls, and ought to be kept innocent in regard of our ſelves. 2. To carry the probability of a fair Interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation. 3. To be free from juſt offence, that we may be blameleſs in the midſt of a crooked Generation,<note n="b" place="margin">Phil. 2.4, 15.
2 Cor. 4.17.</note> and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove our ſelves in much patience in af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction.<note n="c" place="margin">2 Cor. 6.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>For our Actions have a voice in them, ſo as every Diſſimulation, or outward Complyance with any thing ill, ſpeaks me guilty of it to God and men; in <pb n="108" facs="tcp:94067:59"/> that <hi>ſigna exteriora non ſolum ſunt verba, ſed etiam facta; &amp; mendacium eſt falſa ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificatio cum voluntate fallendi:</hi> So as e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very diſſimulation is a ſpecies of a Lye, and can in no caſe be lawfully done; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe,
<hi>omne mendacium eſt peccatum,</hi>
                     <note n="d" place="margin">Aug. l. 4. c.
7. Tom. 5</note> which we are commanded to hate,<note n="e" place="margin">Rom.
12.</note> and to have nothing to do with the ſtool of Wickedneſs, which imagineth miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief, as a Law.<note n="f" place="margin">Pſal. 94.20.</note> For then, <hi>(incipit eſſe licitum, quod ſolet eſſe publicum; &amp; deſinit remedio locus, ubi quoe fuerant vitia mores ſunt:)</hi> when they gather them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves together againſt the Righteous, and condemn the Innocent Blood,<note n="g" place="margin">verſ. 21.</note> ſin becomes natural to them.</p>
                  <p>And that we may the better oppoſe thoſe whom we are not to conform to; nor have any Fellowſhip with,<note n="h" place="margin">Rom. 12.2. Eph. 5.11. 2 Tim. 3. Gala. 5.</note> we muſt put on the whole Armour of God, to withſtand in the evil day,<note n="i" place="margin">Eph. 6.</note> doing all things heartily, as unto God, and not to men,<note n="k" place="margin">Col.
3.23.</note> who are filled with all unrighteouſneſs, and even Diſobedient to Parents, Covenant-breakers, impla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cable, unmerciful,<note n="l" place="margin">Rom. 1.29.30, 31.</note> (all which was foretold ſhould appear in the laſt times, under the pretence of Piety, the Mask or Form of Godlineſs)<note n="m" place="margin">2 Tim. 3.</note> rejecting their King and Prieſts,<note n="n" place="margin">Hoſ. 10.</note> not induring ſound Doctrine, but heaping to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves <pb n="109" facs="tcp:94067:59"/> Teachers;<note n="o" place="margin">2 Tim. 4.3.</note> not called, as <hi>Aaron</hi> was lawfully,<note n="p" place="margin">Heb. 5.</note> nor commiſſioned by any Miſſion from God,<note n="q" place="margin">Rom. 10.</note> to inſtruct his people, and diſpence his Ordinances. And how this is now fulfilled in our Ears he that runs may read. For (as the Key to the Lock its made for, the Print to the Seal) the Text fits the ſtory of theſe times, and is the juſt Character of them<note n="r" place="margin">Hoſ. 5.4<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 2 Tim. 2.19. Iſa.
20.12. Mat. 15.8. Jer. 12.</note> that turn their hearts from God, and their very Devotions into ſin, when by them they ſeek to give Counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance to Wickedneſs.<note n="s" place="margin">Ezek. 33. ver. 30.31, 32,
<hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="8">8. Eighthly, We muſt avoid all things evil or ſcandalous, leſt ſome be with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawn from their duties, and others confirmed in their wicked Practiſes by our ill example, which is the ſhorteſt way of teaching, and, like the ill in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence of Planets, kills moſt deadly. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is it only the moſt perſwaſive Rhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torick and Oratory to weak underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, but many times carries the force of a command, nay of a compulſion in it; (as may appear by the Apoſtle;<note n="t" place="margin">Gal. 2.14.</note> and, like Poyſon in the Blood, (that runs through all the Veins, taints, and diſcolours them) infects the very Air of our Converſation.</p>
                  <p>And therefore on the contrary let us as we ought, rather ſuffer all for the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect's <pb n="110" facs="tcp:94067:60"/> ſake, with St.
<hi>Paul,</hi>
                     <note n="u" place="margin">2 Tim. 10.</note> and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe our ſelves to all perſonal hazards, in a ſtrict walking according to this rule, than comply in any unlawful act againſt Kings; for thoſe are not Children of the moſt Voices, but of the moſt high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt, as hath been ſaid; the Peoples Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation ſerving only <hi>ad Pompam,</hi> but not
<hi>ad neceſſitatem.</hi> (Thus the firſt King <hi>Melchiſedech</hi> was ſaid to have no Father in regard of his Office, to ſhew that Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal Power is an emanation from the Deity it ſelf) and therefore the People cannot depoſe their Kings, nor their Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geny, becauſe they are not of their mak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, (For, <hi>cujus eſt inſtituere, ejus eſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brogare,</hi>) but ſtill owe them Obedience and all things tending to their outward glory and ſupport.</p>
                  <p>But our Royal Soveraign having alſo a Civil Right, by the Municipal Laws of this Nation, both to the Crown and all his other
<hi>Regalia,</hi> Rights and Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nues, none can, but by a complication of many ſins, (as Rebellion, Oppreſſion, and the like) invade him in any of them, nor acquit themſelves from the guilt of it, without oppoſing them that do it by all lawful means; being bound to it by (the Law of God and of this Kingdom) and a Natural Obligation and common <pb n="111" facs="tcp:94067:60"/> Charity, which tyes every man, not only to commiſerate, but relieve another that ſuffers under unjuſt preſſures; ſo as thoſe neutral men, that ſtand upon a ſafe Shore, while the Ship is in danger, and afford it no help, cannot be found guilt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs; becauſe they have not endeavour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to deliver him that had no helper, nor broken the Jaws of the Wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and pulled the Prey out of their Mouth.<note n="w" place="margin">Job. 29<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </note>
                  </p>
                  <p>And if Damnation be to be pronoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced againſt ſins of Omiſſion at the laſt day, as for not helping, not comforting thoſe to whom we owe it, but by a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle Obligation of Charity, what Hell is hot enough for thoſe that act againſt ſo many clear convictions, and endeavour to enforce others to approve of, or ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly to Covenant and engage for, their Tyranny and Oppreſſion; and like thoſe that have a Plague-ſore, deſire to dilate and ſpread their Infection (their ſin) to others, when he that maintains or ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proves of an unlawful act done, repeats it, and ſins it over again, eſpouſes the ſin, and makes it ſo habitually his, as not to admit of any Divorce; but, as he that ſets upon his houſe by Oppreſſion or Injuſtice, entails a Curſe upon it to
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:94067:61"/> the Fourth Generation:<note n="x" place="margin">Exod.
20.5.</note> So he that countenances or confirms another in any unjuſtifiable Action, and always approves it, doth as much as in him lyes to make his whole life but one continued act of Wickedneſs, and entails it upon his Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity.</p>
                  <p>Nay our Charter for Heaven hath this condition in it, That we ſpeak the truth from our hearts,<note n="y" place="margin">Pſ. 15.</note> and in our hearts too, in Words, Actions, and Deſires; for my inclination to a ſin makes me guilty without the Act, (in that there is an Eye-Adultery and a Mental-Idolatry, the Devil's ſingle mony) and the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nivance at (much more complyance with) another's ſin in out-ward appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance makes it mine (and ſo in God's account) though my heart diſ-allow and deteſt it.</p>
                  <p>For every Hypocriſie, Diſſimulation, Guile, and the like, multiplies the ſin, and makes it two to me approving it in any; for I contract both the guilt of the ſin I countenance in another, and the Lye I am guilty of in my ſelf by it; for my Hand, or Eye, or Foot, or any fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctitious Action may tell a lie as well as my Tongue.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="113" facs="tcp:94067:61"/>But then every untruth is not a Lye, when I believe what I ſay upon fair and probable grounds, becauſe <hi>mendacium conſiſtit in voluntate;</hi> every thing having only ſo much more of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinateneſs and obliquity in it, as it departs from what we believe or ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledg to be truth.</p>
                  <p n="9">9. Ninethly, we muſt not comply in any thing ill, nor do the beſt Action, if we believe it bad,<note n="a" place="margin">Rom.
14.23.</note> nor counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance an ill cauſe, though to a good end, in that the man is by it divided, (the heart and the hand moving ſeveral ways) and becomes guilty of diſſembling; which is no leſs (as hath been ſaid) than a real acted Lie; and that every Lie is a ſin, that ought not to be given way to<note n="b" place="margin">Rev. 22.</note> out of the contemplation of the greateſt good, even the ſaving of Souls:<note n="c" place="margin">Rom. 3.8.</note> For the Ark muſt fall rather than be ſupported by <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>zzah</hi>'s hands,<note n="d" place="margin">2 Sam.
6.6.</note> (any undue means) and no Sacrifice muſt be offered to God, rather than Diſobedience:<note n="e" place="margin">1 Sam. 15.</note> So that we muſt be ſure that what we do be not only <hi>bonum,</hi> but <hi>bene,</hi> good in reſpect of the means as well as end. For, with St.
<hi>Auguſtine,</hi> (<note n="f" place="margin">lib. 4 cap 7. tom. 5.</note>
                     <hi>Quod eſt ſecundum ſe malum ex genere nullo modo poteſt eſſe bonum &amp; licitum.</hi> Becauſe (as <hi>Aquinas</hi> ſaith) <hi>ad hoc quod aliquid ſit bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num <pb n="114" facs="tcp:94067:62"/> requiritur quod omnia recte concurrant;</hi> in that <hi>Bonum eſt ex cauſa integra, malum vero ex ſingularibus defectibus:</hi>) A ſingle defect making an Action ſinful, when all Circumſtances are required to concur in a good one; in that,
<hi>omne verum eſt omni vero conſentiens, &amp; quicquid non licet certe non oportet,</hi> (So <hi>Cicero</hi>
                     <note n="g" place="margin">Pro Bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bo.</note>) For <hi>poteſt aliquid licere, &amp; non expedire; ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedire autem, quod non licet, non poteſt.</hi>
                     <note n="h" place="margin">Aug. de Adult. Conjug. cap. 15.</note> So that I will conclude with St.
<hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine,</hi>
                     <note n="i" place="margin">Tom. 4. cap. 10. de mendatio.</note> and <hi>Thomas Aquinas</hi> excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently, <hi>Non licitum mendacium dicere ad hoc quod aliquis alium a quocun<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> periculo li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beraret.</hi> And therefore, with the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Poet Mr. <hi>George Herbert,</hi> let us
<q>
                        <l>Dare to tell truth; there's nothing needs a Ly;</l>
                        <l>A Fault, that needs it moſt, grows two thereby.</l>
                     </q> and let us purifie our hearts,<note place="margin">Jam. 4.8.</note> as well as cleanſe our hands, if we will draw nigh unto God;<note n="k" place="margin">Jer. 17.</note> the Law of God re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiring (an inward univerſality of the Subject) to walk in, as well as an Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal Obedience of the Precept to walk by.</p>
                  <p n="10">10. Tenthly, Yet all this doth not by way of Obligation extend to the <pb n="115" facs="tcp:94067:62"/> ſpeaking of the whole truth at all times, (as in <hi>Abraham</hi>'s calling <hi>Sarah</hi> his Siſter, to diſguiſe his Relation to her as a Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band)<note n="l" place="margin">Gen. 20,</note> when God is not diſhonour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, nor my Brother damnified by it; in that it may be but a concealing of ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing I am not bound to reveal; when
<hi>Mendacium eſt, quippe falſa ſignificatio cum voluntate fallendi.</hi>
                     <note n="m" place="margin">Aug. tom 4. l. 2.</note> And therefore I will conclude with St. <hi>Auguſtine,</hi>
                     <note n="n" place="margin">Tom. 4. cap. 10. de mendacio,</note> it is lawful ſometimes to hide a truth, (nay prudent and good;) but <hi>[non licet]</hi> it is never lawful to tell a Ly, or to commit the leaſt evil for the greateſt good.</p>
                  <p>And for theſe Reaſons let us not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply in any thing that is <hi>malum in ſe,</hi> or <hi>malum quia prohibitum,</hi> or ſo only in our Opinions; but let every man be fully perſwaded in his own mind what he ſhould (or may) do, and not ſwerve from it in his Practice. But in indifferent things the Commands of the lawful Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate ought to caſt the Scale and poyſe him to Obedience; which he ought to ſubmit to in things evenly ballanced, though he may perhaps a little ſcruple or doubt of the lawfulneſs of them. For there he is not his own man, but acts with relation to a further duty; Pater<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Power ſwaying much in ſuch caſes, as we may ſee by an higher example. <pb n="116" facs="tcp:94067:63"/>
                     <note n="o" place="margin">Num. 30.</note> Otherwiſe there cannot be a greater contempt to God, than for a man to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temn the Power of his own Conſcience, (ſaith <hi>Bonaventure,</hi>) or to appear what he is not; every ſimulation being a Ly (as hath been ſhewed) when it hath not ſome ſignification in it more than is expreſſed;<note n="p" place="margin">Aug. tom. 4. lib. 2. Queſt. Evang qu. 51.</note> and the Mouth that lyes ſlayes its own Soul,<note n="q" place="margin">Ezech. 16.</note> in that he dares God, yet fears man.</p>
                  <div n="1" type="objection">
                     <head>OBJECTION I.</head>
                     <p>Obj. 1. <hi>Ay but I deny the Premiſes and Ground of the former Concluſions: For e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Diſſimulation is not unlawful: Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> David's <hi>before the King of</hi> Achiſh, <hi>and</hi> Joſhua's <hi>flying before</hi> Ai. <hi>Nor is eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry appearance in a diſguiſe or ſeeming <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truth a Ly, but in ſome caſes lawful; as in</hi> Joſeph's <hi>Carriage in</hi> Egypt <hi>towards his Brethren, and</hi> Naaman's <hi>bowing in the houſe of</hi> Rimmon, <hi>allowed by the Prophet</hi> Eliſha; <hi>nor are theſe ſo many in-lets as you pretend.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>To this I anſwer.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Anſw.</hi> Firſt, That the lawfulneſs or unlawfulneſs of no Action is to be grounded upon matter of Fact; for no Preſidents of others actings ought to be be an Authority for us to imitate,
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:94067:63"/> though done by the Saints of God them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; in that they are to be conſidered as men (Chriſtianity not deſtroying Humanity) ſubject to many weakneſſes and Infirmities, nay great failings in particular Actions, and may become the more dangerous to others by the emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nency and reputation of the perſon; as that Body is moſt in hazard that hath a confluence of ill and noxious humours harbored under a ſeeming healthful Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexion; which, interrupting the Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of a well-tempered conſtitution, at laſt march under the colours of Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency.</p>
                     <p>Secondly, As to <hi>David</hi>'s Caſe,<note place="margin">1 Sam. 21.</note> 
                        <hi>[r]</hi> I ſay it was no act of diſſimulation, but a prudent aſſuming of a lawful diſguiſe for the preſervation of his life; (for his Heart and Act both concurred in the means he uſed for his eſcape,) and had nothing in it of ſcandal, nor any counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nancing of any thing evil, or of prejudice to any, but only a concealing of himſelf, and appearing as one that wanted the uſe of his underſtanding at that time, that he might the better enjoy and uſe it, when freed from his Enemies.</p>
                     <p>Thirdly, To the Inſtance of <hi>Joſhua</hi>'s fleeing before <hi>Ai,</hi> I anſwer, It was law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, being a Stratagem of War, having <pb n="118" facs="tcp:94067:64"/> nothing of diſſimulation in it. For as he had to do with Enemies, ſo the uſing of all Circumventions, and taking of all advantages was lawful to conquer them by (even by the Law of Arms and Nations) as well as force; and no more than all profeſſed Enemies mutu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally profeſs and expect. For though all Capitulations, Contracts, and Promiſes muſt be Religiouſly obſerved with Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies when made, (as long as War is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced and continued,) Circumventions as well as Force are allowable; as in uſing their Colours, and the like, to bring them into Ambuſh; or with the
<hi>Romans</hi> to throw Bread out of their beſieged Capitol to the
<hi>Gaules,</hi> to diſguiſe their want when they were ready to famiſh, that the Conditions of Surrender might be the better; which St.
<hi>Auguſtine</hi> with the Fathers and Schoolemen allow: though no Covenant made is ever to be broken with any, (where the violation is not firſt on the others part;) for then there can be no faith nor ſecurity in any thing, nor commerce, nor contract between men; and that breach of Faith made the
<hi>Trojans,</hi> who could not be conquered by War, to be overcome by a pledge of Peace, when the Mask was taken for the Man, as in <hi>Abſolom.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <pb n="119" facs="tcp:94067:64"/>Fourthly, I grant that every ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing untruth is not a Ly, (nor every un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truth it ſelf; for, <hi>mentiri eſt contra men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem ire;</hi> ſo that if I ſpeak a Falſhood, and believe it true, I yet do not tell a Ly:) nor can diſſimulation or Falſhood be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted to <hi>Joſeph,</hi> either in his repreſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the perſon of an
<hi>Egyptian,</hi> or ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſing his Brothers for Spyes, or <hi>Benja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min</hi> for his Cup,<note n="t" place="margin">Gen. 42. &amp; 43.
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </note> becauſe both his Words and Actions were for his Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>threns advantage, and in their Interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations and conſequence ſignificant of his intentions to bring them to him, though they were ſomething dark and myſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous in themſelves, after the manner of the Prophets, and uſe of all Nations; whoſe Actions are ſometimes like the Hieroglyphicks, which make every Fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſpeak a Precept, and every Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance to ſignifie ſomething to men of ſenſe; ſo as all Ironies, Hyperbolical Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions, Diſguiſes, nay Reſervations of a truth are juſtly to be exempt from the nature of a Lye in ſome caſes, the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures being full of them.</p>
                     <p>For though my Tongue ſhould be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways in my heart, my heart needs not to be always in my Tongue. I may conceal a truth, not tell a Ly, being not always bound to diſcover my ſelf in Dangers
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:94067:65"/> or Tryals, where God's Honour, or ſome duty to his revealed Will exacts it not. So that St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> determines in
<hi>Joſeph</hi>'s caſe,<note n="u" place="margin">Lib. Qu. ſuper Gen. Q.
45.</note> and ſaith, <hi>Mendacium eſt enunciantis cum voluntate falſum enun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciandi,</hi> or, <hi>cum voluntate fallendi.</hi>
                        <note n="w" place="margin">Lib. de vera inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centia.</note> For <hi>Abraham,</hi> by calling his Wife Siſter, <hi>[x]</hi> would not be known to be her Husband,<note place="margin">Gen. 20</note> for fear of <hi>Abimelech;</hi> though ſhe was both Siſter and Wife to him.</p>
                     <p>And thus our Saviour concealed his going up to
<hi>Jeruſalem</hi> from the <hi>Samari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tans</hi> when asked the queſtion,<note n="y" place="margin">Mat. 9.</note> by ſaying, His hour was not yet come, (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the period of time was not then accompliſhed he fix'd upon for his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move) though the Text ſaith he went immediately, and that<note n="z" place="margin">Luke 24.28, 29.</note> to his Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples (for the Tryal of their Affections, or perhaps intending it, if their impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunities had not interpoſed;) he made as if he would have gone further and have left them, when he yet ſtayed in the next Village with them.</p>
                     <p>By all which we are taught, That Pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty is no Enemy to Prudence, though it no ways countenance Diſſimulation, Equivocation, or any the leaſt ill or unlawful Action in any: So that St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> in
<hi>Abraham</hi>'s caſe,<note n="a" place="margin">Lib. Qu. ſuper Gen.
4.46.</note> and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that action of our Saviour's,<note n="b" place="margin">Qu. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vang. l. 2. qu. 41.</note> 
                        <hi>Quae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>libet
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:94067:65"/> fictio non dicitur eſſe mendacium. Fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xit ſe longius ire Dominus; non enim quod fingimus mendacium eſt, ſed quando id fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gimus quod nihil ſignificat. Cum autem fictio noſtra refertur ad aliquam ſignifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionem, non eſt mendacium, ſed aliqua fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gura veritatis.</hi> As <hi>Nathan</hi>'s Parable to <hi>David,</hi>
                        <note n="c" place="margin">Aug. l. de mendacio cap. 5.</note> and Chriſt's of the loſt Sheep, and loſt Groat, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Fifthly, To that of <hi>Naaman</hi>'s bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the in Temple of <hi>Rimmon</hi> before the Idol (not to it) I ſay,</p>
                     <p n="1">1. It was not only a ſingle but mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiplied ſin; (and no ways tolerated by the Prophet;) for, like <hi>Ezekiel</hi>'s Wheels,<note place="margin">2 King. 5.</note> one moved within the other; when firſt his acting againſt his Conſcience (if he be preſumed to have done what he asks a merciful diſpenſation for) drew him to an outward diſſimulation (in ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing what he was not in heart) by countenancing Idolatry. Secondly, To a ſcandal of the Godly. And Thirdly, To a confirmation of the <hi>Pagan</hi> Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhippers in their Idol-ſervice to their falſe Gods; which was a ſin <hi>prohi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitum quia malum,</hi> and ſo cannot ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionally be preſumed to have had any diſpenſation from the Prophet, (though for the gaining of <hi>Naaman</hi> to the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of the true God) when their Dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation <pb n="122" facs="tcp:94067:66"/> is juſt that ſay, <hi>Let us do evil, that good may come,</hi>
                        <note n="e" place="margin">Rom. 3.8.</note> or that Gods needs ſuch humane Artifices, when men and Beaſts take their Prey by craft.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. The Prophet's ſaying <hi>[go in peace]</hi> was but a civil Farewell, after the cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom of that Nation, no allowance of
<hi>Naaman</hi> in that ſin, nor at all taking no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of his intention; becauſe perhaps his reproof might then prove unſeaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable to his new Convert, who (as our Saviour ſaith of his Diſciples, when he had other things to declare unto them after their firſt Converſion) could not bear it, being but an Infant in Grace; a new-born <hi>Proſelyte,</hi> capable only of milk, (the firſt Principles of Religion) not ſtrong meat; in that it would ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther turn into corruption and a ſurfeit to endanger, then nouriſh the man; ſo as it was in the Prophet a prudent ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence only for that time, no connivance at his intended errour.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. As <hi>Naaman</hi>'s bowing was ſinful in it ſelf, and ſo in his Opinion (elſe why did he beg pardon in that particular from God?) out of the conviction of a na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Conſcience, in that even to ſuch what is not of Faith is Sin,<note n="f" place="margin">Rom.
14.23.</note> I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the Prophets <hi>[Go in Peace]</hi> might have the nature of a Reproof in it, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <pb n="123" facs="tcp:94067:66"/> as much as if he ſhould have ſaid, Well, ſince you find a check of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience at it, as a thing that needs a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, why do you not rather decline it (as you ought) than interrupt the Calm, Tranquillity and Harmony of a quiet mind, in which peace I wiſh you ſtill to go forward, (by ſaying <hi>Go in Peace</hi>) with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out raiſing any ſuch Earthquake or Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motion in your ſelf.</p>
                     <p n="4">4. In <hi>Naaman</hi>'s Caſe, matter of juſt ſcandal was taken off (as ſome conceive) in that he publickly profeſſed his diſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowance of the Idol-Worſhip, and ſo could not confirm the Wicked, offend the Godly, nor miſguide others by his performing of a Civil Duty; ſo as the Prophet might be thought rather to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctifie a tender Conſcience, by his words, than tolerate a ſin,<note n="g" place="margin">Aug. Pſ. 5.</note> when <hi>Naaman</hi>'s intention was only to bow Civilly, not Religiouſly, with his King, not to the Idol.</p>
                     <p n="5">5. Laſtly, Admit the Prophet did diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſe with
<hi>Naamans</hi> civil bowing, as ſome conceive in reſpect of his late Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, being immediately commiſſioned by God for it in a thing not
<hi>malum in ſe,</hi> (who as the Supreme Law-giver could only diſpence with his own commands;) if any man ſhall by that example pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:94067:67"/> to do what <hi>Naaman</hi> did, he doth not as
<hi>Naaman</hi> did, unleſs he have the ſame Warrant, without which none ought ſeemingly to partake of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers ſins,<note n="h" place="margin">Eph.
5.7.11.</note> but rather reprove them, walking with all Circumſpection in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of the ſeveral ways they are to be contracted; though there are (as the Schools call them) <hi>[peccata compenſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>va]</hi> profitable ſins, as in the <hi>Egyptian</hi> Midwifes ſaving the <hi>Hebrews</hi> Children by a Ly: But I commend only their Obedience to God, in not killing, not their excuſe which needed pardon: Their Mercy was recompenced, their Ly not approved: Nor ſhall we ever be juſtified in the leaſt degree of ſinning,<note n="i" place="margin">1 Tim. 5.22.</note> which may be contracted many ſecret ways, and more than moſt men uſually apprehend. And therefore we ought to be very cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious of contracting ſin, there are ſo many avenues to it: as,</p>
                     <p n="1">1. <hi>Conſulendo,</hi> By adviſing others in evil, as <hi>Achitophel</hi> did <hi>Abſolom</hi> to make good his Treaſon and Rebellion againſt <hi>David;</hi> but ſuch ſhall be taken in their own ſnare and periſh in and by their own counſels, ſaith
<hi>Solomon.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="2">2. <hi>Adulando,</hi> By feeding other Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and nurſing them up with the milk of Flattery, in calling good evil, and
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:94067:67"/> evil good,<note n="k" place="margin">Iſa. 5.20.</note> which is a beautifying of a people (as the <hi>Pagan</hi> Negroes by painting) with Ink inſtead of Colours,<note n="l" place="margin">Iſa. 9.16,</note> to which the greateſt woe belongs; though the Wicked may bleſs for a time whom God abhorreth.<note n="m" place="margin">Pſ. 10.3,</note>
                     </p>
                     <p n="3">3. <hi>Mandando,</hi> So <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>riah</hi>'s Murder and Drunkenneſs were <hi>David</hi>'s ſins, though effected by others.</p>
                     <p n="4">4. <hi>Conſentiendo,</hi> For thus <hi>Saul</hi> became guilty of <hi>Stephen</hi>'s Martyrdom.<note n="n" place="margin">Act.
22.20.</note> And therefore, <hi>If ſinners entice thee conſent thou not.</hi>
                        <note n="o" place="margin">Pro. 1.10.</note> For, <hi>ſentient eandem poenam qui conſentiunt in eandem culpam.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="5">5. <hi>Provocando,</hi> By inflaming or inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing others to ſin, as the Harlot in the <hi>Proverbs;</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Pro.
7,</note> for by ſetting any others houſe on Fire, we are ſure to burn and conſume our own, if contiguous to it, and be anſwerable for the other's damage.</p>
                     <p n="6">6. <hi>Participando,</hi> For if thou ſeeſt a Thief attempting to ſteal, and haſt a pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to hinder him and doeſt it not, thou art guilty of his Crime: The not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venting a ſin in another, where I may do it lawfully, being a promoting of it: And then <hi>[aequum eſt ut qui participes fuerunt in peccato participes fiant in ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicio]</hi> it is but juſt that we ſuffer in the puniſhment, if we partake in the ſin:<note n="q" place="margin">Rev. 18.4</note> For ſo Wrath came upon
<hi>Jehoſhaphat</hi> 
                        <pb n="126" facs="tcp:94067:68"/>
                        <note n="r" place="margin">2 Chro. 19.2.</note> becauſe he helped the Ungodly, and loved them that hated the Lord, when a good wiſh to a bad action is a partaking of the evil.<note n="s" place="margin">2 Joh.
5.11.</note>
                     </p>
                     <p n="7">7. <hi>Omittendo vel connivendo,</hi> by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niving at or not reproving others;<note n="t" place="margin">Eph. 5.11. Lev. 5. Ezech.
3.</note> ſuch a Love and Indulgence to my Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther being the greateſt hatred;<note n="u" place="margin">Lev. 19.17.</note> as God hates us moſt when he ſeems not to hate us at all, by reproving and correct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing us, but ſuffers us to go on in a courſe of ſin.<note n="w" place="margin">Iſa.
1.</note>
                     </p>
                     <p n="8">8. <hi>Defendendo,</hi> For he that defends or maintains a bad Cauſe or Action eſpouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the guilt of it; in that, He that ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifyeth the Wicked or condemneth the Juſt is abominable before or unto God,<note n="x" place="margin">Prov. 27.15.</note> and becomes the greater ſinner, in that it hath more of deliberation, and perhaps leſs of Temptation in it than the other had.</p>
                     <p n="9">9. <hi>Praecedendo,</hi> By giving ill example. For if I pluck up the firſt pale in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers Incloſure, and engage others by my Example to lay it waſte and common, I am guilty of their Treſpaſs; as he that wilfully makes or inlarges any cuts in a Sea-bank is liable to repair the damages any receives by thoſe Waters. For thus <hi>Jeroboam</hi> made
<hi>Iſrael</hi> to ſin (ſaith the Text) even <hi>exemplum dando,</hi> as well as <hi>imperan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do,</hi> and <hi>Peter</hi> the <hi>Jews.</hi>
                        <note n="y" place="margin">Gal. 2.</note>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <pb n="127" facs="tcp:94067:68"/>And to theſe I might add many other ways (as a learned Divine hath obſerv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to me) by which we derive others ſins upon our ſelves; but is not this e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to make us vigilant over our Souls, ſince there are ſo many Avenues for ſin to approach us, and that it is of ſo ſubtil and inſinuating a nature, as (tho the Guards be never ſo well kept) it will ſometimes enter by a falſe paſs, or glide in by the advantage of that gloo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my darkneſs that over-ſhadows the beſt men? So as we need add (ballaſt to our ſail) Examination to every Action, to poiſe and prove it by; it being a ſafe and noble, no melancholy thing (as one wittily obſerves) to be always in plough<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, weeding and worming a Conſcience, in removing (Straws as well as Loggs) occaſions of Temptations, by trying and teſting every thought, word and work to make them currant, by filing the I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron and melting the Ore, to clear and ſmooth the greateſt difficulties, leſt our ſpungy ſouls, apt to (receive any Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quor) ſuck in and embrace any ſin, ſwell us into ſuch an immenſe body of ſin, as (through cuſtom or impenitency) ſhould become too big to enter into the
<hi>Betheſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da</hi> of Chriſt's Blood, (when what comes there is ever cleanſed and cured.)</p>
                     <p>
                        <pb n="128" facs="tcp:94067:69"/>And therefore, though prudence in declining evils of puniſhment be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded<note n="z" place="margin">Mat.
10.16.</note>, it muſt always be with In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocency: So as <hi>prudens ſimplicitas</hi> is the greateſt Policie and beſt Fort to retreat to in all dangers, when the leaſt ungirt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a man's ſelf (or allowed liberty) in any thing evil, by outward complyan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces or diſguiſes, is but a proſtitution of him to contempt, and would inſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure the Intereſts of all men, and make all things uneaſie to them in matters of Truſt and Confidence, the period (as one ſaith) of cares, and only Pillow of reſt for man's Spirit, when a pleaſing entertainment to the Senſes, may, as a Chamber of death, and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gazine of Corruption, become by its ſtench Poyſon to the Brain; and ſurely no man is the better for anothers artifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial ſweetneſs, that feels the noiſomneſs of his putrid and corrupted Lungs break in upon him through the thin Cloud of a perfumed breath. And he that ſtrowes a Pits mouth with Flowers and covers it with an Icy-cruſt (inſtead of a Criſtal Pavement) for others fall and ruine, hath but more of Artifice, not leſs of Malice than a profeſſed Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, but is more dangerous and deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive to all Humane Society; ſo as diſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulation
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:94067:69"/> is in no caſe to be allowed, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ill in it ſelf, and the parent of ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny miſchiefs.</p>
                     <p>Queſt. 1. <hi>But admit God ſhould for our Sins give us up for a time to the Arbitra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Tyranny of our State-Deformers, and permit,</hi> de facto, <hi>a change in the face, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a total Metamorphoſis in our Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, how far may we obey?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Anſw.</hi> Why then men may in refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to their Power (while it continues and they command lawful things) obey; but not to the Authority. For once ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit of a Conſcientious Obedience as due to an Uſurped Power, no State in the World ſhall ever be free from the Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherous Practiſes and daring Attempts of ambitious Spirits, or be left means to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover their juſt Rights, if loſt, when Power of Arms ought only to ſupport the juſt Power of Princes, and not by Power to ſet up an Illegal and Uſurped one.</p>
                     <p>Yet Conqueſt ſometimes, if grounded upon a juſt War (which cannot be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween King and Subjects) may challenge a Conſcientious Obedience, as well as a King that comes to a Crown by a juſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcent, (as ours;) yet the perſons of ſuch many times raiſe a Title from common, Humane and Municipal Laws alſo, to <pb n="130" facs="tcp:94067:70"/> their Subjects Obedience, and many times by a mixture of both Humane and Divine, weave the ſtrongeſt Thread; men being always more ready and prone to conform to their own than God's Laws. And therefore it was the wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of our former Monarchs, compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſively to engage their People (in the ſeveral Repreſentatives) to all thoſe Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes they were to be governed by; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituting their Parliaments of the three Eſtates of Men; Clergy, Nobles, and Commons; by that temper and even poyſe of Power (in regard of the exerciſe of it) to bring in all to a chearful Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, when their known Laws were the known Boundaries and middle things between Supreme Power and Common Right: By this, exrtacting, as it were, the pureſt Eſſence and Spirits out of all other Forms of Government, to make one perfect one, including the reſt; as man doth the Inferiour Creatures, hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing reaſon proper to himſelf, ſenſe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon with Bruits, and Vegetation with Plants; for thus we have Monarchy in our King, Ariſtocracy in the Houſe of Peers, and Democracy in the Houſe of Commons. And to prevent any exor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitancies in any one, all muſt concur to the making any Law, with the King's <pb n="131" facs="tcp:94067:70"/> aſſent, not otherwiſe; and let him that affects either Arbitrary Power or Parity, but begin it in his own houſe, and he will never wiſh it ſhould ſpread into the State of which he is a Member.</p>
                     <p>Queſt. 2. <hi>But may I not act under an <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurped Power, or a Power I conceive to be ſo, nor ſeemingly comply to preſerve my ſelf?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Anſw.</hi> No, not in any caſe to own the Authority, but Power: I am paſſive under ſome compulſion, and that in lawful things.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="objection">
                     <head>OBJECTION II.</head>
                     <p>Object. 2. <hi>But if a People depoſe their lawful King, (for a Tyrannical and exor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitant uſe of a juſt Power, or to preſerve Religion it ſelf) be it by War or otherwiſe; and by aſſuming the Power, place it in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, or one, that wholly imployes it for the maintenances of the true Religion and juſt exerciſe of the known Laws, may I law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully and conſcientiouſly obey him?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Anſw.</hi> That it is not lawful to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge ſuch an Authority juſt, and in that notion to obey it, becauſe the Supreme Power in any one Perſon is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rived from God, and is Paternal, found<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in <hi>Adam</hi> upon Natural and Paternal <pb n="132" facs="tcp:94067:71"/> Principles, never collated by man, but is abſolute and unlimitted in regard of Humane Influences upon it in its firſt collation,<note n="c" place="margin">1 Sam. 8.</note> though limited in reſpect of Divine Precept,<note n="d" place="margin">Deut. 17.</note> in regard of Exerciſe, and ſometimes by National and Municipal Laws; (through the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgence of good Princes) yet Kings are never ſubject to the Coactive but Dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive Power of them, and anſwerable unto God only (as <hi>David</hi> was,<note n="e" place="margin">Pſal. 51.</note> not to man for their violation,) from whom they hold their Commiſſion.<note n="f" place="margin">Prov. 8.25. Rom. 13. 1 Pet.
2. Hoſ. 13.11.</note> And therefore by Precept they are exempt in their Perſons from all other Powers,<note n="g" place="margin">Prov. 21.3. &amp;
8.15. Eccleſ. 8. 1 Pet. 2. Rom. 13.</note> as immediately deſigned by God in their individual perſons to be obeyed,<note n="h" place="margin">Deut.
17.15. Job 3.6, 7. &amp; 34.30. Hoſ. 13.11. Wiſd. 6.3.</note> with a brand and deſert of puniſhment upon all thoſe that reſiſt or rebel againſt them,<note n="i" place="margin">1 Sam. 8. Num. 16. 2 Sam. 1.4. &amp;
15.15.</note> as if done againſt God;<note n="k" place="margin">Rom. 13.</note> when our Prayers, Tribute, Reverence, Aſſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, and Obedience are an Homage we owe them, though Wicked and Tyrants, (where the Divine Providence concurs with other juſt, mediate, inſtrumental ways for the making their Titles law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful)<note n="l" place="margin">1 Tim. 2.2. Jer. 25.9. &amp; 29.7. Dan.
3.21. Gen. 20.27. Mat. 22.21. 1 Sam. 8. &amp; 24. 1 Pet. 2.27.</note> as they are God's breathing I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages, the Mortal Pictures of the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortal God, ſaith
<hi>Optatus,</hi> even Gods before men,<note n="m" place="margin">Pſ.
82.6.</note> though men before God. Firſt, By Analogie. Secondly,
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:94067:71"/> Deputation. Thirdly, Participation. So
<hi>Tertullian,</hi>
                        <note n="n" place="margin">Lib. de Scapul.</note>
                        <hi>Cyrill,</hi>
                        <note n="o" place="margin">Epiſt. ad Theod. prefix. lib. adverſ. Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian.</note> 
                        <hi>Hierom,</hi>
                        <note n="p" place="margin">Ad Pap. An<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>i Greg. l. 9. decret. 1 Tim 3.3.</note> &amp;c.</p>
                     <p>Nay, this truth hath been derived to us from all Antiquity as well as Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and was never contradicted till the <hi>Romaniſts</hi> and <hi>Schiſmaticks,</hi> (like <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meon</hi> and <hi>Levi,</hi> Brethren in Iniquity) as <hi>Samſon</hi>'s Foxes, concurred (though looking contrary wayes) to the ſetting all <hi>Criſtendom</hi> on Fire by it, and broach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the contrary Doctrine. As <hi>Buchanan</hi>
                        <note n="q" place="margin">De Jure Regis apud Scotos.</note> and <hi>Bellarmine,</hi>
                        <note n="r" place="margin">De Rom. Pont. l. 5.</note> though all an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquity be againſt them, as
<hi>Calvin</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgeth,<note n="s" place="margin">Inſt. l. 4. c.
20.</note> and as appears by mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titudes of Authors both ancient and Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dern.<note n="t" place="margin">Gloſ. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cog. in Pſ. 50. R.P. dedicated to Tho. de Trugil. Loranus. in Pſ. 50. Hieron. Ep. 22. &amp; 46. So St. Chryſoſt. in Pſ. 50. as cited by Cyril. So Cyprian ad Nova<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian. Ambroſ. Serm. 16. in Pſ. 118. Clemens Alex. l. 4. c. 6. Turrecre. 1 Sum. de Ec. 1. Q 92</note> Which ought to convince our late <hi>Statiſts</hi> (the
<hi>Corahs, Dathans</hi> and <hi>Abirams</hi> of theſe times) of their Errours, and ſatisfie all men, that the perſon in whom the Supreme Power is placed, cannot by any Tyrannical Act, or In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troducing Hereſie, forfeit his Right; and that none ought nor can Conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiouſly obey it in another, that aſſumes or accepts it from an unjuſt Collation, though for the beſt ends imaginable.</p>
                     <p>Yet if the Objection be ſtill framed and preſſed (as I ſuppoſe it is) by the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors in our preſent troubles (the ſad ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects whereof are but the Airy Off-ſpring <pb n="134" facs="tcp:94067:72"/> of their Platonick Speculations, a wild and wiſe folly) they may receive a fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſatisfaction from our known Laws, (as may be ſeen in <hi>Bracton</hi> and all our ancient Sages) the Oaths of Supremacy and Allegiance, and our King's juſt Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, acknowledged by all <hi>Carolus Dei Gratia,</hi> not by the Peoples Suffrage; his Coronation not making but declaring him King only. Nor ought it to be o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe in Popular States, where, by Univerſal Suffrage and conſent, the People have lawfully placed the exerciſe of the Supreme Power in many (retain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the <hi>eſſe,</hi> perhaps, not <hi>bene eſſe,</hi> of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment) there being no riſing up, or oppoſition lawful againſt the Supreme Power, or thoſe we conceive lawful Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates.<note n="u" place="margin">Rom. 13.</note>
                     </p>
                     <p>Now upon theſe grounds (that the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme Power is not Originally, Funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentally, and radically in the People, but in that ſingle Perſon God hath by Preſcription, Succeſſion, and Inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, or other Humane Rights commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioned for it) there is no juſt means of aſſuming it into the People, and their transferring it upon any; nor can any ſuch act be lawful, whether by the Pomp and Artifice of a pretended Juſtice, or the Power of the Sword; both which <pb n="135" facs="tcp:94067:72"/> do but heighten the Crime, according to the weight of Circumſtances in ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; the one clothing the Devil in the Robes of Juſtice and Majeſty; the other making the Sword the unjuſt Arbitrator over the Lives, Liberties, and Fortunes of many innocent perſons, without any lawful Power,<note n="w" place="margin">Mat. 26. Joh. 10.10.</note> and againſt all our known Municipal Laws; when in ſuch a caſe no Title of Conqueſt can ly; for that muſt be ever grounded upon a juſt War, which is alwayes conſtituted of theſe eſſential parts. 1. A Juſt Power. 2. A Juſt Cauſe. 3. Juſt means to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecute it. None of which can concur in Subjects taking up Arms againſt their lawful Soveraign, or Warrant Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to any other, without countenanc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Injuſtice, Violence, Oppreſſion, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                        <note n="x" place="margin">Mat. 26. &amp; 22, 24. Joh. 19.10.</note> which is in no caſe lawful; no diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſation being lawful to any Action that partakes of the nature of ſin.</p>
                     <p>For with the Hypocrite, to do a ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing good, to let in or countenance any evil (for the moſt pious ends) is but to bring in Religion upon the Devil's Shoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, and follow a ſeeming Triumph to Hell.</p>
                     <p>So as all that can be done under ſuch a Government is but a prudent ſubmiſſion to the Power in things indifferent, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:94067:73"/> giving any countenance to the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority that impoſes it, or juſt ſcandal to our weak Brethren. For then even lawful and indifferent things in their nature, are not at all times expedient to be done, ſaith St. <hi>Paul;</hi>
                        <note n="y" place="margin">1 Corin. 6.12.</note> as in the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances of eating or not eating;<note n="z" place="margin">1 Corin.
8.13.</note> but we may or may not, according to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Circumſtances. For,</p>
                     <p n="1">1. A thing indifferent may become in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eligible unto me, in regard of uſe or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe, where a lawful Power interpoſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing determines my choice either way, if the thing be equally indifferent, and ſtand, like the Pin in the Ballance, in an even poyſe; (all Obedience to the Supreme Magiſtrate depending in its juſt latitude upon things indifferent to be done, or omitted;) upon which ground (as a learned man obſerves) God made choice of a Fruit in Paradice, indifferent in its own nature to be eaten or refuſed, for the tryal of man's Obedience in the State of Innocency, to teach us that the interpoſing of a Command from a juſt Authority ought in all things indifferent to determine our choice; and by mak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it a duty takes off all juſt cauſe of ſcandal to others; for in this way ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dal is taken, not given; in the other I am guilty of Diſobedience to my Supe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour, <pb n="137" facs="tcp:94067:73"/>
                        <note n="a" place="margin">Rom. 13.</note> as my Magiſtrate, of ſcandal to him, as my Brother, and of ill exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to all if I do the contrary.</p>
                     <p>Though my choice may, nay ought to be determined in the uſe of an indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent thing, rather than break a rule of Charity in the doing or not doing it; as in the Inſtance before of eating or not eating of Fleſh at any time to the ſcandal of my weak Brother,<note n="b" place="margin">1 Cor. 8.</note> when free in the <hi>aequilibrium</hi> of choice. Yet if any neceſſity of nature, or other great prejudice to my Perſon or Fortune de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pends upon my not eating, I ought to eat Fleſh though to the ſcandal of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, rather than impair my health, or bring any great miſchief upon my ſelf by the Omiſſion of it. For there, though the thing be indifferent in it ſelf, it is not ſo to me, ſuch Natural or Moral Neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty interpoſing.</p>
                     <p>From whence I conceive I may ſafely conclude againſt the former Objection, That no conſcientious Obedience is due to ſuch an exerciſe of Power as is there propoſed; (no nor ſubmiſſion in indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent things, if done with ſcandal to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, becauſe not impoſed by a lawful Power to determine my choice;) yet where my perſonal freedom, ſelf-preſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or any great prejudice to my Eſtate
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:94067:74"/> (in which my Poſterity is concerned) be put into the Scale to weigh againſt an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willing ſcandal, I may ſubmit; for that alters the caſe in relation to Conſcience, though not the nature of the thing; for there I owe a prudent ſubmiſſion, when by the rule of Charity (which is but to love my Neighbour as my ſelf) I am to prefer the well being of my ſelf and mine to an offence taken by, not willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly given to another; where a compulſory Injunction and Power inforceth my ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion to an indifferent thing; it being agreeable to the Law of God, Nature, and Nations, to preſerve my ſelf by all lawful ways.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="objection">
                     <head>OBJECTION III.</head>
                     <p>Object. 3. <hi>If it be ſo that honeſt and well-meaning men may not be in any caſe vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntarily inſtrumental under an uſurped and unlawful Power to the executing the known Laws, by which diſtributive Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice between Party and Party, Religion, Peace and Propriety may be maintained, and perhaps ſome advantages gained, by which they may much improve the Intereſt of their lawful Soveraign, (which they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer in their wiſhes to their own Being) and that if they decline a making uſe of ſuch oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunities, and that all men ſhould walk by the <pb n="139" facs="tcp:94067:74"/> ſame Rule, there muſt neceſſarily follow Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion, Atheiſm and Anarchy, the Womb of all Confuſion, that would reduce all things into the firſt Chaos ſo as nothing but darkneſs and diſorder would cover the Earth, which their Omiſſions may contract the guilt of, when, in acting with the preſent Power for theſe ends, they do but chooſe the leaſt of Evils, and have no thought of doing the leaſt Evil, and ſo may act.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Anſw.</hi> As I ſaid, The leaſt Evil is not to be committed nor allowed, to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce the greateſt good:<note n="c" place="margin">Rom. 3.8.</note> and that there the choice is not between Evils of Puniſhments where the leaſt may be cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen; but between an Evil of Sin (which I have proved an outward Compliance in an Unjuſt Cauſe, or with an Uſurped or unlawful Power, eſpecially againſt a juſt claim to be) and no Sin, being (as the Schools determine) in the number of things eligible. (<hi>Malum non eſt in numero eligibilium propter aliud bonum,</hi> in that,
<hi>actus peccati non eſt ordinabilis in bonum finem.</hi> So <hi>Thomas Aquinas</hi>
                        <note n="d" place="margin">2. 2. Qu. 110. Art. 3.</note>). And upon the <hi>Egyptian</hi> Midwives, and <hi>Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chels</hi> Pious Ly; it is concluded by St <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine,</hi>
                        <note n="e" place="margin">ſup Pſ. 5.</note>
                        <hi>Peter Lombard,</hi>
                        <note n="f" place="margin">Lib. 3. diſt. 38.</note> and
<hi>Thomas Aquinas,</hi>
                        <note n="d" place="margin">2. 2. Qu. 110. Art. 3.</note> That no man ought to tell a Ly to preſerve a Life, nor for any Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Good. Though St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſaith <pb n="140" facs="tcp:94067:75"/> wittily,<note n="g" place="margin">Tract. 5. Tom. 9. ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Joan.</note>
                        <hi>Nemo habet de ſuo, niſi mendacium &amp; peccatum;</hi> when all truth comes from the Fountain of it, God.<note n="h" place="margin">Eccleſ. 7. Jam.
1.</note> And St. <hi>Ambroſe</hi>
                        <note n="i" place="margin">Tom. 4.</note> (upon thoſe words, <hi>Quis ex vobis arguit me de peccato?) Omne mendacium fugiendum eſt tam in ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis quam in operibus,</hi> &amp;c. all outward diſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulation is to be avoided; when <hi>Opus exterius naturaliter ſignificat intentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem.</hi>
                        <note n="k" place="margin">Aquin. 2. 2. Qu. 111. Art. 11. Qu. 111. Art. 2.</note>
                     </p>
                     <p>And we ſhould be the more careful not to make Hell the way to Heaven, (Vice to introduce Vertue) when even lawful Actions become ſins, if done with ſcandal to others, and that ſome higher end or duty determine not my choice in them (as I have determined in another caſe of Conſcience concerning Actions in themſelves indifferent:) For the leaſt defect or exceſs makes a lawful Action become ſinful; and a willing countenancing of any ſin draws on the toleration of all, and like the Spirits in the Blood, will ſoon run through the whole Body of ſin. For, with
<hi>Aquinas,</hi>
                        <note n="l" place="margin">2. 2. Qu. 110. Art. 2.</note>
                        <hi>veritas aequalis eſt, cui per ſe opponi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur magis &amp; minus.</hi> So as in doubtful Caſes <hi>Gerſon</hi>'s rule is good,<note n="m" place="margin">Par. 2. Reg. mor.</note> 
                        <hi>(Ab omni actu, cui non eſt neceſſario aſtrictus, teneatur deſiſtere)</hi> where ſcandal may be given.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="4" type="objection">
                     <pb n="141" facs="tcp:94067:75"/>
                     <head>OBJECTION IV.</head>
                     <p>Object.4. <hi>Ay but</hi> Salus Populi eſt Supre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma Lex:
<hi>So as I may act voluntarily with and under an uſurped Power, though againſt legal ſettlements and known Laws for the preſervation of the Common-wealth, and that by a Law of neceſſity, which gives the Law to all Laws, and warrants the doing of that which otherwiſe is unlawful; for by this our Saviour ſeems to juſtifie his Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciples gathering Ears of Corn on the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath-day, and urges the Authority of</hi> Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid's <hi>Example for it.</hi>
                        <note n="n" place="margin">Mat. 12.</note>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. It is true that <hi>Salus Populi eſt Suprema Lex,</hi> in reference to Humane and Municipal Laws; for ſo Kings, in whom the Supreme and Legiſlative Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er reſides, may for the good of their People, in great Exigents, act beſides, nay againſt the known National Laws of their Kingdom, but not contrary to any Divine Sanction.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Anſw.</hi> 2. I acknowledg that neceſſity is a very powerful Argument, both be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God and man, to excuſe (not juſtifie) an ill Action: For ſo God himſelf, the Supreme Law-giver, hath ſometimes been pleaſed in a Gracious Condeſcenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to man's infirm condition, to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence <pb n="142" facs="tcp:94067:76"/> with his own Laws, as well as Kings with theirs, in Caſes of great ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity, as may be inſtanced. But this hath been ever in things only <hi>[mala quia prohibita]</hi> evil becauſe forbidden; as in Ceremonial and Judicial Laws; never in any thing that is
<hi>[malum in ſe, &amp; prohibitum quia malum,]</hi> evil in it ſelf, and forbidden becauſe ſpecifically ſo: Such as are Schiſms, Hereſies, Idolatry, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion, Uſurpation, Oppreſſion, Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, Sacriledg, and the like; for in theſe God never leaves his Servants without a juſt way of extricating themſelves from any ſuch neceſſity of acting, by enabling them to dare to dye rather than do any thing that in its nature is evil. and, by ſuffering according to the Will of God, to commit the keeping of their Souls to him in well-doing, as unto a faithful Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor:<note n="o" place="margin">1 Pet. 4.19.</note> Otherwiſe no man ſhall ever have the Honour and Reward of ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for and with his Saviour, nor have means to manifeſt and exerciſe his Faith, Patience, Fortitude, Perſeverance in well-doing, and many other Graces.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Anſw.</hi> 3. For the Example brought out of the twelfth of <hi>Matthew,</hi> to prove the human lawfulneſs of doing an unlawful thing in caſe of neceſſity, only to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve a ſingle perſon, (as in <hi>David</hi>) which <pb n="143" facs="tcp:94067:76"/> 
                        <hi>a fortiori,</hi> from the leſs to the greater, muſt be the more juſtifiable for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of a Common-wealth: It ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears that our Saviour doth approve of his Diſciples in gathering the Corn on the Sabbath, by
<hi>David</hi>'s Example as it was made lawful by an Humane Neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, in a Ceremonial Precept only. Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſs, as Lord of the Sabbath, he did then cancel the duty of that Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monial Law of not gathering any thing upon that day, as appears by the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>text.</p>
                     <p>Yet our Saviour in citing <hi>David</hi>'s eat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Shew-bread, did not free <hi>David</hi> from the breach of a Ceremonial Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept, (For the Text ſaith expreſly, it was not lawful for him, nor thoſe with him to eat it, but only for the Prieſts,) but urgeth it for the illuſtration of Gods Indulgence and Mercy to the frailty of his nature in ſo great a Humane ſtrait un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Law, in a thing only <hi>malum quia prohibitum;</hi> that they might the leſs wonder at his compaſſionating his Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciples weakneſs, in taking that they might conceive to be againſt a Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nial Precept only, and that under the Goſpel, for the relief of nature in an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremity.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="5" type="objection">
                     <pb n="144" facs="tcp:94067:77"/>
                     <head>OBJECTION V.</head>
                     <p>Object. 5. <hi>Well, but if it be not lawful to comply voluntarily with an <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurped Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, by which I may be ſaid to give it coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance and reputation, may I not yet act under it in things good or indifferent in their own nature, when they are command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed under a Coercive Penalty; and that for the preſervation of my ſelf and Poſterity, which the Law of God, Nature, and Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons oblige to?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Anſw.</hi> A Paſſive Submiſſion to the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Power may in ſome ſuch Caſes be lawful. For I am not bound to tempt a Temptation, nor, with the <hi>Porpus,</hi> to ſeek and hunt the ſtorm, where it may be honeſtly avoided; ſelf-preſervation being ſo natural, as by inſtinct it catch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth at any thing, that may but ſtay or ſupport it; as a Hop for want of a Pole will claſp and embrace a Nettle to ſtay it from falling. But here we muſt be cautious, and diſtinguiſh between the acting of a Magiſtrate and other inferior Employments, which perhaps may be preparatory only to ſome Adminiſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Juſtice, or yet of leſs importance. Yet in caſe of Magiſtracy we muſt di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſh <pb n="145" facs="tcp:94067:77"/> between Cauſes Criminal and meerly Civil. For,</p>
                     <p n="1">1. In Cauſes Criminal, where Blood is by the Law required to expiate the Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, I conceive it wholly unlawful to act, in that they muſt derive their Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion for it from them, who have a juſt Power of conveying it by Divine Commiſſion and the known Laws; or elſe they do not take but wreſt and force the Sword out of God's hand: and he that ſo ſheds mans blood with it, by man ſhall his blood be ſhed; in that he doth it without any lawful call, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out which no man can act but in a pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate capacity; and then it were mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der in any to kill a Murderer: and he that as a Magiſtrate will do a thing that requires the juſt Influence of Supreme Power to make it lawful, doth tacitely own that Power to be in him or them from whom he derives his Power to act. Eſpecially in the Method of proceeding againſt Malefactors in Criminal Cauſes, where the frame of the Inditement and reading the Commiſſion muſt be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood an owning a juſt Power to be in them from whom they derive theirs; in that no private perſon or Community of men, unleſs combined into a lawful Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, ever had the Power of Life <pb n="146" facs="tcp:94067:78"/> and death in them. For it is by that Power only men juſtly ſuffer; (not the Law, which is only a Regulation of the exerciſe of it;) ſo as any man may preſs the deſert of death againſt a Wicked Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lefactor by the Law, as preparatory to Sentence and Execution, but muſt not be active in the latter without a juſt Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion, in that all men ought to act in a lawful poſture and ſubordination only. For if the Power Originally be invalid, it cannot derive a juſt one, by vertue of which men may operate; no more than a ſulphurous Spring can ſend forth a ſweet ſtream; for, with <hi>Ariſtotle, Quod deeſt in cauſa deeſt in effectu.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="2">2. In caſes meerly Civil, between Party and Party, I am ſomething doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful how to determine, if compelled to accept of a place of Judicature; though perhaps in ſome Caſes I may be morally bound (from the Object it points at) to act, without any outward force upon me, in the name (not vertue) of the Uſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, where the thing is intrinſically good, or hath the countenance of ancient and known Laws, but never to the countenan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing or upholding of the Power; ſo as I may act under, but not for it in ſuch caſes. And in others, when I have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed and reſiſted it, as far as I can with <pb n="147" facs="tcp:94067:78"/> ſafety to my Perſon and Fortune, I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive I have taken off all matter of juſt ſcandal of giving any countenance to the preſent Power, and rather ſhew my diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>approving of it; when force and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulſion only hath determined my choice, and that only to a ſubmiſſion, in reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to the Power that is upon me, (but not to any juſt Authority in the Impoſer, which Conſcience would ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lige unto.)</p>
                     <p>Nor do I in this conſider my ſelf veſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in any juſt capacity for the doing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny diſtributive Juſtice, ſo as to force a Conſcientious Submiſſion from any to my Determinations, but only as an Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitrator to mediate a juſt end of differen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, which the neceſſity of the times (all other Channels, by which Juſtice as a ſtream ſhould derive to us, being wholly obſtructed) enforces all men to a volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary and free ſubmiſſion unto.</p>
                     <p>And therefore with theſe Limitations it may perhaps be lawful, ſo as neither by Oath or Acting, I own the exerciſe of the Supreme Power as juſt in them that aſſume it, nor endeavour to coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance or ſupport it; which Cautions all Callings of men, eſpecially Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioned Officers, are to obſerve under an unlawful and uſurped Power, that poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſes <pb n="148" facs="tcp:94067:79"/> only an uſufructuary and guber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>native one to rule, without any juſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priety in the Legiſlative Power, to which none can pretend, but ſuch as are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioned by God according to his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed Will, and poſſeſs their Titles by a lawful and civil Right. For in an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawful poſture of ſubordination none can have a juſt Power derived. Though (as I ſaid) perhaps in ſome caſes, where I am morally bound to a thing intrinſically good, I may act in the name (not Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er) of the Uſurper. Neither do thoſe abuſed Texts<note n="p" place="margin">Rom. 13. 1 Pet. 2.13.</note> oblige us further; for God cannot breath hot and cold in the ſame words, <hi>i. e.</hi> countenance Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion under a pretence of lawful Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. Laſtly, For other inferiour em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployments; in things abſolutely in their own nature lawful, men may, as an Act of Submiſſion under a Power, comply paſſively; (though no Beam of any juſt Power appear in the Perſon command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing;) ſo as it be involuntary, and with a publick owning the diſlike of it.</p>
                     <p>Nay there may be perhaps a voluntary and yet lawful acting in ſome ſuch Capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cities in things of, an inferior nature, when men do it rather by permiſſion of than commiſſion from the Uſurpers of the
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:94067:79"/> Supreme Power, having their Call only from the ancient and known Laws of the Kingdom, as Conſtables, Bailiffs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="6" type="objection">
                     <head>OBJECTION VI.</head>
                     <p>Object. 6. <hi>Well, if it be not lawful to countenance or any way ſupport an unjuſt Power, it is not lawful to pay Taxes, Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoms, Exciſe,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>when impoſed, and to maintain a War againſt a Juſt Title.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Anſw.</hi> Every Voluntary Act herein is ſinful, and not to be done; in that the matter, manner, and end ought to be good in every Action. And in this caſe, though it may be in ſome caſes lawful to ſubmit to ſuch Payments, I ought ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to dye than do any thing willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that may advance thoſe ends for which it is deſigned.</p>
                     <p>But then if the demand of it comes ſeconded with a Power and direction to levy ten times as much if refuſed, the ſtate of the queſtion is altered and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rects me to an act of prudence in chooſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the leſs evil of puniſhment, (which will be rather a weakening than ſtrength to the Uſurper, who would make an advantage by my refuſal,) without con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracting the guilt of the Tyrants miſap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying <pb n="150" facs="tcp:94067:80"/> it. For the compulſion in the Law it ſelf looks only at the money, not the employment of it, and directs my choice to what is leaſt penal; and takes off all juſt cauſe of ſcandal, when my in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions in paying are as far diſtant from his in receiving as Heaven from Hell. And though this particular caſe be hardly to be found amongſt the Caſuiſts, it is thus reſolved in other Notions; to which I will propoſe a Parallel or two for illuſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion (never queſtioned or condemned by any I ſuppoſe as unlawful) having Univerſal Conſent and Practiſe for it. But firſt I ſhall anſwer another Obje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="7" type="objection">
                     <head>OBJECTION VII.</head>
                     <p>Object. 7. <hi>It is true, every Act hath only ſo much of ſin as it hath of the will in it; but here what you do cannot be ſaid to be meer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Paſſive, or Involuntary, but a mixed Action, partly conſtrained and partly free, and ſo in ſome meaſure ſinful, as involving your conſent.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Anſw.</hi> I confeſs man in all things works as a rational Creature, and doth nothing but of choice; his will being never for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, as Natural Agents are, from the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulſe of a Foreign Power; ſo that it is <pb n="151" facs="tcp:94067:80"/> his choice not neceſſity which fixes him, be the thing in its nature eligible or not: but this happens not in this caſe; For if the queſtion were whether I would pay Taxes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to the ends pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed, or looſe all, I ought to part with all, and my Life too, rather than do it.</p>
                     <p>But if it be reduced to this: Will you give me ſo much money, or let me take all you have, or ten times as much? then the choice is meerly between evils of puniſhment, in which the Law of Nature obliges me in prudence to chooſe the leaſt; as alſo the Law of Charity; and is ſo univerſally underſtood to free me both from ſcandal and ſiniſter inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretations; Compulſion in Law never implying more than ſubmiſſion to the Act: and then when all Power of reſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance is taken from me, and no liberty of Election left, whether I will part with ſo much Money or not; but that my liberty is limited to one Object only, the evil of ſuffering in a leſs or greater degree; I may pay the Money aſſeſſed without any check of Conſcience, in <hi>ſenſu diviſo,</hi> abſtracted from all ill, but not in <hi>ſenſu compoſito,</hi> as parting with it to a ſinful end.</p>
                     <p>
                        <pb n="152" facs="tcp:94067:81"/>Nor doth the intention of the Impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers (though it binds not in Uſurped Powers) extend further than to our ſubmiſſion to the payment of the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney they require; (though they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare the end for which they intend it) or elſe to undergo the Penalty they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire; as may appear by all the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances of theſe times. And for Parallels to this,—</p>
                     <p n="1">1. Conſider, That if Thieves aſſault me upon a way, and ſwear to kill me, if I will not give them a Bond for an hundred pounds, to be employed for the corrupting of ſome Virgins Chaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, or other Wicked end, and will have it inſerted in the Conditions I am to ſubſcribe, I ought not to do it for a World.</p>
                     <p>But if the condition be only to pay ſo much Money, I may yield to it as a ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom for my life. For it then becomes a choice of the leaſt evil of puniſhment only, (without countenancing or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracting any evil of ſin;) which I am ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged to by the Law of ſelf-preſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, eſpecially when my Actions declare no more.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. Conſider, If a lawful King, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puting his juſt Rights againſt the actual Invaſion of his Rebellious Subjects,
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:94067:81"/> ſhall place all his Treaſure and Magazines in ſome ſtrong Garriſon, there to be kept as the Nerves and Sinews of his War, as Pillars and Supports of his Royalty, and intruſt them into ſome Loyal hand to keep and defend them for his Service, they cannot be delivered up to his Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies (to prove his Maſters Ruine when deſigned for his ſtrength) without great ſin, till held and diſputed beyond all pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bability of longer defence, or hope of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief, becauſe ſomething of his Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigns Intereſt remains ſtill in his Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er.</p>
                     <p>But when it can be no longer kept by force, it is a duty upon him, both for the preſervation of himſelf, and the Loyal Party with him, to ſurrender upon Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitulation, rather than become a wilful Sacrifice; all Election being taken from him but that of the leſs evil of puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, when he only parts with what he cannot keep, to preſerve himſelf for ſome fairer opportunity of ſerving his King, which proportion holds in our pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Taxes, when the demand is ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conded by a Compulſory Power.</p>
                     <p>For there Natural Equity permits a Paſſive Submiſſion; and in things not abſolutely neceſſary by Divine Sanction, as in obſerving the Rules and Canons of <pb n="154" facs="tcp:94067:82"/> the Church, in Ceremonies, Forms of Prayer, and Liturgies, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> For there O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſions are no acts of Contempt, nor juſt cauſe of ſcandals, if we are forced to it.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="8" type="objection">
                     <head>OBJECTION VIII.</head>
                     <p>Object. 8. <hi>Well, admit that it be not lawful voluntarily to obey, but paſſively on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to ſubmit to the Impoſitions of thoſe that uſurp an unjuſt Power, I may yet (to ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome my perſon in caſe of reſtraint or Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſonment, and to enjoy the benefit of Laws and protection of the preſent Government) engage to be true and faithful to them, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than to continue both in Miſery and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>capacity of ever paying that Tribute of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage and Allegiance I owe my juſt Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign, either in aiding or aſſiſting to the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery of his juſt Rights.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Anſw.</hi> In this caſe, Faithfulneſs imply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Truſt, Duty, and Active Obedience, (as in the <hi>Revelations, Be faithful unto Death, and I will give thee a Crown of Life;</hi> and ſo underſtood in Common No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions) you ought not to do it. For though you cannot pay the Debt of an Opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Allegiance to the right Owner, it is not in your Power to transfer his Right to another; the Duty of Subjects to their Kings, deriving from God's Precept, <pb n="155" facs="tcp:94067:82"/> not Man's Donation; ſo as it falls not under the conſideration of things Arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, Obedience being ſimply good or evil, as it is objected.</p>
                     <p>And therefore all I conceive we can do in this caſe lawfully, is but the giving of a Negative Aſſurance not to act any thing againſt them, ſo long as we remain under their protection; which once made, we ought to be faithful in the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving, till our condition be enlarged by Exchange, Ranſom, or ſome other way of Providence, which ever pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumes the means to be lawful, as well as the end good. For this is but a ſubmiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to my fate, with an Improvement of my Condition, no reſtraint of my Power; (but the exerciſe of it for a time) a prudent Election of the leaſt evil of Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, without any Ingredient of the evil of ſin: For ſo we may keep Loyal, and ſtrengthen in the Habit, when ſuſpend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the Act, and interrupted in the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtation of the Duty; a wrong poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>de facto,</hi> never cancelling the Owners right
<hi>de jure,</hi> but engages all honeſt mens Compaſſions to the oppreſſed, and Prayers for their reſtitution; and not, with the <hi>Pagan Indians,</hi> to worſhip the Devil, <hi>ne noceat;</hi> or for the Temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Greatneſs or Power.<note n="q" place="margin">Mat. 4.</note> So as <pb n="156" facs="tcp:94067:83"/> our Oaths and Engagements muſt be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways, as the
<hi>Caſuiſts</hi> determine, 1. <hi>Super re licita.</hi> 2. <hi>In bonum finem.</hi> 3. Never <hi>contra pactum aliquod prius initum;</hi> which the equity of the thing and ſome juſt occaſion may again call me to upon a former tye or Obligation; for if other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe taken they engage us only to an hearty Repentance for having taken them.</p>
                     <p>And all this we ought to do out of an humble and reverential awfulneſs to the Perſon and Commands of our King, not ſervile Affection, (as not conſiſting with a noble and ingenuous nature) but a filial one, iſſuing from love: For this is grounded upon the Law of Nature, and ſhould be filial, as Power it ſelf is Paternal.<note n="r" place="margin">Lev. 19.3. Pro. 14.21.</note> And therefore my Son, (ſaith
<hi>Solomon</hi>) fear God and the King; for as the King to God, ſo the Subjects are to the King, and he is a middle thing in regard of juſt Power, between them and God. Nay, he is ſo much Gods (nay God to us) in regard of the imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate Power and delegation he hath from God, (that <hi>Joſephus</hi> to diſtinguiſh Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchical Government from all others framed by men, calls it <hi>Theocratie,</hi> that of God) which, in the Inventory of all Bleſſings of this life, was by <hi>Eze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiel</hi> 
                        <pb n="157" facs="tcp:94067:83"/> accounted the greateſt: (<hi>Ezek.</hi> 16.3.) And, as a Beam from the Sun, it is ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeparable from the perſon, where it is once legally ſetled in a King and his Progeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, as it is with us, (owned both by the Articles of our Church, Canons, Homilies, Laws, and Oaths, both of Supremacy and Allegiance) that nothing but death can divide them.</p>
                     <p>For though ſome Kings have been de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed by Rebellions, and others forced to reſign their Crowns, as <hi>Edward</hi> the Second, (ſee <hi>Baker</hi>'s Chronicle) they were never diveſted of the Habit of Power <hi>(de jure)</hi> but only deprived of its exerciſes <hi>(de facto:)</hi> And though that of Reſignation, can hardly be juſtifiable in any caſe, it ought never to be done but to his lawful Succeſſor, (as it was in the Inſtance mentioned) without throw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing off God, (as in the rejection of <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muel</hi>) where his Providence had other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes ſettled the Right; in that where the Divine Conſtitution hath placed the Supremacy in any, God ſtill expects from him a juſt managing of that Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er for the advancement of his Glory, and good of his people, which he can never caſt off, no more than a Father, Wife, or Child can diſcharge themſelves from
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:94067:84"/> the mutual duty, of thoſe Relations, ſo long as they continue.</p>
                     <p>Nor is this ſlightly to be paſſed over when the ſingle duty of fear, due to the King,<note n="s" place="margin">Eccl.
12.13.</note> is comprehenſive of all others; for as Love, it is a Catholick Grace, runs through all our Actions, and is a Watch upon them for their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gulation; or, as the Life and Soul that animates them; and the more it is free, the more it dilates to ſhew it ſelf, (ſaith <hi>Irenaeus</hi>) in juſt duties; and makes our Filiation under the Goſpel of much more liberty than the condition of Servants under the Law, as it imports a volunta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Reverence or Worſhip: for ſo Fear and Reverence in the Language of the Spirit ſpeak the ſame thing.<note n="t" place="margin">Eccl. 1. Pſ. 5.7. compared with Pſ. 132.7. Pſ. Pſ. 95. Mal. 1.6.</note>
                     </p>
                     <p>But to teſt our ſelves in this duty, we may know it by our fear of God, which includes it; as God will know (that is take notice of) our fear of him, by that to our Superiours. As in <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice, where though intuitively and eternally he knew that
<hi>Abraham</hi> feared him, yet he would not own it, but from the evidence of his outward expreſſions:<note n="u" place="margin">Gen. 22.13.</note> And thus our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour would only take notice of St. <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi>'s love to him by feeding his Flock, <pb n="159" facs="tcp:94067:84"/>
                        <note n="w" place="margin">Joh. 2 P. 17.</note> though he well knew his Affections before, which was alſo the reaſon of <hi>Job</hi>'s Tryals.<note n="x" place="margin">Job. 1.</note>
                     </p>
                     <p>Nor is this a ſlight Argument, (as a Reverend Divine obſerves) but ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon an impregnable Reaſon and Syl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logiſm framed by the Spirit of God,<note n="y" place="margin">1 Joh. 4.</note> who concludes by a Topick rule, That if we love not the general Image of God in our Brethren, whom we do ſee, we cannot love God whom we do not ſee, but in ſuch Shadows and Repreſentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. And if by my want of Affection and Charity to my Brother, and the fruit of it, God concludes againſt my love to him, he will do it much more for the want of our duty of fear to our King, (who is not only his general, but the particular and peculiar Image of his Divine Power and Glory, to whom fear is originally due,) which made <hi>Jacob</hi> to ſay of his Lord <hi>Eſau,</hi>
                        <note n="z" place="margin">Gen. 32.10.</note> 
                        <hi>vidi faciem ut faciem dei:</hi> And <hi>Moſes,</hi>
                        <note n="a" place="margin">Num.
16. Exo. 16.8.</note> Your murmurings are not <hi>contra nos ſed contra</hi> Jehovam.</p>
                     <p>Nay, thus God himſelf ſaith of the ten Tribes revolt,<note n="b" place="margin">2 Chr. 13.8.</note> they reſiſted the Kingdom of God in <hi>David</hi>'s Son; and to <hi>Samuel,</hi>
                        <note n="c" place="margin">1 Sam. 8.7.</note> 
                        <hi>non te ſed me.</hi> So as our failings in this, or any other way to our <pb n="160" facs="tcp:94067:85"/> Prince, is a diſobedience to God himſelf, as their hearts are ſaid to be in his hands by appropriation. Therefore, my Son, (ſays he, not Sons) give me thy heart,<note n="d" place="margin">Pro. 24.21.</note> in exchange for thoſe many hearts I have ſubmitted unto you, when you ſhall appear in Power and Majeſty; and this to ſpeak the near ground of Relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons between God and his Vice-gerent; and inſtruct us that we ought to be Sons to the King in our Duties, if we will be Heirs to God, and Inheritors of his Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry.</p>
                     <p>For as in that where he ſaid, The Poor ye ſhall have always among you, Chriſt did not only foretel but propoſe it, as a Glaſs to repreſent God's bounty to us, and an Object for the exerciſe of ours to him; ſo in promiſing Kings ſhould be our Nur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing-Fathers, he doth as it were promiſe us ſome Beams of his Majeſty and Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs ſhould ſhine through that Glaſs, and always be amongſt us, for the comfort of his people, and commands our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flections of Gratitude and Obedience to himſelf in them.</p>
                     <p>For when we look upon the Actions of Kings, we terminate not our ſelves in their perſons, but the power of God working in them, (when lawfully de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted:) <pb n="161" facs="tcp:94067:85"/> which makes the Schooles call Rebellion Sacriledge, in that King's Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons are ſacred, and that God is oppoſed and violated in them, who hath given them a right of propriety in Power, (not an uſufructuary one only) ſuch as one King may gain in another's Kingdom by a juſt War; yet of right he ought only to hold it till Reparation be made for the firſt Injury done, and the Expence he hath been forced upon for the Vindication of himſelf and his Rights.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="9" type="objection">
                     <head>OBJECTION IX.</head>
                     <p>Object. 9. <hi>But if a Nation be invad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, when under an <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurped Power, (by a Foreign King or People) without either juſt Title or Ground of War, I ought to aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurper in the defence of it.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Anſw.</hi> In this Caſe I ought only to joyn with any Force to defend my ſelf and the Kingdom againſt any ſuch Inva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, ſo as I neither fight for the Uſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per's Intereſt and Eſtabliſhment, nor a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thoſe of my lawful Soveraign.</p>
                     <p>But out of this Bough many Branches ſpring, that afford Fruit of excellent taſte and nouriſhment, could I but gather and
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:94067:86"/> preſs them; but I leave them for an abler hand, and period my Lines and the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der's trouble in what I have expreſt al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready.</p>
                     <p>In which Reſolutions, if I have been too ſevere and rigid, I ſhall willingly and readily retract my errour upon the Evidence and Conviction of better Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons: For I only hold forth this Glow-worm-ſhine, and little twilight, to afford ſome glimmering in theſe benighted times, by which men may gueſs at the way they ſhould chooſe to walk in, (though difficult and rugged) and to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voke ſome of the great Luminaries, who had a fixation in the Orb of our late glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Church; or other Orthodox Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines (Stars too, though of a leſſer mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitude) to ſend forth ſome clearer Beams and more wholeſom Influences, both to guide and refreſh us in this Wilderneſs we walk in: (inhabited rather by Beaſts than rational Creatures:) there being no ſubject more proper and uſeful to theſe times, wherein, if we ſhould but ſee <hi>Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genes</hi> in his buiſie ſearch, and ask what he ſtrove to find, he would anſwer, <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minem quaero.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Nay, I confeſs I am wholly excentrick in my motion, being out of my own <pb n="163" facs="tcp:94067:86"/> Sphere; and have nothing but Pious In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions, and a Holy Zeale (for a <hi>Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chel</hi>'s Mantle) to cover this weak Eſſay with, and to hide it from the ſevere cenſure of a more exact Inquiſition. On<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the Rule I propoſe to my ſelf, is, in all doubtful and controverted Caſes of Conſcience, to determine in that which is the ſtricteſt, and hath moſt of ſelf de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nial in it, in regard of the proneneſs of Man's Nature to ſtrain his Fetter and paſs his Bounds; and becauſe the leaſt ſin (like the falling of the firſt drop in the Orifice, or the firſt Sand in the Hour-Glaſs) diſpoſeth to and prepares the way for more; and many times, if allowed, proves the moſt dangerous, in that it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers more to Infinity it ſelf, and grows into Habits, becauſe repeated without notice or purpoſe of limitation; when great devaſtating Sins Allarms the Soul to a ſpeedy diſcounting them by repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, and as great Fiſh-bones, that are not eaſily ſwallowed, ſtick in the mouth and are ſpit out again.</p>
                     <p>How Conſcientious then ought we to be in every Action, ſince the doing of an Act, good in it ſelf, becomes ſin to me, if I be not fully perſwaded of the law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs of it, and the Complyance with
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:94067:87"/> others in any thing that is evil in it ſelf (though I do believe it lawful) makes their ſin become mine. For ſo St.
<hi>Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine</hi>
                        <note n="e" place="margin">Serm. 6. de verb. dom.</note> ſaith, the Scriptures do attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute to one what he acts by (or approve of in) another's perſon: Thus the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet attributes the Murder of <hi>Naboth</hi> to <hi>Ahab,</hi> in ſaying, <hi>Thou haſt killed him:</hi>
                        <note n="f" place="margin">3 King. 20.</note> becauſe he diſallowed it not when done; though it was not he, but <hi>Jezabel,</hi> that contrived and acted it without his knowledge: And thus the <hi>Jews</hi> are charged by St. <hi>Peter</hi> to have killed the Lord of Life; though they did it not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctually, nor was it lawful for them (as they confeſſed) to put any man to death; yet their guilt was more than the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans,</hi> in that they had Malice in their hearts to proſecute it, when the other had hands only dipt in his Blood.</p>
                     <p>Therefore walk (ſaith the Apoſtle) with all Circumſpection, or Preciſeneſs, as the word bears it)<note n="g" place="margin">Eph. 5.15. <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap>.</note> recoyling from all ſorts of Evils in their firſt approach; as the Blood in the Body will do from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny apprehended danger, to fortifie the moſt vital parts. For if we muſt account for every vain thought,<note n="h" place="margin">Jam. 4. Jer.
4.14.</note> (though thought be ſo near nothing as no man can think what it is) how ſhould we a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>void <pb n="165" facs="tcp:94067:87"/> the leaſt act of ſcandal to our Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, or complyance in the moſt mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nute ſin, when the ſmalleſt ſins many times prove more dangerous than great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, (as is before expreſſed:) For like Worms they get inſenſibly into the heart of the Fruit, and deſtroy it; when the great Birds, that fall upon the Tree, are watched and driven away.</p>
                     <p>Thus ſmall Diſtempers many times kill, where a ſtrong Feaver would not; in that they infuſe their Venom by gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle inſinuations, not to be diſcovered, when the other by Aſſaults gives Allarm to our watchfulneſs. Nay, great ſins diſcounted, or not repeated, are not ſo dangerous as the leaſt, multiplyed with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out our care or notice; in that (as I ſaid) they refer more to infinity it ſelf, when augmented without purpoſe of limitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. For thus our pale-fac'd, weak (but repeated) ſins, become many times more deadly, than our ſcarlet and impudent ones repented of.</p>
                     <p>Therefore let us be ſo far from making little account of great ſins, as to make great account of little ones. For if the owning or patronizing the leaſt minute Atom, aiery ſin, be ſo dangerous, and (when alone) ſits in State, and draws a <pb n="166" facs="tcp:94067:88"/> whole Train of Vices after it; what hope is there of thoſe men, who, on the contrary, are ſo far from making great account of little ſins, as they make little or no account of great ones; and yet aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume the diſguiſe of Piety, as the hating of Idolatry, when they commit Sacriledg.<note n="i" place="margin">Rom. 2.22.</note> by it, and their Hpocriſie, making them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves more guilty than they could be in the thing they abhor? For (as one ſays wittily) the Idolater is but miſtaken in his God, the other thinks God is miſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in him; the one diſhonours, the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther undeifies his God. Yet the men of our times, who make themſelves the only Church of God, and reprobate thoſe who are of the true Church, are not only guilty of this, but many other crying ſins; which they not only Act, but Enact, as a Law; as Blood-ſhed, Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion, Prophanation of God's Rights and Ordinances; by which you may know them not to be yet born of God,<note n="k" place="margin">1 Joh. 3.</note> for thoſe ſin not, (not ſuch great known ſins, not with a deliberate pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to ſin.)</p>
                     <p>And therefore let us neither adhere to their Perſons, (how ſeemingly holy ſoever they are in other things) nor countenance that Cauſe, that cauſes ſo <pb n="167" facs="tcp:94067:88"/> many crying Diſorders and Impieties. For, (as St. <hi>Cyprian</hi> ſaith) <hi>ea non eſt Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligio, ſed diſſimulatio, quoe per omnia non conſtat;</hi> when as Religion teacheth us to walk in an orderly, ſincere, univerſal, and uniform obſervance of all God's re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed Will, and ſo walking to perſevere. For they (and they only) who are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant unto death ſhall enjoy a Crown of Life; which I heartily wiſh to the greateſt Enemies of God, our juſt Cauſe, and our Perſons; beſeeching God, that (though they ſend us through a red Sea of our own Blood to our Heavenly <hi>Canaan,</hi> and, with
<hi>Mahomet</hi>'s Tomb, hang us between Heaven and Earth, as unworthy of ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther) they may yet become Inſtruments of reſtoring Peace and Truth in this Kingdom, and account thoſe fair and ſpotleſs Lillies greater Ornaments to th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Garlands, than all their Roſes of Bloody Trophies. And that they may make God and the Kingdoms good the only Centre and Circumference of all their Thoughts, Words, and Actions; truly repenting of their Sins, that by Gods Mercy they may obtain Pardon for them, and not be left in hardneſs of Heart, Blindneſs and Impenitence, (a Judgment beyond all Judgments, as it is <pb n="168" facs="tcp:94067:89"/> a Judgment that hath no ſenſe of Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and yet hath both Sin and Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in it.) And though they have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved all Law into the Sentence of the Sword, and almoſt all Goſpel into the private whiſpers of a ſeducing Spirit, God in Mercy keep them from the deſtruction of the one, and afford them Mercy in the other for their Conviction and Amendment; and let not the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Lethargy of Sin any longer ſtupi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie their Conſciences, but awaken them to an active endeavour of repairing their Errours, and reſtoring of God's Truth, that their Souls may be ſaved.</p>
                     <p n="5">5. Laſtly, Prayer is the great Out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent and Homage the Subject, as a duty, ows his Soveraign.</p>
                     <p>Now as Prayer is the top-Branch of all our Duties to God, and the moſt prevail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Oratory for his Bleſſings upon a Nation, we muſt pray for them as men, but firſt as Kings, that we may lead a peaceable and quiet life under them, in all Godlineſs and Honeſty.<note n="l" place="margin">1 Tim. 2.</note> And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in the practice of that Duty I ſhall wind up my Diſcourſe,</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <p>
                  <pb n="169" facs="tcp:94067:89"/>Humbly beſeeching God, that as he hath given us a <hi>Caeſar</hi> for Piety exemplary, for Prudence as an Angel of God, knowing both good and evil, who by day as a Cloud, and as a Pillar of Fire by night, doth go before us to direct, comfort and refreſh us in all our weariſom marches and hard ſufferings; not refuſing to wade through another red Sea, though tinctured with his own Blood, for the regaining and maintaining of Truth and Peace amongſt us; that God would give us Grace truly to value ſo great a Bleſſing in our King; and for his Fatherly Kindneſs to us, to pay all filial Obedience to him. And let us ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ceaſe humbly to pray thee, O Lord, ſtill to eſtabliſh the Crown upon the Head of him and His Poſterity, till <hi>Shiloh</hi> come.</p>
               <p>Plead thou this Cauſe of our King, O Lord, (or rather thine own Cauſe) and fight a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thoſe that fight againſt Him; hate them not ſo much, as not to ſeem to hate them at all, (by letting them ſtill proſper in their Wickedneſs;) but correct them, to amend them here, that they may not be condemned hereafter; and make Him the more Pious by His Preſſures, the more juſt by their Oppreſſions, and every way the better for, and more glorious by His Sufferings.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="170" facs="tcp:94067:90"/>Make His Enemies as the Duſt before the Wind, and the Angel of the Lord ſcat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering them; but upon His Head let His Crown ever flouriſh.</p>
               <p>And thou, who art the Supreme Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, ſo temper thy Juſtice, we beſeech thee, as to make thy Strokes become Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies to Him, that He may read thy favour in thy frowns, and not turn thy Rod into a Serpent, thy Antidote into Poyſon,) but make thou it, like <hi>Aaron's,</hi> in the end to bud, and bring forth the bleſſing of a happy Peace to Him and us.</p>
               <p>Yet let Him not ſo value Peace as to prefer it to Truth; (for a juſt War is better tban an unjuſt Quiet,) but as His and our Sins have let in one, ſo make our Sufferings by, and Sorrows for them, to fit us for the Bleſſing of the other; and us by following Righteouſneſs to find a happy reſt.</p>
               <p>In the mean time, ſanctifie and preſerve Him from all the Artificial <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderminings and open Violence of Bloody and Wicked Men; prepare him for all Events, and give him an holy uſe of all thy varied Judgments, and make Him to make a pious advantage of His Enemies, and they to become His beſt Friends; when by ſucking the Venom and Poyſon out of their Injuries, He can (by a <pb n="171" facs="tcp:94067:90"/> charitable forgiveneſs) turn them, through God's Mercies, into the richeſt Cordial Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, to refreſh His Soul with in His great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Conflicts and Faintings.</p>
               <p>And ever give Sentence with Him (O God) and defend His Cauſe againſt the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ngodly: Let not the Juſtice of it ſink under the weight of the Sins of His Party, nor the not only acted (but enacted) Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion, Sacriledge, <hi>and</hi> Oppreſſion of His Enemies, ſeparate any longer betwen them and thee, nor us from one another, but unite us all in inward Affections, and the Bond of an outward Peace; and that we may maintain truly zealous hearts to our God, Loyal to our Soveraign, and loving one towards another.</p>
               <p>Protect Him by thy Power againſt all His Adverſaries, guide Him by thy Grace in all His Actions, bring him to His Throne again with Happineſs, Safe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and Honour; re-eſtabliſh Him in all His iuſt Rights, and grant that all thoſe committed to His charge may lead a peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able and quiet life under Him, in all God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs and Honeſty: and that as He hath always defended thy Faith, ſo thy Faith may ſtill defend Him; and He make it His Endeavours to reſtore thy Worſhip to its ancient Purity, thy Church and Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters <pb n="172" facs="tcp:94067:91"/> 
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="173" facs="tcp:94067:91"/> 
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <pb n="172" facs="tcp:94067:92"/> to their ancient Glory, and Him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf and Kingdom to a happy and eſtabliſhed Peace.</p>
               <p>And for this end, calm (O Lord) the raging of the Sea, and the madneſs of His Pepole; bound their Paſſions; turn their outward Form into the ſubſtance of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; let all their Schiſms end in a Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table Accord, their Errours in Truth, their Rebellion in Loyalty; that as they have requited Him Evil for Good, and Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred for His Good-will, they may now have hearts to repent of their Evils done, and he one to forgive thoſe he hath ſuffered by them.</p>
               <p>Still preſerve Him a Faithful Servant to thee (though His Subjects be falſe to Him) and ready to undergo the greateſt In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juries, rather than to conſent to the leaſt Sin: Give Him a heart to part with all for thee, but nothing of thine; and though they would <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n-King Him by their Demands, let Him not <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n-man Himſelf in His Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſcentions; (depoſe the juſt Soveraignty of Reaſon in Himſelf,) nor prefer any pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation to that of His own Conſcience; but in all things to preſerve His Subjects juſt Rights, without enſlaving Himſelf or His.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="173" facs="tcp:94067:92"/>Make thy Will (O Lord) the Rule of His, and thy Glory and thy Self the Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tre and Circumference of all His Thoughts, Words, and Actions: Give Him a free ſubmiſſion to thee in all Events; extricate Him from all His troubles; carry Him through all Difficulties; increaſe in him all ſaving Graces; ſubdue in Him all Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions; pardon all His Sins; ſanctifie unto Him all Afflictions; guide him in all His wayes; ſupply Him in all His wants; lay no more upon Him than He may be able to bear, but with the Temptation give Him a means to eſcape, even the Snares of Sin and Malice of His Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies: and make Him not only be ready to ſuffer, but to dye for the name of <hi>JE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SUS;</hi> in Affections and Habit ever, yet never in Act, a Martyr, unleſs for the advancement of thy Glory and His, by one dying Man to make many living Saints, to encreaſe the joyes of the Saints in Heaven, though it would take from us the greateſt upon Earth.</p>
               <p>Give Him (O Lord) a dry Victory over all His Enemies, and not the Temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of a Bloody Conqueſt: But if by thoſe Iſſues thou wilt recover our weak and dying State, come again with healing in
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:94067:93"/> thy Wings, and once more reſtore what we have loſt, and give what is want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the manifeſtation of thine own Glory. So be it, Lord JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S,</p>
               <trailer>Amen. Amen.</trailer>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:94067:93"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
